[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "In traditional machining, which component is made of relatively harder material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tool",
            "b) Work piece",
            "c) Holding device",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tool should be harder than work piece in order to cut the work piece according to the required geometry."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "For machining to take place, tool should be penetrated into work piece to a certain _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Height",
            "b) Depth",
            "c) Length",
            "d) Width"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chips are removed only when certain depth is given."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which motion is responsible to determine the geometry of jobs to be machined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only Motion of tool",
            "b) Only motion of work piece",
            "c) Relative motion between tool and work piece",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Relative motion between the above mentioned components are required for machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Turning is done on which type of surfaces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat surfaces",
            "b) Cylindrical surfaces",
            "c) Irregular surfaces",
            "d) Spherical surfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Turning is generally used to produce cylindrical surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Shaping and Milling are used to generate which one of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cylindrical surfaces",
            "b) Flat surfaces",
            "c) Irregular surfaces",
            "d) Spherical surfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: They are used for generation of flat surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Drilling is used to produce which type of geometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slots",
            "b) Holes",
            "c) Profiles",
            "d) Keyways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Drilling is one of the processes which are used to produce holes."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "As the temperature increases, what happens to material’s strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) increases and then decreases",
            "d) remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the temperature increases, materials lose their strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "As the temperature is increased, ductility is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) increased",
            "b) decreased",
            "c) increased and then decreased",
            "d) remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As temperature increases, ductility of material is also increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "In abrasive machining __________ are used to form the tool.",
        "Options": [
            "a) iron particles",
            "b) grains and grits",
            "c) steel alloy particles",
            "d) aluminium particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Grains are used as abrasive particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Abrasive machining is used when __________ is needed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cutting",
            "b) Roughing",
            "c) Finishing",
            "d) Drilling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grains are used for finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Non-Traditional machining is recommended when we need which of the following features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex shapes",
            "b) High surface quality",
            "c) Low-rigidity structures",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For above requirements this machining is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Non-Traditional machining can also be called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contact Machining",
            "b) Non-contact machining",
            "c) Partial contact machining",
            "d) Half contact machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tool and work piece are at a distance apart in this type of machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "In which of the following industries, Non-traditional machining methods play an important role?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Automobile",
            "b) Aerospace",
            "c) Medical",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Non-traditional methods are used widely in many industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Different classifications of Non-traditional machining based on source of energy are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical",
            "b) Thermal",
            "c) Chemical and electro-chemical.",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It can be classified into the above mentioned categories."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "In mechanical machining, material is removed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erosion",
            "b) Corrosion",
            "c) Abrasion",
            "d) Vaporization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Abrasive grains remove material by mechanical erosion in USM."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Material in thermal machining is removed by which of the following means?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vaporization",
            "b) Melting",
            "c) Electro-plating",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this machining, heat is the source of energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Which of the following process comes under mechanical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) USM",
            "b) EDM",
            "c) LBM",
            "d) PAM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: USM removes material by mechanical erosion."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Surface defects that may be occurred during thermal machining are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro cracking",
            "b) Heat affected zones",
            "c) Striations",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During thermal machining surfaces defects occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Sources used in thermal machining are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ions",
            "b) Plasma",
            "c) Electrons",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different sources are used to remove the materials accordingly."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Vacuum is the machining medium for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LBM",
            "b) WJM",
            "c) EBM",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vacuum is the medium for Laser Beam Machining and Ion Beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "In chemical machining is material removal takes by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical reaction",
            "b) Erosion",
            "c) Electron removal",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chemical machining removes material by chemical reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of hybrid machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultrasonic Machining",
            "b) Electron Beam Machining",
            "c) Ultrasonic assisted electrochemical machining",
            "d) Laser Beam Machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: More than one phase is used to combine to form hybrid machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Who discovered USM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Balamuth",
            "b) Paul O Flawer",
            "c) Turing",
            "d) Steve John"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Balamuth was the scientist, who discovered Ultrasonic Machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "What is the full form of USM in advanced machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultrasound manufacturing",
            "b) Ultrasonic machining",
            "c) UV spectrum manufacturing",
            "d) Ultra sonar machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Full form of USM in advanced machining processes, is Ultrasonic machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "USM removes materials using the ____________ tool.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perpendicularly rotating",
            "b) Perpendicularly oscillating",
            "c) Axially oscillating",
            "d) Inclined oscillating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Material is removed using axial oscillating tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Which is softer material in USM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tool",
            "b) Work piece",
            "c) Tool & Work piece",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tool is softer than work piece in USM."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Frequency of tool’s oscillation in USM ranges between ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-10 kHz",
            "b) 10-15 kHz",
            "c) 18-20 kHz",
            "d) 25-50 kHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Frequency used in USM is between 18 – 20 kHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Amplitude of oscillation of tool in USM ranges between ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1-10 μm",
            "b) 10-40 μm",
            "c) 50-100 μm",
            "d) 100-1000 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: The optimal range used is between 10-40 μm."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "In which year, discovery of USM took place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1910",
            "b) 1925",
            "c) 1943",
            "d) 1945"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ultrasonic Machining was discovered in 1945."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The machining system of USM contains which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetostrictor",
            "b) Concentrator",
            "c) Tools and slurry",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In machining system of USM, the above mentioned components have to be present."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Of the following scientists, who discovered magnetostrictor effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Balamuth",
            "b) Steve O Flawer",
            "c) Joule",
            "d) Turing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To oscillate, magnetostrictor must be energized to ultrasonic frequency in USM."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "In Ultrasonic Machining, magnetostrictor converts magnetic energy into which type of energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical energy",
            "b) Electrical energy",
            "c) Thermal energy",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This effect was discovered by Joule in 1874 at Manchester."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "What is the value of the amplitude obtained without mechanical amplifier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0001 – 0.001 µm",
            "b) 0.001 – 0.1 µm",
            "c) 1 – 10 µm",
            "d) 10 – 100 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oscillation of magnetostrictor takes place by converting magnetic energy to mechanical energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "What is the value of the amplitude obtained when we use mechanical amplifier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 10 µm",
            "b) 10 – 40 µm",
            "c) 40 – 50 µm",
            "d) 50 – 100 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Relatively very small amplitudes are obtained without amplifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "At what rate slurry is pumped through nozzle in USM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 L/min",
            "b) 25 L/min",
            "c) 50 L/min",
            "d) 75 L/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Relatively larger amplitudes are obtained when amplifier is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "By which of the following means, material is removed in USM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical abrasion",
            "b) Microchipping",
            "c) Cavitation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Ultrasonic Machining, material is removed by any of the above means."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of contribution of cavitation to the total material removed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <5%",
            "b) 5 – 10 %",
            "c) 10 – 20 %",
            "d) 20 – 50 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cavitation contributes to only less than 5 % of total material removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "In the following mechanisms, which one is dominant in material removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hammering",
            "b) Cavitation",
            "c) Microchipping",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hammering is dominant mechanism in material removal of USM."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "When machining porous material, which type of mechanism is introduces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasion",
            "b) Erosion",
            "c) Corrosion",
            "d) Vaporization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Material removal of porous material takes place by erosion."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "The rate of material removal depends on which of the following features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency",
            "b) Static Pressure",
            "c) Machining area",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Material removal rate depends on all the above mentioned factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the features of tool affecting MRR in USM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hardness",
            "b) Wearability",
            "c) Accuracy",
            "d) Mounting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both machinability and MRR depends on brittleness of material."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "What is the machinability rate of glass by USM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 75%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different features of tool also affect the material removal in USM."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "What happens to MRR with increase in tool amplitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As amplitude of the tool increases, rate of material removal increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The vibration amplitude determines, which parameter of the abrasive particles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Force",
            "b) Torque",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amplitude determines the velocity of abrasive particles between tool and work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Amplitude of the oscillation ranges between which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.04 mm",
            "b) 0.04 – 0.08 mm",
            "c) 0.08 – 0.10 mm",
            "d) 0.10 – 0.20 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Splashing occurs if amplitude is very high which in turn decreases the material removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "As the vibration frequency increases, what happens to material removal rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Increase and then decrease",
            "d) Decrease and then increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Optimum value of the amplitude of the tool will vary between 0.04-0.08 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used as an abrasive carrying medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Benzene",
            "c) Glycerol",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Up to a certain limit of vibration frequency, MRR increases and after that it decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "If there is an increase in viscosity of slurry, what happens to MRR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Any of the above liquids can be used as abrasive carrying medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "How much percent of the abrasives are recommended in general for abrasive medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 15 %",
            "b) 15 – 20 %",
            "c) 25 – 30 %",
            "d) 30 – 35 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As viscosity is increased, material removal rate is decreased."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "As the tool area increases, what happens to MRR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In practice, volumetric concentration of abrasives used range between 30 – 35 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "When the static pressure of the feed is increases, what happens to MRR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Increase up to a limiting condition",
            "d) Decrease up to a limiting condition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In USM, Machining rate increases as the mentioned ratio decreases and vice-versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Which of the following distribution factors, does not affect the machining parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side wear of tool",
            "b) Abrasive wear",
            "c) Accurate feed",
            "d) Form error of tool"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inaccurate feed is the factor that affects the accuracy of machining parts."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which one of the following factors affects the accuracy of parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steady abrasive flow",
            "b) Accurate feed",
            "c) Unsteady abrasive flow",
            "d) Ultrasonic frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Unsteady and uneven abrasive flow affects the dimensional accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Options": [
            "3. State whether the statement is true or false.",
            "“Hole oversize measures the difference between hole diameter measured at the bottom surface, and the tool diameter.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oversize measures the difference of the hole diameter measured at top surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "While machining W4C and glass, tool over cut size when compared to mean grain size is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two times greater",
            "b) Two times smaller",
            "c) Three times greater",
            "d) Three times smaller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tool over cut size is 2 or 4 times greater than mean grain size."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "While machining B4C, tool over cut size when compared to mean grain size is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two times greater",
            "b) Two times smaller",
            "c) Three times greater",
            "d) Three times smaller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tool over cut is 3 times greater than mean grain size while machining B4C."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "In the following USM accuracy levels are limited to which value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.01 mm",
            "b) ± 0.05 mm",
            "c) ± 0.10 mm",
            "d) ± 0.50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Ultrasonic Machining the dimensional accuracy levels are limited to ± 0.05mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Conicity resulting after machining by Ultrasonic Machining can be reduced by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct injection of slurry",
            "b) Tools having negative taper",
            "c) High static pressure",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Conicity can be reduced by above means and also by using wear resistant tools, finer abrasive particles etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Typical roundness error in graphite, resulted due to lateral vibrations is between?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 01 – 20 μm",
            "b) 20 – 60 μm",
            "c) 60 – 100 μm",
            "d) 100 – 150 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The roundness is between 20 – 60 μm while machining graphite by Ultrasonic Machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Typical roundness error in glass, resulted due to lateral vibrations is between?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 01 –20 μm",
            "b) 20 – 40 μm",
            "c) 40 – 140 μm",
            "d) 150 – 250 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The roundness is between 40 – 140 μm while machining graphite by Ultrasonic Machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors affect the surface finish of machined parts in Ultrasonic Machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Material",
            "c) Tool surface",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The above factors influence the surface quality of the machined parts in Ultrasonic Machining very significantly."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "What is value of surface finish achieved, when we use the abrasive of grit number 240?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.08 μm",
            "b) 0.08 – 0.13 μm",
            "c) 0.13 – 0.25 μm",
            "d) 0.25 – 0.38 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The surface roughness obtained, when machined using abrasive of grit number 240, is between 0.25 – 0.38 μm."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "When the viscosity of liquid carrier is increased, the surface quality of the parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased",
            "b) Decreased",
            "c) Remained same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the viscosity of the liquid carriers reduces we can obtain smoother surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Ultrasonic Machining can be used for which of the following processes and applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drilling",
            "b) Sinking and contouring",
            "c) Polishing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ultrasonic Machining can be used for drilling holes, sinking, contouring and many more wide variety of applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "What is the limit of surface area that is to be machined using USM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <100 mm2",
            "b) <500 mm2",
            "c) <1000 mm2",
            "d) <1500 mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the surface area to be machined is above 1000 mm2, this type of machining will not be apt for the parts."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Drilling in Ultrasonic Machining is done, by which motion of the tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only rotation",
            "b) Only oscillation",
            "c) Oscillation and rotation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process, which uses USM for drilling, is known as Rotary Ultrasonic Machining (RUM)."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "In which of the following materials, Rotary Ultrasonic Machining can be used to drill holes through them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Alumina",
            "c) Ferrite",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rotary Ultrasonic Machining can be used to drill holes in the above mentioned materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Options": [
            "5. State whether the following statement is true or false.",
            "“Rotary Ultrasonic Machining is the process in which, interrupted drilling of small-diameter holes takes place.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rotary Ultrasonic Machining is the process in which, uninterrupted drilling takes place unlike traditional drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "On which of the following features of cavity, will the penetration depth depend on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth",
            "b) Diameter",
            "c) Size",
            "d) All of the mentioned."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Penetration rate depends on cavity’s depth and size of the cavity i.e.., area and volume, which can be determined by diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is the value of depth in Ultrasonic sinking, after which, material removal becomes difficult?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 2 mm",
            "b) 2 to 5 mm",
            "c) 5 to 7 mm",
            "d) 7 to 10 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: After a depth of 5 to 7 mm, in USM sinking, material removal becomes very difficult."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "In production of EDM electrodes, typical ultrasonic speeds, in graphite ranges between?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.10 cm/min",
            "b) 0.10 – 0.25 cm/min",
            "c) 0.25 – 0.40 cm/min",
            "d) 0.40 – 1.40 cm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Typical ultrasonic speeds used are between 0.4 – 1.4 cm/min, used in producing EDM electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "How much is the value of surface finished, achieved using Ultrasonic Polishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 μm",
            "b) 0.3 μm",
            "c) 0.5 μm",
            "d) 0.7 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using Ultrasonic Polishing, very low values of surface finish can be obtained, which may be very low as 0.3 μm."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "In Micro-Ultrasonic Machining, which of the following component vibrates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tool",
            "b) Work piece",
            "c) Feed pipe",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike the normal Ultrasonic Machining, Micro-USM utilizes the work piece’s vibration and the rotation of the tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "In Micro-USM, using WC tool, what is the value of diameter can be achieved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 μm",
            "b) 3 μm",
            "c) 5 μm",
            "d) 7 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diameter value up to 5 μm can be achieved, using Micro-ultrasonic machining on glass, silicon and quartz materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "What is the full form of WJM in advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water Jack Manufacturing",
            "b) Water Jet Machining",
            "c) Water Jet Manufacturing",
            "d) Water Jack Manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of WJM is water jet machining in advanced machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "What is the key element of water jet machining for material removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tool Holder",
            "b) Work piece",
            "c) Water jet",
            "d) Power source"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water jet is the one, which is used to cut the work piece and to remove material."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "What is the velocity of water jet stream in water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 m/sec",
            "b) 300 m/sec",
            "c) 700 m/sec",
            "d) 900 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Velocity of water jet stream that is used in Water jet machining is about 900 m/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of machining system of Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transducer",
            "b) Accumulator",
            "c) Jet cutting nozzle",
            "d) Hydraulic pump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transducer is not a part of Water jet machining and other components come under WJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "What is the general power rating of the hydraulic pump, used in WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 kW",
            "b) 20 kW",
            "c) 30 kW",
            "d) 40 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The power rating of the motor of hydraulic pump, which is used in WJM is about 30 kW."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the components of intensifier present in water jet machining system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Piston",
            "b) Plunger",
            "c) Limit switch",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The above mentioned components are present in the intensifier of water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Intensifier increases the pressure water by which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 100 MPa",
            "b) 100 – 200 MPa",
            "c) 200 – 400 MPa",
            "d) 400 – 1000 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Use of intensifier is to increase the inlet water pressure to 200 – 400 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "On which property of water, will the accumulator in Water jet machining rely on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density",
            "b) Compressibility",
            "c) Viscosity",
            "d) Velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Accumulator relies on compressibility of water (12% at 3800bar), in order to maintain a uniform discharge pressure in WJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "What are the values of typical tube diameters in the machining system in WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 1 mm",
            "b) 1 to 6 mm",
            "c) 6 to 14 mm",
            "d) 14 to 25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Typical tube diameter values range between 6 to 14 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "What is the expected life of the nozzles used in WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 hrs",
            "b) 20 hrs",
            "c) 100 hrs",
            "d) 200 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The life that is expected from the nozzle, which is a part of machining system, is 200 hrs."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not damage the nozzle used in Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Particles of dirt",
            "b) Mineral deposits",
            "c) Water",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Only dirt particles and mineral deposits are responsible for damage of nozzle."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "What are the uses of catcher in machining system of Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collecting dirt",
            "b) Collection of debris",
            "c) Reduce noise levels",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Catcher in WJM is used to collect the dirt, machined debris and reduce the noise levels."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Distance between which components, is the stand-off distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nozzle-inlet and work piece top",
            "b) Nozzle-outlet and work piece-top",
            "c) Nozzle-inlet and work piece-bottom",
            "d) Nozzle-outlet and work piece-bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stand-off distance is the distance between top of work piece and nozzle outlet."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "What is the value of diameter of the jet cutting nozzle in WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.1 mm",
            "b) 0.1 – 0.3 mm",
            "c) 0.3 – 0.7 mm",
            "d) 0.7 – 1.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In WJM, diameter of the nozzles range between 0.10 – 0.30 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "What is the value of stand-off distance in Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 1 mm",
            "b) 1 – 2 mm",
            "c) 2 – 6 mm",
            "d) 6 – 14 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stand-off distance value ranges between 2.5 – 6 mm in Water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "What are the values of jet velocities in Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 – 200 m/s",
            "b) 200 – 500 m/s",
            "c) 500 – 1500 m/s",
            "d) 1500 – 3000 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Velocity of the water jet stream ranges between 540 – 1480 m/s in WJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Options": [
            "5. State whether the following statement is true or false.",
            "“As the pump pressure increases, depth of cut decreases in Water jet machining.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the pump pressure is increases, the depth of cut also increases in WJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "What is the value of material thickness of work piece in WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 – 0.25 mm",
            "b) 0.8 – 25 mm",
            "c) 50 – 100 mm",
            "d) 100 – 500 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The material thickness value of work piece range between 0.8 – 25 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "What is the value of feed rate in Water Jet Machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0001 – 0.025 m/min",
            "b) 0.05 – 0.25 m/min",
            "c) 0.5 – 200 m/min",
            "d) 200 – 500 m/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Water jet machining, value of the feed rate ranges between 0.5 – 200 m/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "In WJM, what are the properties of jet fluid that affect the MRR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity",
            "b) Flow rate",
            "c) Viscosity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the mentioned properties above, of jet fluid affect the MRR in Water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Which of the following property/ies of nozzle does not affect the material removal rate in Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material",
            "b) Diameter",
            "c) Outside temperature",
            "d) Stand-off distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the nozzle, outside temperature has no effect on the rate of material removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "In the following materials, Water jet machining can be used on which type of material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metals",
            "b) Plastics",
            "c) Ceramics",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: WJM can be used on metals, cloth, paper, plastics, food, leather, and ceramics."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "What are the processes and applications, where Water jet machining can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cutting",
            "b) Drilling",
            "c) Deburring",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Water jet machining can be used for drilling, cutting, deburring, surface treatment and many more applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "What is the tolerance limit range of thin materials in WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.1 mm",
            "b) ± 10 mm",
            "c) ± 25 mm",
            "d) ± 50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Water jet machining, the range of tolerance is ± 25 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "In cutting of rocks using water jet machining, which type of pressure is needed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low pressure",
            "b) Medium pressure",
            "c) High pressure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In WJM, very high pressures and velocities are needed while cutting rocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "In deburring, which combination removes the material from non-metallic materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High pressure and low flow rate",
            "b) High pressure and high flow rate",
            "c) Low pressure and low flow rate",
            "d) Low pressure and high flow rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For non-metallic materials high pressure and lower flow rates are used in deburring."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials has some drawbacks of cutting WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Food",
            "b) Rocks",
            "c) Fibre-reinforced plastics",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water gets deflected due to the fibre embedded in the matrix of fibre-reinforced plastics when we use WJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "What is the accuracy level obtained when PCB’s are cut by WJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.05 mm",
            "b) ± 0.13 mm",
            "c) ± 0.26 mm",
            "d) ± 0.33 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In WJM, accuracy obtained in cutting of PCB’s is ± 0.13 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "In WJM, surface treatment includes which type of processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removing deposits",
            "b) Removing chemicals",
            "c) Degreasing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Surface treatment is done using WJM to clean the surface from many toxic chemical, deposits, residues etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "In how many directions, can the cutting takes place in Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uni-directional",
            "b) Bi-directional",
            "c) Multi-directional",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water jet machining has multi directional cutting capacity i.e.., in any direction in three dimensional space."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "In Water jet machining, cuts can be started at which place of workpiece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) From left",
            "b) From right",
            "c) From middle",
            "d) From any point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In WJM, cuts can be started from any point on the workpiece."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Options": [
            "3. State whether the following statement is true or false.",
            "“To start the cuts in Water jet machining, pre-drilled holes are not necessary.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Water jet machining, we need not require any pre-drilled holes to start the cuts."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burr produced is minimal",
            "b) No Heat is produced",
            "c) Relatively low hourly rates",
            "d) Environmentally safe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Costs per hour are relatively high in Water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Which of the following secondary processes are eliminated in Water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grinding of surface",
            "b) Surface treatment",
            "c) Polishing of surface",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tool does not wear in water jet machining, so it need not be sharpened."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "How many parts are cut using Water jet machining, on a single blank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One part",
            "b) Two parts",
            "c) Three parts",
            "d) Multiple parts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the mentioned secondary processes above, are eliminated in Water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrow kerf width",
            "b) Small diameter of nozzle",
            "c) Not suitable for mass production",
            "d) Burr is minimal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Depending up on the kerf width, multiple parts can be machined using a single blank."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of AJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Automatic Jet Manufacturing",
            "b) Abrasive Jet Machining",
            "c) Automated Jet Machining",
            "d) Abrasive Jet Manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of AJM is Abrasive jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "In AJM, which of the following materials are used as abrasive grains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Al2O3",
            "b) SiC",
            "c) Glass beads",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, any of the particles mentioned above can be used as abrasive grains."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "In Abrasive jet machining, work piece material of removed by which of the following means?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vaporization",
            "b) Electro plating",
            "c) Mechanical abrasion",
            "d) Corrosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Abrasive particles hit the surface with high pressure and high velocities, which removes the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Which type of materials can be machined using Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Ceramics",
            "c) Hard materials",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Materials like ceramics, glass, hard and super hard materials can be machined using Abrasive jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "In machining system of AJM, which is the medium of carrying the abrasive grains for machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquids",
            "b) Gases",
            "c) Any fluids",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In AJM, different types of gases are used as the medium for carrying abrasives."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "In machining system of AJM, what is/are the gas/es used for carrying the abrasives?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2",
            "b) Air",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In AJM, gases like CO2, air or nitrogen are used to carry the abrasives."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "What is the pressure of gas that is to be supplied, for carrying the abrasives?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 1.0 kg/cm2",
            "b) 2.0 to 8.0 kg /cm2",
            "c) 10.0 to 18.0 kg/cm2",
            "d) 25.0 to 35.5 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pressure of the carrying gas should range between 2 to 8 kg/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which of the following gas, should never be used as the carrier of abrasives?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen",
            "b) CO2",
            "c) Oxygen",
            "d) Air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Oxygen should not be used as carrier because it causes a violent chemical reaction with abrasives or work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "What is the frequency of mixing chamber, consisting of gas and abrasives?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 Hz",
            "b) 30 Hz",
            "c) 50 Hz",
            "d) 70  Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mixing chamber consisting of carrier gas and the abrasive grains, vibrates at a frequency of 50 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "In Abrasive jet machining, what may be the size of the abrasive grains used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 40 µm",
            "b) 50 – 100 µm",
            "c) 100 – 150 µm",
            "d) 200 – 300 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Abrasive grains of size, between 10 – 40 µm can be used for machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "What are the processes where Abrasive jet machining can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleaning",
            "b) Cutting",
            "c) Deburring",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Abrasive jet machining can be used for deburring, cutting, cleaning and for many other heavy duty applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Options": [
            "12. State whether the following statement is true or false.",
            "“In Abrasive jet machining, commercial grades powders can be used for machining.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For AJM, commercial grade powders are not used because their sizes are not classified widely."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "In machining system of AJM, which of the following controls the relative motion between work piece and nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cam drives",
            "b) Pantographs",
            "c) Trace mechanisms",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Relative motion in Abrasive jet machining can be controlled by the above mentioned means."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Masks, which are used to confine the jet stream location on work piece are made of, which type of materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper",
            "b) Glass",
            "c) Rubber",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Masks can be made of any of the above-mentioned materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "In AJM, what is the mechanism of removal of material from the work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corrosion",
            "b) Abrasion",
            "c) Electron transfer",
            "d) Vaporization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, the removal of material takes places by mechanical abrasion, using abrasive grains."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "In AJM, abrasive jet from the nozzle follows, which type of path for a short distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel",
            "b) Inclined",
            "c) Perpendicular",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Abrasive particles follow a parallel path for short distance and then flare outward."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following components, influence the material removal rate in Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nozzle",
            "b) Carrier gas",
            "c) Abrasive grains",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the components mentioned above, influence the rate of material removal, directly or indirectly."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "In the following properties of nozzle, which of them does not influence the MRR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size",
            "b) Wear",
            "c) Outside temperature",
            "d) Distance from work piece"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The outside temperature of nozzle has no influence on the material removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "In the following properties of abrasive grains, which of them changes rate of material removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size",
            "b) Strength",
            "c) Shape",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The above mentioned properties of abrasive grains influence the material removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "As the abrasive flow rate increases, what happens to the volumetric removal rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Increase and then decrease",
            "d) Decrease and then increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In AJM, volumetric removal rate increases up to a level and then decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "What is the value of abrasive grain flow rate in Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 2 g/min",
            "b) 3 – 20 g/min",
            "c) 30 – 56 g/min",
            "d) 68 – 85 g/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Abrasive grain flow rate is between 3 – 20 g/min, in AJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "What must be the velocity of the carrier gas that carries the abrasive particles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 50 m/sec",
            "b) 50 – 150 m/sec",
            "c) 150 –300 m/sec",
            "d) 300 – 500 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Velocity of abrasive carrier gas must be between 150 – 300 m/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "What is the value of carrier gas flow rate in Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 L/min",
            "b) 17 L/min",
            "c) 28 L/min",
            "d) 39 L/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, the flow rate of abrasive carrier gas is around 28 L/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Which of the following material/s cannot be used for making of nozzle in Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten Carbide",
            "b) Steel alloy",
            "c) Sapphire",
            "d) Synthetic sapphire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nozzle in Abrasive jet machining is made up of sapphire or WC."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of the following values, does the diameter of the nozzle lies between?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.10 mm",
            "b) 0.30 – 0.50 mm",
            "c) 0.70 – 0.90 mm",
            "d) 1.10 – 1.50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In AJM, Diameter of the nozzle ranges between 0.30 – 0.50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "What is the life of Tungsten carbide material nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 8 hrs",
            "b) 2 – 5 hrs",
            "c) 10 – 15 hrs",
            "d) 25 – 40 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nozzle made up of WC material has a life period which range between 10 – 15 hrs."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "In AJM, what is the life of synthetic sapphire material nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 hrs",
            "b) 300 hrs",
            "c) 500 hrs",
            "d) 700 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nozzle made up of synthetic sapphire material has a life period which is about 300 hrs."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance limit values in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.01 mm",
            "b) ± 0.03 mm",
            "c) ± 0.05 mm",
            "d) ± 0.07 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, tolerance limit values range between ± 0.05 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "In AJM, surface roughness value will vary between which values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.10 µm",
            "b) 0.15 – 1.5 µm",
            "c) 2.0 – 5.0 µm",
            "d) 7.0 – 10.0 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface roughness value in AJM varies between 0.15 – 1.5 µm, depending on grain size."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Which of the following, are the processes and applications in which Abrasive jet machining can be applied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drilling",
            "b) Cutting",
            "c) Deburring",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Abrasive jet machining can be used for cutting, drilling, deburring and cleaning processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "In Abrasive jet machining, intricate shapes and holes are machined on which type of materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brittle",
            "b) Thin",
            "c) Difficult to machine",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Without affecting the conductor, both stripping and cleaning are done, by using Abrasive jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false, about Abrasive jet machining.",
            "“Using Abrasive jet machining, micro deburring of hypodermic needles can take place.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Abrasive jet machining is used to machine, intricate shapes and holes in brittle, thin and difficult to machine materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "What are the type of materials that can be machined using Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Sapphire",
            "c) Quartz",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Abrasive jet machining can be used for micro deburring of hypodermic needles."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "What is the amount of material utilizes when we machine parts using Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, the above mentioned materials can be machined, which are heat sensitive and brittle."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "After how much time tool has to be changed in AJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 hr",
            "b) 2 hrs",
            "c) 5 hrs",
            "d) No tool change required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, material utilization is very high since it removes material by using abrasives."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "By using Abrasive jet machining, how much amount of hardening does the materials experience?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No hardening",
            "b) Very less hardening",
            "c) Average hardening",
            "d) High hardening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, tool changes are not required."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which type of materials cannot be machined using Abrasive jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soft materials",
            "b) Hard materials",
            "c) Difficult to machine materials",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Abrasive jet machining, hardening is not experienced by the machined materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials in Abrasive jet machining can be a health hazard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasive grains",
            "b) Air carrier",
            "c) Silica dust",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Soft materials such as candy bars, thin softwood etc.., cannot be machined using AJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "In AJM, air filters are used to remove which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moisture",
            "b) Oil",
            "c) Other dust particles",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silica dust, that occurs after machining can be a health hazard in AJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Automated Water Jet Machining",
            "b) Automated Water Jet Manufacturing",
            "c) Abrasive Water Jet Machining",
            "d) Abrasive Water Jet Manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Full form of AWJM is Abrasive Water Jet Machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "What are all the types of materials, which can be machined using AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Ceramics",
            "c) Concrete",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hard to cut materials, which are mentioned above, can be machined using Abrasive water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "When was Abrasive water jet machining developed first?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1942",
            "b) 1958",
            "c) 1974",
            "d) 1980"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Abrasive water jet machining was first developed in the year 1974."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "When compared to the conventional machining, how much times faster, is the Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 times",
            "b) 10 times",
            "c) 15 times",
            "d) 20 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Abrasive water jet machining is 10 times faster than the conventional machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of the abrasives and water in the mixture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20% water and 80% abrasives",
            "b) 80% water and 20% abrasives",
            "c) 30% water and 70% abrasives",
            "d) 70% water and 30% abrasives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Abrasive mixture consists of 70 percent water and 30 percent abrasives."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "What are the materials used for abrasives in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SiC",
            "b) Corundum",
            "c) Glass beads",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All of the materials mentioned above can be used for making abrasives in Abrasive water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "In the machining system of AWJM, which one accelerates the abrasives to remove material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water only",
            "b) Water jet stream",
            "c) Feeder",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Water jet stream accelerates abrasives but not the water only, to remove material."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "What is the grain size of abrasive particles, which are often used for Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.50 µm",
            "b) 10 – 150 µm",
            "c) 200 – 500 µm",
            "d) 500 – 1000 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compressed air increases the pressure energy of the jet stream, which enhances the material removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "How is the material removed in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vaporization",
            "b) Electron transfer",
            "c) Corrosion",
            "d) Erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Grain size of the abrasive particles range between 10 – 150 µm in Abrasive water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the feed mechanism of the abrasives in AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Side feed",
            "b) Cross feed",
            "c) Central feed",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only side feed and central feed are used in Abrasive water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "In Abrasive water jet machining, how are the abrasives fed into the water jet stream?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suspension",
            "b) Injection",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Abrasives are fed into the water jet stream through suspension or injection."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What is the use of delivery system in the machining system of AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To deliver colloidal solution",
            "b) To pump water",
            "c) To fed abrasives",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Abrasive water jet machining, water delivery system is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Of the following components, which one does not come under the machining system of AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water delivery system",
            "b) Transducer",
            "c) Cutting nozzles",
            "d) Mixing chambers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transducer is the component which does not come under the machining system of AWJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "In Abrasive water jet machining, intensifier is used to deliver which type of pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low pressure",
            "b) Low pressure",
            "c) Medium pressure",
            "d) High pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In AWJM, intensifier is used to deliver high pressure water using pistons with it."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "In mixing chamber of AWJM, which of the following are mixed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasives and colloidal solution",
            "b) Abrasives and water jet",
            "c) Colloidal and water jet",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In mixing chamber, abrasives and water jet stream are mixed."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Of the following, which one is a type of suspension in AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct pumping",
            "b) Indirect pumping",
            "c) Bypass pumping",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are three different types of suspension AWJ formed by indirect, direct and bypass pumping."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "In machining system of AWJM, mixing chamber is immediately followed by which of the following component?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Focusing tube",
            "b) Cutting Nozzle",
            "c) Intensifier",
            "d) Water delivery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Abrasive water jet machining, mixing chamber is immediately followed by the focusing tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Which of the following energies are absorbed using the catchers in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure energy",
            "b) Kinetic energy of abrasives",
            "c) Residual energy",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In AWJM, catchers are used to absorb the residual energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of the following are different types of catchers used in AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water basin type",
            "b) Submerged steel balls type",
            "c) TiB2 type",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The above mentioned types are the types of catchers used in AWJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a process parameter of Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency of vibration",
            "b) Orifice diameter",
            "c) Pressure",
            "d) Stand-off distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency of the vibrations does not belong to the parameters of Abrasive water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following come under the process parameters of the Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasive size",
            "b) Machine impact angle",
            "c) Traverse speed",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the parameters mentioned above come under Abrasive water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "What is the value of orifice diameter in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.03 mm",
            "b) 0.03 – 0.09 mm",
            "c) 0.10 – 0.30 mm",
            "d) 0.30 – 0.90 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of diameter of the orifice should range between 0.10 – 0.30 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Of the following values, between which of them pressure value will range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 – 1500 bar",
            "b) 1500 – 2500 bar",
            "c) 2500 – 4000 bar",
            "d) 4000 – 10000 bar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Abrasive water jet machining, pressure value will range between 2500 – 4000 bar."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "When compared to sand, how much effective is garnet as abrasive material in AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20%",
            "b) 30%",
            "c) 40%",
            "d) 50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Garnet, which is commonly used abrasive material is nearly 30% more effective than sand in Abrasive water jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false about Abrasive water jet machining.",
            "“A material, whose material removal rate is higher, produces larger surface roughness.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As rate of material removal increases in AWJM, large surface roughness are produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Surface roughness depends on which of the following parameters in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece material",
            "b) Grit size",
            "c) Abrasive type",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the parameters mentioned above, are responsible for variation in surface roughness."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "What is the value of focusing diameter in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 0.6 mm",
            "b) 0.8 – 1.4 mm",
            "c) 1.6 – 2.8 mm",
            "d) 3.2 – 5.2 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diameter value of WC focusing tube in AWJM varies between 0.8 – 1.4 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Abrasive flow value in Abrasive water jet machining will range between which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.1 kg/min",
            "b) 0.1 – 1.0 kg/min",
            "c) 1.0 – 10 kg/min",
            "d) 10 – 100 kg/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In AWJM, abrasive flow ranges between 0.1 – 1.0 kg/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "What is the value of stand-off distance in Abrasive water jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0 – 2.0 mm",
            "b) 2.0 – 4.0 mm",
            "c) 4.0 – 6.0 mm",
            "d) 6.0 – 10.0 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stand-off distance in Abrasive water jet machining will vary between 1 – 2 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Impact angle in Abrasive water jet machining range between which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0&#176 to 10&#176",
            "b) 10&#176 to 30&#176",
            "c) 30&#176 to 90&#176",
            "d) 90&#176 to 100&#176"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Machine impact angle in AWJM will range between 30&#176 to 90&#176."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Of the following values, between which values traverse speed will range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 5 m/min",
            "b) 5 to 100 m/min",
            "c) 100 to 500 m/min",
            "d) 500 to 1000 m/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Value of traverse speed ranges between 5 to 100 m/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Depth of cut values in Abrasive water jet machining ranges between which values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 2 mm",
            "b) 2 to 250 mm",
            "c) 300 to 500 mm",
            "d) 650 to 900 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of depth of cut in AWJM ranges between 2 to 250 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "In the existing advanced machining processes, what is the full form of IJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ice Jet Manufacturing",
            "b) Ink Jet Manufacturing",
            "c) Ice Jet Machining",
            "d) Ink Jet Machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Full form of IJM is Ice jet machining in advanced machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "In Ice jet machining, the abrasive particles used for material removal are replaced by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica particles",
            "b) Ice particles",
            "c) Fluids",
            "d) Colloidal solutions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Ice jet machining, the abrasive particles are replaced by ice particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "When compared to Abrasive water jet machining, how are the material removal rates in Ice jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) High",
            "d) Remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Ice jet machining, material removal rates are relatively low when compared to AWJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false about Ice jet machining.",
            "“Water can be reused in IJM, unlike that of AWJM and WJM.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unlike that of AWJM, water can be reused in Ice jet machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the components of machining system of IJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High pressure pump",
            "b) Ice particle generator",
            "c) Ultrasonic Atomizer",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the components mentioned above are present in the machining system of IJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Which of the following component will be present just after the cooling coil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High pressure pump",
            "b) Ice particle generator",
            "c) Cutting nozzle",
            "d) Ultrasonic Atomizer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Prior to nozzle water is cooled by coils that is submerged in liquid nitrogen."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Ice particles of size <500 µm are produced by which of the following process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stream freezing",
            "b) Ice particles supply",
            "c) Normal cooling",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ice particles of size <500 µm are produced by using stream freezing."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Ice particles of size >500 µm are produced by which of the following process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stream freezing",
            "b) Ice particles supply",
            "c) Normal cooling",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ice particles of size >500 µm are produced by ice particles supply."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "In Ice jet machining, stand-off distance value varies between which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0 – 2.0 mm",
            "b) 2.0 – 3.0 mm",
            "c) 3.0 – 5.0 mm",
            "d) 5.0 – 10.0 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Value of the stand-off distance ranges between 3.0 – 5.0 mm in IJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "What is the value of diameter of nozzle that is used in Ice jet machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.175 mm",
            "b) 0.425 mm",
            "c) 0.548 mm",
            "d) 0.654 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of diameter of nozzle in Ice jet machining is about 0.175 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Ultrasonic atomizer used in ice particle generator, produces water droplets at which rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 ltr/hr to 1 ltr/hr",
            "b) 2 ltr/hr to 12 ltr/hr",
            "c) 20 ltr/hr to 35 ltr/hr",
            "d) 40 ltr/hr to 65 ltr/hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Atomizer produces droplets at the rate 2 ltr/hr to 12 ltr/hr."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "What are the advantages of Ice jet machining over the other advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Environmentally safe",
            "b) Cost reduction",
            "c) No heat affected zone",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Advantages of Ice Jet Machining are mentioned above when compared to other processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of ice jet machining when compared to AWJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Environmentally safe",
            "b) Cost reduction",
            "c) Low material removal rate",
            "d) No heat affected zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When compared to AWJM, IJM has lower material removal rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the processes and applications by the use of IJM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ice Deburring process",
            "b) Ice Cutting process",
            "c) Ice Blasting process",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the processes mentioned above are done by using IJM."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Which of the following industries use Ice jet machining for different applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Food industry",
            "b) Medical industry",
            "c) Space industry",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different type of industries mentioned above use Ice jet machining for wide variety of applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "In this type of machining, machining forces are controlled by which of the following fields?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic field",
            "b) Electric field",
            "c) Radiative field",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this machining, the magnetic field controls all the major forces of machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of tools, are required for magnetic field assisted polishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rigid tools",
            "b) Expensive tools",
            "c) Magnetic tools",
            "d) Ultra precession tools"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Magnetic field assisted polishing requires only magnetic machining elements, for the purpose of machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a magnetic field assisted machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro-plating process",
            "b) Magnetic abrasive finishing",
            "c) Magnetic float polishing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are only two types of magnetic field assisted polishing: Magnetic abrasive machining and Magnetic float polishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "In the advanced machining processes, what is the full form of MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnet Automated Finishing",
            "b) Magnetic Abrasive Finishing",
            "c) Magnet Assisted Floating",
            "d) Magnetic Association for Floating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of MAF is Magnetic Abrasive Finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "In Magnetic abrasive finishing, which of the following particles do not contribute to the material removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasive particles",
            "b) Magnetic particles",
            "c) Non-magnetic particles",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Material is removed by colloidal dispersion of the magnetic particles in abrasive particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of the following motions are opted, in order to carry on with the Magnetic abrasive finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotary motion",
            "b) Oscillatory motion",
            "c) Vibratory motion",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the motions mentioned above, are needed for machining parts in MAF."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Magnetic Abrasive finishing is used for which of the following application/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface finishing",
            "b) Cutting",
            "c) Drilling",
            "d) Boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnetic abrasive finishing is a process, which is opted for finishing of parts that are already machined on the other machines."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which is the place, where Magnetic field assisted polishing was invented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The United States of America",
            "b) The United Arab Emirates",
            "c) Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "d) Japan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnetic field assisted polishing was invented in the United States of America."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes cannot be machined using Magnetic abrasive finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface finishing",
            "b) Surface polishing",
            "c) Hole Drilling",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Holes drilling is one of the processes that cannot be done using Magnetic Abrasive Finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Which of the following components, come under machining system of Magnetic Abrasive finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotatory spindle",
            "b) Oscillating Magnets",
            "c) Holding chuck",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The components, which are mentioned above come under machining system of Magnetic Abrasive Finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials can be machined using Magnetic Abrasive finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alloy steels",
            "b) Ceramic materials",
            "c) Iron materials",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Magnetic abrasive finishing is a process which is used for different materials, magnetic and nonmagnetic."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Options": [
            "3. State whether the following statement is true or false about Magnetic abrasive finishing.",
            "“Vibratory motion that is axial, is introduced in the magnetic field by the oscillation of magnetic poles.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Axially vibrating motion is required for machining in MAF."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following material/s is/are used to hold the abrasives, in MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nonmagnetic materials",
            "b) Ferro magnetic materials",
            "c) Ceramic materials",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ferro magnetic materials hold the abrasives in order to remove material through finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "What is the other name of ferromagnetic material used for holding the abrasives in MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic abrasive conglomerate",
            "b) Magnetic abrasive holder",
            "c) Magnetic abrasive container",
            "d) Magnetic abrasive ampule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ferro magnetic material is also called as Magnetic abrasive conglomerate."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What are the sizes magnetic abrasive conglomerates required in the machining system of MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 10 microns",
            "b) 20 – 50 microns",
            "c) 50 – 100 microns",
            "d) 100 – 200 microns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sizes of magnetic abrasive conglomerates range between 50 – 100 microns."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "What are the size ranges of the abrasives used in Magnetic abrasive finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 1 microns",
            "b) 1 to 10 microns",
            "c) 10 to 100 microns",
            "d) 100 to 1000 microns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The size of abrasives used for finishing range between 1 to 10 microns."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which of the following are commonly used magnetic materials in finishing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron and iron oxides",
            "b) Nickel and cobalt",
            "c) Steel and stainless steel",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the materials mentioned above, are commonly used magnetic materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following are commonly used abrasive materials in finishing process of MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon Carbide",
            "b) Aluminium Oxide",
            "c) Cubic Boron Nitride",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the materials mentioned above, are used as abrasives in Magnetic abrasive finishing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials combine to form the magnetic abrasive brush in MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece",
            "b) Magnetic and abrasive particles",
            "c) Magnets",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the materials mentioned above, combine to form the magnetic abrasive brush."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "In order to achieve uniform circulation of abrasives, the magnetic abrasives are undergone through which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stirring",
            "b) Oscillation",
            "c) Vibration",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To achieve uniform circulation of abrasives, the abrasives are undergone thorough stirring."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Magnetic lines of force flows on which part of the work piece material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Through the work piece",
            "b) Over the surface",
            "c) Above the work piece",
            "d) Below the work piece"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnetic lines of force flow through the work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "What is the limit of the roller speed used in MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Up to 0.5 m/s",
            "b) Up to 1.3 m/s",
            "c) Up to 2.6 m/s",
            "d) Up to 3.3 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Roller speed used can be up to 1.3 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "What is the value of magnetic field intensity used in MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 – 0.53 Tesla",
            "b) 0.6 – 0.70 Tesla",
            "c) 0.70 – 0.90 Tesla",
            "d) 0.90 – 1.1 Tesla"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Value of the magnetic field intensity used in MAF range between 0 – 0.53 Tesla."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "What is the value of magnetic pressure used in Magnetic abrasive machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 – 30 kPa",
            "b) 50 – 100 kPa",
            "c) 100 – 200 kPa",
            "d) 200 – 500 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Magnetic abrasive finishing, value of magnetic pressure ranges between 0 – 30 kPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "What is the value of frequency used in Magnetic abrasive finishing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 10 Hz",
            "b) 12 – 25 Hz",
            "c) 30 – 50 Hz",
            "d) 60 – 100 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In MAF process, value of the frequencies used range between 12 – 25 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "In which direction, oscillatory motion of magnets are carried out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Axial to work piece",
            "b) Perpendicular to work piece",
            "c) Inclined to work piece",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Axial oscillation motion of magnets takes with respect to work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following surface defects are removed using Magnetic abrasive finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scratches",
            "b) Hard spots",
            "c) Lay lines and tool marks",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the surface defects mentioned above, can be removed using Magnetic abrasive finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "What is the value of the limited depth to which form errors, tapers, looping can be corrected?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 microns",
            "b) 20 microns",
            "c) 30 microns",
            "d) 40 microns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Form errors, tapers, looping etc.., can be corrected up to a limited depth of 20 microns."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false about magnetic abrasive finishing.",
            "“Increasing the magnetic flux density raises the rate of material removal in finishing.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In MAF, as the magnetic flux density increases, material removal rate increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors, does material removal rate depend on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic flux density",
            "b) Working clearance",
            "c) Work piece material",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factors mentioned above, are responsible for change in material removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors does not affect the magnetic abrasive conglomerates in MAF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasive type",
            "b) Abrasive size",
            "c) Work piece material",
            "d) Volume fraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Magnetic abrasive finishing, work piece material has no effect on magnetic abrasive conglomerates."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "11. State whether the following statement is true or false about Magnetic abrasive finishing.",
            "“Higher rates of material removal are obtained, with an increase in amplitude and frequency.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the amplitude and frequency increases, the rate of material removal increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following applications where MAF is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finishing of inner surfaces",
            "b) Polishing of balls and rollers",
            "c) Chamfering and deburring of gears",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the applications mentioned above can be fulfilled using MAF."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Diamond abrasives used for finishing operation results in which type of surface defects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deep pits",
            "b) Surface scratches",
            "c) Micro cracks",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the defects mentioned above occur, when we use diamond abrasives for material removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditions is/are not suitable for finishing of ceramic balls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Controlled force",
            "b) Large abrasive sizes",
            "c) Small abrasive sizes",
            "d) Less harder abrasives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a better finish, controlled force, fine and less hard abrasives are required."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "In MAF, ceramic balls and the bearing rollers are placed in between which components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasives and float",
            "b) Drive shaft and float",
            "c) Float and magnets",
            "d) Magnets and abrasives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ceramic balls are placed in between drive shaft and float."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Polishing in Magnetic abrasive finishing is done, by which action of material removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical abrasion",
            "b) Mechanical erosion",
            "c) Chemical corrosion",
            "d) Material vaporization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Abrasives are used for the polishing and finishing operations of the parts, in Magnetic abrasive finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding MAF.",
            "“As the forces exerted on the rollers are very small, polishing actions takes place very finely.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the forces exerted are very small, polishing is very fine."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "For obtaining a better finish using Magnetic abrasive finishing, tubes are rotated at which speeds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) Very High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To obtain a better finish in Magnetic abrasive finishing, tubes are rotated at very high speeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an advantage of MAF over Electrolytic finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disposing of electrolyte",
            "b) Cost effective",
            "c) More flexible",
            "d) More accuracy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In MAF, the problem of disposing electrolyte as in case of Electrolytic finishing is not present."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "9. State whether the following statement is true or false about Magnetic abrasive finishing.",
            "“Mirror finishing, removed burrs with lowering the accuracy of the shape are achieved by MAF.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Removed burrs without lowering the accuracy are obtained using MAF."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "What are the other applications where Magnetic abrasive finishing can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removal of oxide layers",
            "b) Removal of protective coatings",
            "c) Chamfering",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the processes mentioned above can be done using Magnetic abrasive finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of CHM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical machining",
            "b) Chemical manufacturing",
            "c) Chemical milling",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of CHM is Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Of the following, which mechanism is used for the removal of material using Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material Vaporization",
            "b) Chemical dissolution",
            "c) Mechanical erosion",
            "d) Mechanical abrasion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemical dissolution takes place in Chemical milling for the removing the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which of the following solutions cannot be used as chemical reactive solution in CHM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acidic solution",
            "b) Alkaline solution",
            "c) Neutral solution",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both acidic or alkane solutions are used for chemical dissolution in Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "By using Chemical machining, which of the following can be produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pockets",
            "b) Contours",
            "c) Slots",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By the use of CHM, pockets, contours, slots and materials having high strength to weight ratio can be machined."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Pre cleaning is done on the work piece surface in order to achieve, which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To provide good adhesion",
            "b) To provide clean surface",
            "c) To assure the absence of contaminants",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factors mentioned above, are achieved thorough pre-cleaning process."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Special coatings applied on work piece materials in order to protect them from chemical reaction are known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maskants",
            "b) Protective coverings",
            "c) Protective varnishing",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The protective coatings on work pieces are known as Maskants."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Type of mask depends on which of the factor/s, given below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of work piece",
            "b) Number of parts",
            "c) Desired resolution",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factors mentioned above, are required to select the type of mask."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "During Chemical milling, depth of etch is controlled by which factor of immersion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Mask method",
            "c) Mask area",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the immersion time increases, depth of the etching increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "What is the range of reagent temperatures used for chemical dissolution in CHM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12ᵒC to 35ᵒC",
            "b) 37ᵒC to 85ᵒC",
            "c) 90ᵒC to 101ᵒC",
            "d) 121ᵒC to 142ᵒC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The optimum temperature of reagent used should range between 37ᵒC to 85ᵒC."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "In Chemical milling, excessive flow of chemical reagent results in which of the following defects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Channellings",
            "b) Grooves",
            "c) Ridges",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Chemical milling, if the reagent flows excessively, then the defects mentioned above may occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Options": [
            "11. State whether the following statement about Chemical milling is true or false.",
            "“At higher temperatures, faster etching rates occur in Chemical milling.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the temperature increases, reaction rate increases which in turn increases etching rate in CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Of the following, which ratio defines the etch factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Etching depth to undercut",
            "b) Undercut to etching depth",
            "c) Undercut to mask area",
            "d) Mask area to undercut"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Etch factor is defined as the ratio of undercut to etching depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "CHM cannot eliminate which of the following defects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Irregularities and dents",
            "b) Surface scratches",
            "c) Waviness",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CHM is not a finishing process as that of MAF, there are some sort of defects in Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the tools required for Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maskants",
            "b) Etchants",
            "c) Scribing plates",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the components mentioned above, are required to carry out Chemical milling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Options": [
            "2. State which of the following statement is true or false regarding Chemical milling.",
            "“Maskants are generally used in CHM, to protect the work piece from the etching chemical agent.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In CHM, maskants are used to protect the work piece from chemical agents."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the materials used for making maskants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synthetic materials",
            "b) Rubber materials",
            "c) Polymeric materials",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the materials mentioned above, can be used for making maskants."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "What are the properties that a maskant used in Chemical milling should possess?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Be tough and adhere well",
            "b) Scribe easily",
            "c) Be inert to chemical reagent",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the properties mentioned above, should be possessed by the maskants."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used to apply the maskants on work piece in Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dipping or spraying",
            "b) Rolling or electro coating",
            "c) Adhesive tapes",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Maskants can be applied to work piece, by the above mentioned means."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding maskants.",
            "“After etching, maskants should be removed easily and inexpensively.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: After etching is done, maskants should be removed easily by inexpensive means."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "In maskant application, photo-resist masks ensure which of the following advantages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High accuracy",
            "b) Ease of repetition",
            "c) Ease of modification",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We will have the advantages which are mentioned above, if we use photo resist masking."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Which of the tolerance values are obtained, when we use cut and peel mask method for maskant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.013 mm",
            "b) ± 0.045 mm",
            "c) ± 0.077 mm",
            "d) ± 0.179 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tolerance value of ± 0.179 mm, will be obtained, when we use cut and peel mask method."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of the tolerance values are obtained, when we use silk-screen resist method for maskant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.013 mm",
            "b) ± 0.045 mm",
            "c) ± 0.077 mm",
            "d) ± 0.179 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tolerance value of ± 0.077 mm, will be obtained, when we use silk screen resist method."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of the tolerance values are obtained, when we use photo resist method for maskant application?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.013 mm",
            "b) ± 0.045 mm",
            "c) ± 0.077 mm",
            "d) ± 0.179 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tolerance value of ± 0.013 mm, will be obtained, when we use photo resist method."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following, are the main uses of etchants applied in Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good surface finish",
            "b) Uniform material removal",
            "c) Control intergranular attack",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In CHM, etchants are used for the above mentioned factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "12. State whether the following statement is true or false about etchants.",
            "“Etchants are used for controlling H2 absorption in case of Ti alloys.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Etchants control the H2 absorption in Ti alloys."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Scribing plates are used to define, which of the following parameters in Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Areas to be exposed",
            "b) Volumes to be exposed",
            "c) Areas not to be exposed",
            "d) Volumes not to be exposed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Scribing plates defines the areas that are to be exposed for removal of material."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following are can be used as guides for scribing process in Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Layout lines",
            "b) Simple templates",
            "c) Fibre glass",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the guides mentioned above, can be used for scribing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the accessories, included in the tooling of Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tanks and hooks",
            "b) Brackets and racks",
            "c) Fixtures",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The accessories mentioned above are included in the tooling of Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Which of the following come under process parameters of Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reagent type",
            "b) Concentration",
            "c) Operating temperature",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the parameters mentioned above, are different process parameters required for Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Options": [
            "2. State whether the following statement is true or false about Chemical milling.",
            "“Maskants, applied on work pieces, are not responsible for CHM process.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maskants are also responsible for process to take place in Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "To machine high quality parts using CHM, which of the following need not be necessary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat treatment of work piece",
            "b) Grain size of work piece",
            "c) Frequency of vibrations",
            "d) Range of work pieces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To machine high qualities products vibrational frequency is not necessary in CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "The process parameters will have direct impact on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Etch factor",
            "b) Machining rate",
            "c) Production tolerance",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factors mentioned above, will have direct impact due to above process parameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Thickness of the maskant coating ranges between which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0025 – 0.013 mm",
            "b) 0.025 – 0.13 mm",
            "c) 0.25 – 1.3 mm",
            "d) 2.5 – 13 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maskant material coatings should have a thickness, which range between 0.025 – 0.13 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following, are the general materials used for maskant application?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neoprene",
            "b) Poly vinyl chloride",
            "c) Polyethylene",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the materials mentioned above, can be used as maskant materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "7. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding MRR.",
            "“The rate of material removal, does not depend on uniformity of the solution temperature.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Material removal rate also depends on uniformity of the solution temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "On which of the following factors, MRR will not be depend on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical uniformity",
            "b) Metallurgical uniformity",
            "c) Frequency uniformity",
            "d) Temperature uniformity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemical milling is independent of frequency distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Castings having a larger grain size, will show how much surface roughness value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In castings, as grain size increases, surface roughness increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials have the highest machining rate and best surface quality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolled metal sheets",
            "b) Thick metal plates",
            "c) Polymeric plates",
            "d) Plastic sheets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rolled metal sheets will have highest machining rate and surface quality in CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "For softer materials, which type of etching rates are obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Chemical milling, softer materials need low etching rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "For harder materials, which of the following etching rates are obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Chemical milling, harder materials need higher etching rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "13. State whether the following statement is true or false about etching rates.",
            "“As the etching rate increases, low surface roughness values occur.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High etching rates result in low surface roughness values."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Which of the following are necessary for best surface quality in Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine grain size and homogenous metallurgy",
            "b) Coarse grain size and heterogeneous metallurgy",
            "c) Fine grain size and heterogeneous metallurgy",
            "d) Coarse grain size and homogenous metallurgy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In CHM, for best surface quality, fine grain size and homogenous metallurgical work piece must be required."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the factors, on which, surface finish depends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grain size",
            "b) Heat treatment",
            "c) Induced stresses",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factors mentioned above, are responsible for different qualities of surface finish."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Options": [
            "3. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding surface finish in CHM.",
            "“The surfaces, which are machined using Chemical milling, will have regular lay pattern.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In CHM, surfaces do not have regular lay pattern."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Which of the following defects cannot be altered or eliminated using CHM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waviness",
            "b) Surface imperfections",
            "c) Scratches",
            "d) Dents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using CHM, surface imperfections cannot be eliminated."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Which type of etching rate, mentioned below, produces low surface roughness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Chemical milling, high etching rate produces low surface roughness values and tolerances."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "The depth of cut tolerances increases when machining ____________ depths at high machining rates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very smaller",
            "b) Smaller",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) Larger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Chemical milling, tolerance increases when machining depth increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "What is the value of etching rate, which can be achieved using Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 mm/min",
            "b) 0.025 mm/min",
            "c) 0.050 mm/min",
            "d) 0.075 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While we use Chemical milling etch rates of around 0.025 mm/min are achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance values achieved in Chemical milling, which depend on work piece material and depth of cut?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 10%",
            "b) ± 20%",
            "c) ± 30%",
            "d) ± 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tolerances of ± 10% of cut width are achieved using CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "For what value of machining depths, surface roughness sharply increases with depth of cut?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <100 µm",
            "b) <200 µm",
            "c) <300 µm",
            "d) <400 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For material depths <200 µm, surface roughness increases with depth of cut."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "What is the value of surface roughness, which is generally obtained using Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.08 µm",
            "b) 0.1 – 0.8 µm",
            "c) 1 – 8 µm",
            "d) 10 – 80 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface roughness obtained when general conditions are applied, is between 0.1 – 0.8 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What is the value of surface roughness, when special conditions are applied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 – 0.025 µm",
            "b) 0.025 – 0.05 µm",
            "c) 0.05 – 0.075 µm",
            "d) 0.075 – 0.1 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface roughness obtained when special conditions are applied, is between 0.025 – 0.05 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be easily removed using Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TiO2 layer",
            "b) Decarburized layer",
            "c) Recast structure",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the layers mentioned above, can be removed using Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "13. State whether the following statement is true or false about Chemical milling.",
            "“CHM can also affect mechanical properties, if they differ from surface layer to base metal.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chemical milling can affect the mechanical properties of the machined parts if they are different at surface layers and base metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What are the advantages when we use Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight reduction",
            "b) No burrs",
            "c) No stresses",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the advantages mentioned above, can be obtained using Chemical milling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Weight reduction is possible, on which type of contours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very simple",
            "b) Simple",
            "c) Complex",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Weight reduction can be possible using Chemical milling, on complex contours, compared to conventional machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Simultaneous material removal using Chemical milling, results in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves productivity",
            "b) Reduces wrapping",
            "c) Minimizing part distortion",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factor mentioned above occur, when we use Chemical milling for material removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the advantages of CHM.",
            "“As there are no stresses induced, machining of delicate parts is possible.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In CHM, no stresses are induced, which makes machining of delicate parts easier."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which type of taper can be achieved, using Chemical milling, on contours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discontinuous",
            "b) Continuous",
            "c) Periodic",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using Chemical milling, a continuous taper, on contours can be achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the advantages?",
            "“Capital cost of equipment, for machining large components, is relatively high.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Capital cost of equipment, is relatively low for machining large components."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Which of the following, are the other advantages of CHM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design changes",
            "b) Less skilled operator",
            "c) Minor tooling costs",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All of the advantages mentioned above, are obtained using CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Good surface quality and absence of burr eliminates which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cutting operations",
            "b) Finishing operations",
            "c) Drilling operations",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Absence of burrs and good surface quality eliminates finishing operations in CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "9. State whether the following statement is true or false about advantages.",
            "“Extensive web areas and decorative finishes are not possible using CHM.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Decorative finishes are obtained when we use CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "What are the values of scrap rates obtained in Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 3%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 7%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Low scrapes rates around 3% are obtained when we use the Chemical milling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the limitations of Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disposal of chemicals",
            "b) Limited scribing accuracy",
            "c) Surface imperfections",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factors mentioned above, are the limitations of Chemical milling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "What is the value of shallow cuts obtained on sheets and plates, when we use CHM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.83 mm",
            "b) 6.39 mm",
            "c) 12.27 mm",
            "d) 20.32 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Very shallow depths of value 12.27 mm, are obtained when we use CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Hand masking, scribing and stripping can be difficult, due to which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time consuming",
            "b) Repetitive",
            "c) Tedious",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the factors mentioned above, are main disadvantages for different processes in CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which type of metallurgical surfaces are needed in Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homogenous",
            "b) Heterogeneous",
            "c) Mixture",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Metallurgic homogenous surfaces are needed for chemical milling to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Porous castings yield, which type of surfaces in Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform surfaces",
            "b) Even surfaces",
            "c) Uneven surfaces",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As there are porous castings, there would be pores on the surface which lead to uneven surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement regarding the limitations of CHM.",
            "“Welded areas etch, at a rate that is same as base metal.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Welded areas etch at a different rate, when compared to that of base material."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "The absence of residual stresses on the chemically machined surfaces can produce __________ strength.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Favorable fatigue",
            "b) Unfavorable fatigue",
            "c) Constructive fatigue",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Absence of residual stresses produce unfavorable fatigue strength, unlike to the processes that induce compressive residual stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Which of the following, indicate the accuracy of scribing by Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unlimited",
            "b) Boundless",
            "c) Infinite",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Scribing accuracy is limited in CHM process due to uneven surface finish."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the other limitations of Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen pickup",
            "b) Intergranular attack",
            "c) Complex designs becoming expensive",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydrogen pick up, intergranular attack are some other limitations in Chemical milling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a limitation of Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steep tapers not practical",
            "b) Low scrap rates",
            "c) Less scribing accuracy",
            "d) Deep narrow cuts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Low scrap rates are possible in Chemical milling, which is an advantage to the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the following metals can be machined using the Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper",
            "b) Zinc",
            "c) Steel",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Zinc, copper, lead, and nickel are some of the metals that can be chemically machined."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "What is the range, between which, the depth of cut in Chemical milling varies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.13 – 0. 84 mm",
            "b) 0.93 – 1.56 mm",
            "c) 2.54 – 12.27 mm",
            "d) 13.3 – 104.56 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Practically, depth of cut in Chemical milling range between 2.54 – 12.27 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Which of the following non-metallic materials can be machined using the Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plastics",
            "b) Glass",
            "c) Ceramics",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Non-metallic materials such as glass, ceramics and plastics can also be machined using Chemical milling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most popular application for weight reduction of aerospace components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow cuts",
            "b) Deep cuts",
            "c) Very deep cuts",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shallow cuts in large thin sheets helps in reducing the weight, especially in aerospace industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "How many designs can be machined from the same sheet in Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only one",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Multiple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Chemical milling, multiple designs can b machined on a large thin sheet depending upon the size of the designs."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "CHM is used to thin out walls, web and ribs of parts that have been produces by which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forging",
            "b) Casting",
            "c) Sheet metal forming",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CHM is used for applications mentioned above of the parts, which are formed by casting, forging and sheet metal forming processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Removal of sharp burrs come under which application of Chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deep cuts",
            "b) Multiple part machining",
            "c) Improving surface characteristics",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Removal of sharp burrs improve the surface characteristics of parts machined using Chemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be eliminated from the surfaces using Chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha case from Ti-forgings",
            "b) Decarburized layer from low cast alloys",
            "c) Recast layer from machined parts",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The defects on surfaces mentioned above, can be eliminated using Chemical milling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "CHM is used to remove the thin surfaces from forgings and castings, at which time of process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) After penetration inspection",
            "b) Prior to penetration inspection",
            "c) At the starting of process",
            "d) At the end of process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Removal of thin surfaces from forgings and casting takes place, prior to penetration depth inspection."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Options": [
            "10. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the applications of CHM.",
            "“Removal of thin surfaces, prior to inspection, is done for detection of hidden defects.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Removal of thin surfaces is done to detect the hidden defects in surfaces using CHM."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "In advanced machining process, what is the full form of PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photochemical manufacturing",
            "b) Photochemical machining",
            "c) Photo crystalline manufacturing",
            "d) Photo crystalline machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Full form of PCM in advanced machining processes is Photochemical milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "In this method, which of the following techniques are used to apply the maskant on the machining surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photographic techniques",
            "b) Cut and peel masking",
            "c) Silkscreen resist technique",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maskant is applied on the machining surface using photographic techniques in PCM."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "What is the similarity between normal Chemical milling process and Photo chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both use chemicals",
            "b) Maskant application method",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both method are similar in one property i.e.., they both use chemicals."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "In some cases, Photochemical milling can also be called as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photo chemical blasting",
            "b) Photo chemical blanking",
            "c) Photo chemical drilling",
            "d) Photo chemical erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In some cases flat, thin gauge complex parts can be machined, this process is known as Photochemical Blanking (PCB)."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Photo chemical blanking can be used to machine the parts to high precision, up to which of the following thickness values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 – 0.007 mm",
            "b) 0.007 – 0.012 mm",
            "c) 0.013 – 1.503 mm",
            "d) 1.612 – 2.125 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PCB can be used to machine parts of thickness 0.013 – 1.50 mm to high precision."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding Photochemical milling.",
            "“Unlike that of CHM, PCM can also be used to create parts.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In CHM original parts manufactured in other processes are machined. Unlike that case, in PCM parts can be created from thin sheets using maskants."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "In case of photochemical milling that use using lettering and graphics for surface etching, what will be the depth of surface etched?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very deep",
            "b) Up to certain depth",
            "c) Half-way",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sometimes photochemical machining is used to surface-etch components with lettering or graphics, in which etchant works to only a certain depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "When was the process, Photochemical milling is introduced to the machining environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1920s",
            "b) 1930s",
            "c) 1950s",
            "d) 1960s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCM was introduced to the machining industry in 1960s, as an offshoot of PCBs."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "9. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding PCM.",
            "“In PCM, etching depth does not depend on the time, a component is immersed in the chemical solution.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As in case of CHM, depth of etch in PCM depend upon the time of part immersed in chemical solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes does not come under Chemical machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical milling",
            "b) Photo forming",
            "c) Photo chemical filling",
            "d) Photo chemical blanking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Photo forming is a process of electro plating metals over the mandrels which does not use chemical for material removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first step in Photo chemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generation of photographic film",
            "b) Etching the part",
            "c) Removal of etchant",
            "d) Photo resist stripping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generation of photographic film using CAD drawings is the first step in PCM."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "What is the other name for photographic film generated in Photochemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photo mask",
            "b) Photo tool",
            "c) Photo cover",
            "d) Photo plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The photographic film generated using CAD drawings, which is also called as Photo tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "What is the next step after generation of Photo-tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical cleaning",
            "b) Coating of photo tool",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After generation of photo-tool, it is applied to the chemically cleaned work surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "What is the use of photo tool in Photochemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleaning of work piece",
            "b) Protection of surface against etching",
            "c) Etching of part surface",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In PCM, photo tool is applied as coating which act as stencil resist that protect the surface from etching."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Where are the photo tools applied on the surface of the work piece material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) On the top",
            "b) On the bottom",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Photo tools are applied in pairs- one on the top and one on the bottom like sandwiching work piece between photo layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "The photo tool is exposed to which light source, in order to form a replica of image of the required geometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infrared sources",
            "b) Ultraviolet source",
            "c) Normal light source",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ultraviolet light sources are used to transfer the image of the required geometry on to the resist, precisely."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which can be used as solutions which develop the photo resists in PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Alkaline solution",
            "c) Hydrocarbons",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In PCM, the solutions mentioned above can be used to develop the photoresist films on the surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "What is the next step after creating the photo tool and adhering it to work piece using UV light source?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finishing",
            "b) Etching",
            "c) Rinsing and drying",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After the image is adhered to work piece, etching is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "The right choice of etchant depend on, which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rate of material removal",
            "b) Etching depth",
            "c) Cost and quality",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Etchant selection depends on cost, quality, etch depth and MRR rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "After etching is done, what is the next step in Photochemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finishing",
            "b) Rinsing and drying",
            "c) Removal of protective layer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After etching is done in PCM, the parts are rinsed and dried."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "How are the protective layer coatings on the parts are removed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Use of chemicals",
            "b) Mechanical techniques with chemicals",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The protective layers are removed by the use of chemicals and by using mechanical techniques with chemicals."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the metals that can be machined using Photo chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Nickel",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Copper, aluminium, zinc, steel, molybdenum, zirconium, titanium are some of the metals that can be machined using PCM."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following non-metallic materials that can be machined using PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Ceramics",
            "c) Some plastics",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The non-metallic materials mentioned above, can be machined using PCM."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are excellent for Photochemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brittle materials",
            "b) Ductile materials",
            "c) Elastic materials",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Brittle materials are excellent candidates for PCM, since they tend to break easily using traditional machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false about applications of PCM.",
            "“Using PCM, very high tempered materials are machined easily.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PCM can be favourable for very high tempered and brittle materials unlike that of traditional machining, where they tend to break easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the typical applications of Photo chemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Production of signs",
            "b) Production of labels",
            "c) Fabrication of boxes and enclosures",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Using PCM, the above mentioned applications can be fulfilled."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "What is the value of thickness of work pieces to be used in PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 – 0.003 mm",
            "b) 0.013 – 1.50 mm",
            "c) 1.50 – 2.35 mm",
            "d) 2.50 – 3.33 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thickness value of work pieces in PCM range between 0.013 – 1.50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "What type of work pieces must be used in Photochemical milling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bent surfaces",
            "b) Rolled surfaces",
            "c) Flat surfaces",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The work pieces must be flat in order to carry on the PCM process."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Which of the following industries use PCM for different applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronic",
            "b) Automotive",
            "c) Telecommunication",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCM has its applications in the industries such as electronics, automotive, telecommunication, computer, medical, aerospace and other industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the components that can be machined using PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filters and screens",
            "b) Lead frames",
            "c) Connectors and probes",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Typical components such as gaskets, lead frames, contacts, connectors, probes, filters and screens can be machined using PCM."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "What is the cost per unit for low production volumes of complex designs using PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) High",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Relatively low cost per unit is required in PCM, since tooling is inexpensive compared to that of traditional practices."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "11. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding advantages of PCM.",
            "“In PCM, lead times are large, when compared to that required for hard tooling using traditional means.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lead times are small when compared to that required by processes that require hard tooling."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors can change the parameters of etch such as depth, size of hole etc.?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time of etch",
            "b) Type of etchant",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Type of etchant used and time for etching can change the features such as hole size and depth of etch."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "How much amount of burr is produced, when components are machined using PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Large",
            "d) No burr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Photochemical milling is a burr-free process i.e.., burr is not produced in this process."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of the following properties of materials are changed by using Photochemical milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hardness of material",
            "b) Ductility of material",
            "c) Grain structure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In PCM, material properties such as hardness, ductility and grain structure are not changed."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "15. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding advantages of PCM.",
            "“Patterns can be reproduced easily.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Patterns can be reproduced easily because tooling is made by photographic techniques."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of EP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro plating",
            "b) Electro polishing",
            "c) Electron pocketing",
            "d) Electrical punching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Full form of EP is Electro-polishing in advanced machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "When was the process Electro polishing introduced to the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1918",
            "b) 1922",
            "c) 1935",
            "d) 1943"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electropolishing was introduced to world in the year 1935, when Cu and Zn were successfully electropolished by Germans."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "How is the material removed in Electropolishing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anodic dissolution",
            "b) Cathodic dissolution",
            "c) Chemical corrosion",
            "d) Mechanical erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Material in Electropolishing is removed by anodic dissolution process."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding EP process.",
            "“Electropolishing is same as electro plating.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electropolishing is the opposite of electroplating."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "In the following terminals, part to be finished acts as which terminal in EP process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anode",
            "b) Cathode",
            "c) Neutral",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As this process is opposite to that of Electro plating, part to be finished is the anode in EP."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which of the following come under the components of EP process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrolyte solution",
            "b) Dc power supply",
            "c) Work piece",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The EP process components include DC power supply, electrolyte, electrically charged terminals, of which, one of them is work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Electrolytic solution is a mixture of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insoluble salts",
            "b) Several acids",
            "c) All of them mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electrolytic solution is a mixture of several acids and insoluble salts."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "What amount of current density can be used for Electropolishing to take place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Optimum",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Limiting amount of current should be used in EP process for anodic dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which of the following takes place if the current density used is relatively high?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smoothing",
            "b) Finishing",
            "c) Oxygen evolution",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the current level increases beyond the limiting value, pitting takes place due to gas evolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "More anodic dissolution takes place at which part of the surface of the work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peaks",
            "b) Valleys",
            "c) Troughs",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Anodic dissolution is high at peaks when compared to valleys on the surface of the work pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "11. State whether the following statement is true or false about EP process.",
            "“In EP, produced surface possess true crystalline structure without distortion.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electropolishing, the produced surface possess true crystalline structure without distortion, unlike that of cold working as in mechanical finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Surfaces produced in Electropolishing process possess which of the qualities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bright",
            "b) Clean",
            "c) Microscopically smooth",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Surfaces produced in EP becomes clean, bright and microscopically smooth."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "How much amount of properties of bulk material, are possessed by the finished part in EP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Negligible amount",
            "b) Only some properties",
            "c) All properties",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The part machined using EP process, possess true properties of the bulk material."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "14. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding EP.",
            "“Fine direction lines are left in EP, like that of abrasive polishing.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike that of abrasive polishing, fine direction lines are not produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Of the following material removal mechanisms, material is removed by which one in EP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrode dissolution",
            "b) Corrosion",
            "c) Abrasion",
            "d) Erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Anodic dissolution takes place in Electropolishing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Which of the following come under the process parameters of the Electropolishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece material and condition",
            "b) Current density",
            "c) Applied voltage",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The process parameters of Electropolishing include current density, applied voltage, acid type, temperature original surface roughness, work piece condition and material."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Current density of the EP process generally varies between which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0001 – 0.001 A/cm2",
            "b) 0.005 – 1.8 A/cm2",
            "c) 1.9 – 2.532 A/cm2",
            "d) 3.523 – 4.23 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally current density value used in EP process vary between 0.005 – 1.8 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the work piece materials that can be machined using Electropolishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon steel",
            "b) Alpha brass",
            "c) Phosphor bronze",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different work piece materials that can be machined using EP are carbon steels, stainless steels, copper, alpha brass, nickel, phosphor bronze, aluminium, magnesium etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of the following electrolyte, can be used commonly for stainless steel, Cu, Ni and Mg?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HCLO4",
            "b) H2PO4",
            "c) H2SO4",
            "d) HNO3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: H2PO4 is a common electrolyte used in the machining of Cu, Ni, Mg."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "What is the electrolytic solution’s temperature when stainless steel is machined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50o C",
            "b) 80o C",
            "c) 120o C",
            "d) 150o C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Temperature of electrolytic solution used for machining stainless steel is 80o C."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Options": [
            "7. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding process parameters of EP.",
            "“In EP, process parameters have a direct impact on surface quality and productivity of process.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electropolishing, parameters have a direct impact on quality of surface and productivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "For machining of Cu material which of the following can be used as electrolytes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H2PO4",
            "b) H2PO4 and Na2CrO4",
            "c) HCLO4",
            "d) HNO3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For Cu material electrolyte used in EP process is H2PO4."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "In the following types of voltage, which one best suites EP process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Randomly Fluctuating",
            "b) Constant",
            "c) Periodically fluctuating",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the machining to take place in Electropolishing process, voltage should be correct and constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "10. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding process parameters of EP.",
            "“In EP, high current densities are used for anodic dissolution.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Electropolishing, limited current densities are used for anodic dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "For economical and high quality Electropolishing, which of the following materials are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cold rolled metals",
            "b) Hot flat metals",
            "c) Hot plastics",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cold rolled metals are the most important materials for economical and high quality polishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Options": [
            "2. State whether the following statement is true or false about applications of EP.",
            "“In EP, cast items do not maintain the texture of sand mold.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cast items usually maintain the texture of sand mold since they have coarse grains and include alloying elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be removed by using Electropolishing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scales",
            "b) Distortion",
            "c) Coarse texture",
            "d) Burrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coarse texture cannot be removed using Electropolishing as they produce rough surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Electropolishing prepares surfaces for which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron Beam machining",
            "b) Electro plating",
            "c) Laser beam machining",
            "d) Magnetic Abrasive machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: EP prepares surfaces for electroplating, which creates an opportunity for best adherence."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "For which of the following components, polishing can be done using EP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical conduits",
            "b) Outlet boxes",
            "c) Medical equipment",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polishing light fixtures of electrical conduits, outlet boxes, and medical, surgical, and food processing equipment."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the applications of EP.",
            "“Using Electropolishing, deburring and breaking sharp edges can be done.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Deburring and breaking sharp edges obtained from hand filing, grinding and honing of tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Electropolishing removes scales and distortions that are produces by which of the processes below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Annealing",
            "b) Nitriding",
            "c) Carburizing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Scales and distortions produced by annealing, carburizing, nitriding, welding and soldering can be removed using EP."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false about applications of EP.",
            "“In EP, removal of hardness and stressed surface layers, reduces life of parts.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Removal of hardness and stressed surface layers improves the surface life of part."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Polishing of how many parts can be done using Electropolishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One part",
            "b) Two parts",
            "c) Multiple parts",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Multiple parts can be polished simultaneously using EP, depending upon the size of parts."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Electropolishing cannot cover up which type of defects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burrs on surfaces",
            "b) Scales and distortions",
            "c) Non-metallic inclusions",
            "d) Metallographic examination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Seams and non-metallic inclusions are some defects which cannot be covered up using EP."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a limitation of EP process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rough scratches removal",
            "b) Scales removal",
            "c) Distortions removal",
            "d) Burr removal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In EP, rough scratches cannot be removed even by considerable amount of process."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Metals containing which of the following chemicals will be troublesome in EP process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon",
            "b) Lead",
            "c) Sulphur",
            "d) All of them mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  d\nExplanation: All the elements mentioned above, if present in metals, will be troublesome in EP process."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "13. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the limitations of EP.",
            "“In EP, base metal condition does not affect the process.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Base metal condition affects the process of EP."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Which of the following defects lead to poor electropolishing of the surfaces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improper annealing",
            "b) Non-metallic inclusions",
            "c) Over pickling",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Non-metallic inclusions, over pickling, large grain size, direction roll marks, improper cold reduction leads to poor electro polishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Electropolishing is more suited for, removal of which of the following defects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small scratches",
            "b) Imperfections",
            "c) Smoothing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Small scratches and imperfections can be easily removed when compared to that of rough scratches."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrochemical manufacturing",
            "b) Electrochemical milling",
            "c) Electrochemical machining",
            "d) Electrochemical masking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of ECM is Electrochemical machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "In the following scientists, who was the one to introduce first patent on ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Balamuth",
            "b) Steve O Flawer",
            "c) Gusseff",
            "d) McGeough"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gusseff was the one, who introduced the first patent on ECM in 1929."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "When was the first significant development of ECM occurred?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1920s",
            "b) 1930s",
            "c) 1950s",
            "d) 1960s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: After the first patent in 1929, the first development of ECM was done in 1950s."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following material removal mechanisms is implemented by ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical abrasion",
            "b) Electrochemical dissolution",
            "c) Chemical corrosion",
            "d) Mechanical erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ECM, material is removed by electrochemical dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Electrolysis occur when which of the following takes place between electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric current flow",
            "b) Electron flow",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When there is an electron flow there is current flow in the opposite direction. For electrolysis to take place there should be flow of current between electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "The system which consists of electrolytic solution and electrodes can be referred to as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrolytic cell",
            "b) Electrode system",
            "c) Electrolytic system",
            "d) Electrode cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The system of electrodes and electrolytic solution is referred as electrolytic cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "The chemical reactions occurring at electrodes are called with, which of the following names?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anodic reactions",
            "b) Cathode reactions",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemical reactions occurring at electrodes are called as anodic or cathodic reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Amount of mass dissolved is directly proportional to which of the following quantities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amount of electricity",
            "b) Frequency of vibrations",
            "c) Amplitude of oscillations",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Amount of mass dissolved is directly proportional to amount of electricity and also substances’ chemical equivalent."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Chemical equivalent is the ratio of which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece valence to the atomic weight",
            "b) Atomic weight to work piece valence",
            "c) Tool valence to molecular weight",
            "d) Molecular weight to tool valence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemical equivalent is the ratio of atomic weight to work piece valence."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "What is the value of the current density used in Electrochemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.4 A/mm2",
            "b) 0.5 – 5 A/mm2",
            "c) 6 – 15 A/mm2",
            "d) 20 – 50 A/mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High current densities, which range between 0.5 – 5 A/mm2 are used in ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "What are the values of voltages used in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 8 V",
            "b) 10 to 30 V",
            "c) 40 to 80 V",
            "d) 90 to 110 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Low voltages, ranging between 10 to 30 V are used in Electrochemical machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "How does the current pass between the two electrodes in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrolytic solution",
            "b) Direct contact of electrodes",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Current passes through the solution of electrolyte, which fills the gap between the electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "What is the value of velocity with which, electrolyte flows in the inter electrode gap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) >1 m/s",
            "b) >3 m/s",
            "c) >5 m/s",
            "d) >10 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The velocity of the electrolytic solution must be greater than 5 m/s, in order to intensify the mass and charge transfer."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Of the following, electrolyte removes which of the dissolution products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal hydroxides",
            "b) Heat",
            "c) Gas bubbles",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrolyte removes the dissolution products such as metal hydroxides, heat and gas bubbles formed in the inter electrode gap."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the theory of ECM.",
            "“Application of P.D (potential difference) lead to occurrence of several reactions.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When P.D (potential difference) is applied, different reactions occur at anode and cathode."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Which of the following reactions takes place at the electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generation of hydrogen",
            "b) Dissolution of iron",
            "c) Dissolution of NaCl",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the reactions mentioned above, take place at different electrodes in ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Which of the following reaction takes place at anode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generation of hydrogen",
            "b) Dissolution of iron",
            "c) Generation of hydroxyl ions",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At anode, dissolution of Fe takes place in the process of ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Which of the following reactions take place at cathode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generation of hydrogen",
            "b) Dissolution of iron",
            "c) Dissolution of NaCl",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At cathode, generation of hydrogen takes place in the process of ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Positively charged particles (cations) move towards which electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anode",
            "b) Cathode",
            "c) Anode & Cathode",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Positively charge particles are directed towards the cathode, which is negatively charged."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Negatively charged particles (anions) move towards which electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anode",
            "b) Cathode",
            "c) Anode & Cathode",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Negatively charged particles are directed towards the anode, which is positively charged."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which of the following come under the main components of ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feed control system",
            "b) Work piece holding devices",
            "c) Electrolyte supply system",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main components of Electro chemical machining include feed control system, electrolyte supply system, power supply unit, work piece holding devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Feed control system is responsible for which action in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Giving feed to tool",
            "b) Electrolyte supply",
            "c) Power supply",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Feed control system is used for feeding the tool at constant rate during equilibrium machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "In ECM equipment, what is the role of electrolyte supply system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Giving feed to tool",
            "b) Electrolyte supply",
            "c) Power supply",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the name itself indicates, electrolyte supply system is used to supply the electrolyte required for anodic dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "What is the role of power supply unit in ECM equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Giving feed to tool",
            "b) Electrolyte supply",
            "c) Power supply",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ECM, power supply unit is used to supply the machine current at constant dc voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "For large size machining, which type of facilities are used in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semi-automated facilities",
            "b) Automated facilities",
            "c) Automated & Semi-automated facilities",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Automated and semi-automated facilities are used for large size machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Electrolyte supply system should concentrate on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure",
            "b) Supply rate",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrolyte supply system should supply electrolyte at a given rate, temperature and pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "For high strength or rigidity, which type of coatings are recommended for metals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Other metal coatings",
            "b) Non-metallic coatings",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For high strength and rigidity, non-metallic coatings are recommended for metals."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "What is the value of voltage that the power supply unit supplies for ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 1 V",
            "b) 2 to 30 V",
            "c) 50 to 80 V",
            "d) 100 to 160 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Voltage supply required for ECM ranges between 2 to 30 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Between which of the following values, does the current range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.002 to 0.01 A",
            "b) 0.01 to 10 A",
            "c) 50 to 10000 A",
            "d) 105 to 106 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Electrochemical machining, current value ranges between 50 to 10000 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "What are the values of current densities used in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 2 A/cm2",
            "b) 5 to 500 A/cm2",
            "c) 600 to 1000 A/cm2",
            "d) 1200 to 2800 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Current density values in ECM range between 5 to 500 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which type of adjustment is to be done for gap voltages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous adjustment",
            "b) Discontinuous adjustment",
            "c) Periodic adjustment",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ECM, usually continuous adjustment of gap voltage is required."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Compared to the tool used in ECM, how should be the work piece size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than",
            "b) Smaller than",
            "c) Same as tool",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By an oversize, work piece size is expected to be greater than tool size."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors are used to determine the tool geometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Required shape",
            "b) Electrical conductivity",
            "c) Tool feed rate",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For determining a tool geometry we must specify some factors such as the required shape of the surface, tool feed rate, gap voltage, electrochemical machinability of the work material, electrolyte conductivity, and both electrodes’ polarization voltages."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the simplest methods for applying the insulation on tools?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spraying",
            "b) Dipping",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ECM, dipping or spraying are the simplest methods for insulating the tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Options": [
            "15. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the tools of ECM.",
            "“With computer integrated manufacturing (CIM), cathodes are produced at high costs and less accurately.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using CIM, cathodes are produced at low costs and more accurately."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "What are the main functions of electrolyte in Electrochemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conduct machining current",
            "b) Removal of debris",
            "c) Maintaining constant temperature",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Main functions of electrolyte are conducting machine current, removing the debris, carrying away the heat, maintaining constant temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Electrolytic solution should ensure which type of anodic dissolution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform",
            "b) Non-uniform",
            "c) Low speed",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Uniform and high speed anodic dissolution must be ensured by the electrolyte."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Options": [
            "3. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the electrolytic solution.",
            "“In ECM, formation of passive film is recommended.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrolytic solution should avoid formation of passive layers on anode."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which type of electrical conductivity is necessary for electrolytic solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) High",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: High electrical conductivity is needed for electrolytic solution in ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "What are the other features of electrolytic solution in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non toxic",
            "b) Less erosive",
            "c) Less viscous",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrolytic solution should be nontoxic, less viscous and less erosive."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "How much should be the electrolytic solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highly expensive",
            "b) Inexpensive",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrolyte must be inexpensive and available at ease."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which are the most common electrolytes used in Electrochemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium chloride",
            "b) Sodium nitride",
            "c) Sodium hydroxide",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrolytes such as sodium chloride, sodium nitride, sodium hydroxide are some of the electrolytes used in ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Selection of electrolyte does not depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece material",
            "b) Dimensional tolerance",
            "c) Heat affected zones",
            "d) Machining productivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Selection of electrolyte depend up on work piece material, dimensional tolerance, machining productivity and surface finish required."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "What must be the value of electrolytic temperature in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 to 14oC",
            "b) 22 to 45oC",
            "c) 46 to 57oC",
            "d) 62 to 76oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Temperature of electrolyte should range between 22 to 45oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "What must be the value of the pressure of electrolytic solution used in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 10 kPa",
            "b) 10 to 80 kPa",
            "c) 100 to 200 kPa",
            "d) 300 to 400 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Value of pressure of electrolytic solution must range between 100 to 200 kPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "What must be the value of velocity of the electrolytic solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 15 m/s",
            "b) 25 to 50 m/s",
            "c) 60 to 100 m/s",
            "d) 120 to 200 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Typical velocity of the electrolytic solution must range between 25 to 50 m/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Local metal removal rates are high at which gap locations mentioned below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small gap",
            "b) Medium gap",
            "c) Large gap",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Local metal removal rates are high at small gap locations in ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "When local metal removal rates are high, how will be the current density and current efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the local metal removal rates are high then current density and efficiency are also high."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Current efficiency depends on which of the following in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anodic material",
            "b) Electrolyte",
            "c) Anodic material & Electrolyte",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Current efficiency in ECM depend on electrolyte and anodic material used."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "15. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the electrolytes in ECM.",
            "“In Electrochemical machining, electrolytes should deposit on cathode electrodes.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ECM, electrolytes should not deposit on cathode, so that shape of electrode remains unchanged."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "What is the approximate value of faraday’s constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65,200 C",
            "b) 53,800 C",
            "c) 96,500 C",
            "d) 85,600 C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 1 faraday equals to approximately 96500 C."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "In the following ratios of metal dissolved amounts, which one represent the current efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Observed to theoretical",
            "b) Theoretical to observed",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In electrochemical machining, current efficiency is the ratio of observed amount of metal dissolved to the theoretical amount of metal dissolved."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Apparent current efficiency is due to which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Choice of wrong valence",
            "b) Passivation of anodic surface",
            "c) Gas evolution at anode",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Current efficiency may be apparent because of choice of wrong valence, passivation of anodic surface or gas evolution at anodic surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the working principles.",
            "“In ECM, grain boundary attacks remove the grains through electrolytic forces.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ECM, grain boundary attacks are the cause for removal of grains by electrolytic forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "In ECM, gap increase proportional to which relation of time below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square of time",
            "b) Square root of time",
            "c) Cube of time",
            "d) Cube root of time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Electrochemical machining, gap increases proportional to the square root of time."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "At constant feed rates what happens to gap thickness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Becomes constant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At constant feed rate, work piece becomes stationary and thus the gap thickness becomes constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "At constant gap thickness material removal becomes equal to feed rate. What is this gap called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal gap",
            "b) Equilibrium gap",
            "c) Unique gap",
            "d) Narrow gap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When rate of material removal per unit area is same as feed rate, then corresponding thickness is called as equilibrium thickness indicated by ‘ye’."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "If the gap thickness is greater than equilibrium thickness what will be MRR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MRR is less than feed rate",
            "b) MRR is greater than feed rate",
            "c) MRR is equal to feed rate",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When gap thickness is greater than equilibrium thickness, MRR will be less than feed rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "During ECM drilling, decrease in feed rates lead to which type of machining gaps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wider",
            "b) Narrow",
            "c) Small",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Decrease in feed rate lead to wider gap thickness in ECM drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Too small gap causes which of the following effects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sparking",
            "b) Short circuit",
            "c) Sparking & Short circuit",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sparking or short circuit occurs when the gap is too small."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Electro chemical dissolution phase starts with the movement of ions between which two components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cathode and anode",
            "b) Cathode and power source",
            "c) Power source and anode",
            "d) Power source and electrolyte"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ECD phase occurs by the movement of ions between the two electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Better surface finish and higher accuracy depend on which of the factors below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical composition of the electrolyte",
            "b) Current density",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Proper chemical composition of electrolyte and proper current density are responsible for better surface finish and accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "For alloys, which type of electrolyte is used in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single component",
            "b) Double component",
            "c) Multi component",
            "d) Triple component"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depending up on the elements in an alloy multi component electrolytes are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "Nickel can be machined with 100% current efficiency, when current density value is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 A/cm2",
            "b) 25 A/cm2",
            "c) 45 A/cm2",
            "d) 80 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nickel is a metal suggested by Khayry, which can be machined at 100% current efficiency, if current density is 25 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "When the electrolyte flow is low, what happens to the current efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) Increase and then decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ECM, if the electrolyte flow is low, current efficiency is reduced due to the accumulation of machining products within the gap."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "When machining Ti, in Nacl electrolyte, what values of current efficiencies are obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 20 %",
            "b) 20 – 30 %",
            "c) 30 – 50 %",
            "d) 50 – 80 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While machining Ti using NaCl electrolyte, current efficiencies of 10 – 20 percent are obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Options": [
            "7. State whether the following statement is true or false about electrolyte in ECM.",
            "“Machinability in ECM is enhanced, when electrolyte is heated.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Machinability is increased, when electrolyte is heated, as heating increases the specific conductivity of the electrolyte."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "In practice, what must be the temperature of electrolyte used in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 20oC",
            "b) 20 – 40oC",
            "c) 60 – 80oC",
            "d) 80 – 100oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Temperature of electrolyte used in ECM must not exceed 60 – 70oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "What is the value of moderate level of pH of electrolyte used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 2",
            "b) 2 – 4",
            "c) 4 – 10",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Moderate level of pH of electrolyte used in ECM range between 4 – 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "What must be the working voltage in Electrochemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 V",
            "b) 20 V",
            "c) 30 V",
            "d) 40 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electrolytes in ECM employ a working voltage up to 20 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Surface roughness depend on which of the following quantities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crystallographic irregularities",
            "b) Alloy composition",
            "c) Distribution of current density",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Surface roughness of machined surface in ECM depend on crystallographic irregularities, alloy composition, current density distribution, dislocations and grain boundaries."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "For a better surface finish, which type of current distribution is required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Even",
            "b) Uneven",
            "c) Even & Uneven",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: More even distribution of the current density leads to a better surface finish."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Between which values does the frontal gap’s surface roughness vary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.02 to 0.13 µm",
            "b) 0.30 to 1.90 µm",
            "c) 1.93 to 2.64 µm",
            "d) 2.73 to 4.26 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface roughness varies between 0.30 to 1.9 µm for frontal gap area."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Between which values does the side gap’s surface roughness vary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) >1 µm",
            "b) >3 µm",
            "c) >5 µm",
            "d) >7 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Surface roughness value is 5 µm or more for side gap areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "In Electrochemical machining, larger grain size causes which type of finish?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smoother",
            "b) Rougher",
            "c) Finer",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ECM, larger grains cause rougher finish than finer grains."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "Which type of gap width is necessary for a higher degree of accuracy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very small",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A small gap width represents a high level of accuracy. Very small gap width results in sparks and short circuits."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Accuracy of machining is affected by, which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material",
            "b) Gap voltage",
            "c) Feed rate",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Accuracy of the process is affected by material equivalent, gap voltage, feed rate, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Which properties of electrolyte does not affect the accuracy of the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Concentration",
            "c) Non-reactive",
            "d) Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electrolyte must be reactive in order to carry on the reactions that occur at the electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "For high process accuracy, which of the following factors are needed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High feed rate",
            "b) High conductivity",
            "c) High feed rate & High conductivity",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a higher degree of accuracy, there must be high feed rates and highly conductive electrolytes."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Tool insulation that __________ the side machining action is needed in the process of ECM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limits",
            "b) Enhances",
            "c) Maintains",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tool insulation is needed, which limits the machining of other sides of work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "If the current density is high as required, what type of machining occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitting",
            "b) Polishing",
            "c) Etching",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the current density is relatively high as required, then polishing occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "What happens when the current density is low in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitting occurs",
            "b) Etching occurs",
            "c) Pitting & Etching occurs",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When current density is lower than optimum, then etching and pitting occurs which are undesired."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Fine dimensional control can be obtained if throwing power of electrolyte is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Throwing power of electrolyte must be less in order to obtain a fine dimensional control."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Passivation is done on electrolytes in order to form which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passive layer on machined parts",
            "b) Passive layer on cathode",
            "c) Passive layer on machined parts & cathode",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Passivation is done on the electrolytes in order to form a passive film on machined parts."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "If there is an increase in the electrolyte flow, what happens to the rate of film formation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An increase in electrolytic solution flow decreases the anodic product formation, which reduces the rate of film formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "What are the typical dimensional tolerances for frontal gaps in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.01 mm",
            "b) ± 0.025 mm",
            "c) ± 0.13 mm",
            "d) ± 0.25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dimensional tolerances obtained for frontal gaps are ± 0.130 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance values for the side gap in ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.01 mm",
            "b) ± 0.025 mm",
            "c) ± 0.13 mm",
            "d) ± 0.25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dimensional tolerances obtained for side gaps are ± 0.25 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "What are the typical dimensional tolerances obtained in ECM when there is proper control of machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.01 mm",
            "b) ± 0.025 mm",
            "c) ± 0.13 mm",
            "d) ± 0.25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dimensional tolerances obtained by proper machining are ± 0.025 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "It is difficult to machine inner radii smaller than __________ and outer radii less than ________ in ECM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 mm, 0.2 mm",
            "b) 0.5 mm, 0.8 mm",
            "c) 0.8 mm, 0.5 mm",
            "d) 0.2 mm, 0.1 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is difficult to machine inner radii < 0.8mm and outer radii < 0.5mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "What is the value of the overcut that is obtained using ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3 mm",
            "b) 0.5 mm",
            "c) 0.7 mm",
            "d) 0.9 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An overcut of 0.5 mm is obtained when machined using ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "If there is a change in the selected machining conditions, it will have impact on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process accuracy",
            "b) Surface finish",
            "c) Process accuracy & Surface finish",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Selected machining conditions should remain unchanged, because, it will have a direct impact on accuracy and surface finish."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Surface roughness depends on current density, which is affected by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tool feed rate",
            "b) Gap voltage",
            "c) Work piece material",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Roughness depend on current density, which is affected by tool feed rate, gap voltage, work material, pH number, temperature, conductivity and pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Machining conditions leading to high accuracy are associated with ________ surface roughness and ________ productivity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater, greater",
            "b) Smaller, greater",
            "c) Greater, smaller",
            "d) Smaller, smaller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Accuracy is associated with smaller surface roughness and greater machining productivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Non stationary behaviour of ECM is due to, which of the factors below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas generation",
            "b) Heating",
            "c) Passivation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Non stationary behaviour of ECM is due to the inter electrode gap conditions such as gas generation, passivation, heating and other electrode reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "For large components, actual machining time constitutes to how much percentage of the total machining time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Actual machining time of large components constitutes to a high percentage of total machining time."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "What happens to the product cycle time, if the machining performance is improved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the machining performance is improved, the time take for a product to complete its production cycle, decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "The cost of additional control hardware remain a _________ fraction of total machining cost.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Large",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cost of additional control hardware is very less, which constitutes to a small fraction in total machining cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "With an increase in unmanned machining hours, what happens to the efficiency of ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Reduces",
            "c) Decreases",
            "d) Increase and then decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Increase in unmanned machining hours lead to a raise in efficiency of ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Options": [
            "9. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the process control of ECM.",
            "“In Electrochemical machining, increase in unmanned machining hours reduces the possibility of integration of process with CAD/CAM systems.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An increase in unmanned machining hours, enhances the process integration with CAD/CAM systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which type of damage is caused by deterioration which is caused by spark?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reparable",
            "b) Irreparable",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Deterioration by sparking may cause irreparable damage to the work pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Which of the following use ECM for different applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas turbines",
            "b) Jet engines",
            "c) Bio medical implants",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ECM has its applications in industries such as gas turbines, jet engines, automobiles, medical etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes can be done using ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Die sinking",
            "b) Profiling and contouring",
            "c) Drilling and trepanning",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ECM can be used for die sinking, trepanning, drilling, contouring, grinding and profiling."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which of the following material cannot be machined using ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High strength alloys",
            "b) Hardened steels",
            "c) Nonconductive materials",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ECM can be used for machining high strength alloys and hardened steels which led to many cost-saving applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "ECM is used to _________ the sharp edges produced after rough cuts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enhance",
            "b) Dull",
            "c) Improve",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Using deburring process through ECM, sharp edges are dulled, which are produced after rough cuts."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "ECM is usually characterized as low accuracy machining, for which of the following reason?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrow gap width",
            "b) Wider gap width",
            "c) High current densities",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ECM is usually characterized as low accuracy machining because of its wider machining gap."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "In micro ECM, which of the following is used as micro tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrolyte jet",
            "b) Electrodes",
            "c) Power supply",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrolyte jet in micro ECM acts as the micro tool for machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Micro ECM is used to machine which type of parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large parts",
            "b) Micro parts",
            "c) Normal sized parts",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Micro ECM is used to machine micro parts which can be from micro scale to mesoscale in size."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Which of the following produces small indents and cavities using micro ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moving the work piece",
            "b) Switching the pulse current",
            "c) Moving the work piece & Switching the pulse current",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Indentation and cavitation can be done using micro ECM by moving the work piece or switching the pulse current."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "What fraction of tool will always be in contact with the work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Half",
            "b) Full",
            "c) No contact",
            "d) Quarter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tool does not have any contact with the work piece in Electro chemical machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "How much amount of wear is present in the tool used in Electrochemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No wear",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tool wear is absent in the tool used in ECM, since tool has no contact with the work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Compared to other processes, machining is done at __________ voltages for high rates of material removal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) High",
            "d) very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ECM, machining is done at low voltages, when compared to other processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Very small dimensions, up to which value can be controlled using ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 mm",
            "b) 0.05 mm",
            "c) 0.07 mm",
            "d) 0.12 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to less electrode gap very small dimensions up to 0.05 mm can be controlled."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Complicated profiles can be machined in how many operations in Electrochemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single",
            "b) Double",
            "c) Triple",
            "d) Multiple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One of the main advantage of ECM is, complicated profiles can be machined in a single operation itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "How much amount of thermal damage occurs to the work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Large",
            "c) No thermal damage",
            "d) Negligible amount"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the temperatures are very low, no thermal damage occurs to the work piece material."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials can be machined using ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hard nonconductive materials",
            "b) Hard conductive materials",
            "c) All nonconductive materials",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hard conductive materials can be machined and nonconductive materials cannot be machined using ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "What are the requirements of labour for machining purpose in Electrochemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In electrochemical machining, labour requirements are low compared to conventional or traditional machining practices."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "How much amount of energy is consumed in Electro chemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very small",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) Large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Very huge amount of energy is required for ECM, which is nearly 100 times required for turning or drilling of steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "How are material removal rates of ECM, when compared to that of conventional methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slower",
            "b) Faster",
            "c) Same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ECM, rates of material removal are slow compared to conventional methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Options": [
            "11. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the limitations of ECM.",
            "“In ECM, cleaning and oiling of work piece need not be done after machining.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Work piece needs to be cleaned and oiled just after the machining is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the limitations of electro chemical machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removal of hydrogen",
            "b) Handling the electrolyte",
            "c) Energy consumption",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Removal of hydrogen, handling and containing the electrolyte and energy consumption are some of the limitations of ECM."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "13. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the limitations of ECM.",
            "“In electrochemical machining, duplicating the tool is easier.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Duplication of tool is difficult in ECM, since it has side machining effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Electro chemical machining process cannot produce which of the following mentioned below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drilled holes",
            "b) Deburred edges",
            "c) Sharp edges",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electro chemical machining cannot produce sharp internal or external edges."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Pumping of electrolyte through the narrow gaps causes, which type of forces on tool and work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Negligible",
            "d) No force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrolyte pumping through the narrow gaps gives rise to a large amount of forces on tool and work pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "If electro chemical machining is applied under appropriate conditions, how much amount of health dangers can occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small amount",
            "b) Limited amount",
            "c) Large amount",
            "d) Very large amount"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Occupational health dangers are limited if ECM is done at appropriate conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Which of the following are some of the bad impacts on environment while using ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrolyte splashing",
            "b) Toxic gases release",
            "c) Precipitation of solid matters",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrolyte splashing, precipitation of solid matter, and toxic gas release is very harmful to the environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which of the following parts of the body can be contaminated while using ECM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skin",
            "b) Eyes",
            "c) Skin & Eyes",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Contamination of skin and eyes may occur due to electrolyte splashing and toxic gas release."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "During deburring and die sinking which of the following electrolyte gives high surface quality and accuracy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NaNO3",
            "b) HNO3",
            "c) NaCl",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By using NaNO3, deburring and die sinking can be done with more accuracy and high qualities are obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Dissolution of metal containing chrome results in which of the toxic compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toxic chromate",
            "b) Ammonia",
            "c) Toxic chromate & Ammonia",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dissolution of metal containing chromate results nitrate reduction at cathode tool, which in turn produces toxic chromate and ammonia."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "Slurries mixing with toxic compounds produce, which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid precipitates",
            "b) Liquid solutions",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slurries which mix with toxic compounds such as chromate and ammonia precipitates solid matter in the electrolyte solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "What should be done to the electrolyte with solid matter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Can be reused",
            "b) Disposed off",
            "c) No disposing is necessary",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electrolyte which contain the solid precipitates needs to be disposed immediately, in order to avoid any damage to the environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the environmental impacts of ECM.",
            "“In ECM, accumulation of toxic compounds is due to nitrate reduction at tool cathode.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When chromate containing metals dissolute, nitrate accumulate at cathode tool, which results in toxic chromate and ammonia compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ECDR in advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrochemical Dissolution",
            "b) Electrochemical Drilling",
            "c) Electrochemical Degradation",
            "d) Electrochemical Devastation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of ECDR is Electrochemical Drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "What are the values of diameters produced using Electrochemical drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.2 mm",
            "b) 1 to 20 mm",
            "c) 30 to 50 mm",
            "d) 60 to 100 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Value of diameter produced using Electrochemical drilling, ranges between 1 to 20 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "What are the feed rates used in Electrochemical drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 0.6 mm/min",
            "b) 0.6 to 1 mm/min",
            "c) 1 to 5 mm/min",
            "d) 6 to 15 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Value of feed rates used in Electrochemical drilling, range between 1 to 5 mm/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Of the following, which type of electrodes is used as tool in ECDR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tubular electrodes",
            "b) Flat electrodes",
            "c) Cylindrical electrodes",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ECDR, tubular electrodes are used as cathodic tools for making holes in the materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "The electrolyte is pumped the ________ of tool and exits through _________ of tool.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centre, side",
            "b) Side, centre",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Usually, electrolyte is pumped from centre and exits from side machining gap and vice-versa can also be done in back pressure process."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Material is removed using which part of the electrode in ECDR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only front",
            "b) Only side",
            "c) Front and side",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Material is removed at the frontal gaps and also dissolution takes place at the side machining gaps of the cathodic tool and work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Overcut produced in ECRD is difference between which of the following parameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diameter of tool, diameter of hole",
            "b) Diameter of hole, diameter of tool",
            "c) Depth of tool, diameter of tool",
            "d) Diameter of tool, depth of tool"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Overcut is the difference between the diameter of hole produced in work piece and the diameter of tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "For high machining accuracy and smaller diametrical oversize, which type of feed rates are required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High feed rates are recommended for smaller diametrical oversize and more accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "What happens to the overcut size, if we use the electrolyte flow mode under backward pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Increase and then decrease",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If we use backward pressure for electrolyte flow, the overcut size decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "What are the values of pressure, used in backward pressure mode of electrolyte flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.12 MPa",
            "b) 0.15 to 0.46 MPa",
            "c) 0.6 to 2 MPa",
            "d) 5 to 12 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To reduce overcut size, reverse flow of electrolyte can be used under backward pressure mode, whose value ranges between 0.6 to 2 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "What happens to the electrolyte conductivity if the gap increases, in ECDR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ECDR, as the gap increases, the electrical conductivity increases and the dissolution of material increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Electrolyte back pressure _________ the flow lines on work piece machined using ECDR.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enhances",
            "b) Eliminates",
            "c) Maintains",
            "d) Increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrolyte back pressure eliminates the flow lines on the machined surfaces which is a major advantages of ECDR."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "What happens to the roundness error if we use the rotation of ECDR tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Remains same",
            "c) Decreases",
            "d) Enhances"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Roundness error decreases, if the tool is rotated in ECDR, since it ensures the homogenous flow of electrolyte in the machining gaps."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "If sparking occurs due to very less gap between work surfaces, which parts gets damaged?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tool",
            "b) Work piece",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sparking, which occur due to very less gap between tool and work piece, which damages both the parts in ECDR."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Current efficiencies <100 percent may be related to, which of the following incidents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas evolution",
            "b) Passive oxide film formation",
            "c) Less dissolution",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Current efficiencies less than 100 percent may be related to gas evolution, passive oxide formation, which in turn lead to less dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "What is the full form of STEM in advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small Tool Electrode Machining",
            "b) Small Tube Electrode Manufacturing",
            "c) Shaped Tube Electrolytic Machining",
            "d) Shaped Tube Electrode Machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Full form of STEM in advanced machining processes is Shaped tube electrolytic machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Material is removed on which basis, in Shaped tube electrolytic machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dissolution",
            "b) Vaporization",
            "c) Abrasion",
            "d) Erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In STEM, dissolution takes place when a potential difference is applied between the anodic work piece and cathodic tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used as electrolytes in STEM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphuric acid",
            "b) Nitric acid",
            "c) Hydrochloric acids",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrolytes used in STEM are sulphuric acid, nitric acid and hydrochloric acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of electrolyte dissolved in water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 5%",
            "b) 10 – 25%",
            "c) 40 – 70%",
            "d) 75 – 90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Concentration of electrolyte, used in STEM, is 10 – 25% weight in water."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "What may be the temperature of sulphuric acid used in the STEM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 oC",
            "b) 21 oC",
            "c) 38 oC",
            "d) 50 oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The temperature of sulphuric acids used in the STEM process may be around 38 oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "What may be the temperatures of acids used, other than sulphuric acid, in STEM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 oC",
            "b) 21 oC",
            "c) 38 oC",
            "d) 50 oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Temperature of acids used in STEM, other than sulphuric acid, is about 21 oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "What are the values of pressures used for electrolyte in STEM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 100 kPa",
            "b) 150 – 250 kPa",
            "c) 275 – 500 kPa",
            "d) 600 – 750 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Values of pressure used in the STEM process, range between 275 – 500 kPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "What are the voltage values used in the STEM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 4 V",
            "b) 8 – 14 V",
            "c) 16 – 24 V",
            "d) 28 – 34 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In STEM, voltage values used for the process to carry on, range between 8 – 14 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Compared to the forward voltages, how are the reverse voltages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.1 times",
            "b) 0.1 – 1 times",
            "c) 1 – 10 times",
            "d) 10 – 100 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reverse voltages used in STEM are 0.1 – 1 times the forward voltages, used in STEM."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of the following values, does the feed rate range between?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.1 mm/min",
            "b) 0.25 – 0.5 mm/min",
            "c) 0.75 – 3 mm/min",
            "d) 5 – 7.5 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Feed rates used in STEM, range between 0.75 – 3 mm/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "What may the hole sizes, that can be machined using STEM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.02 – 0.3 mm",
            "b) 0.5 – 6 mm",
            "c) 8 – 20 mm",
            "d) 50 – 76 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The hole sizes that can be machined using STEM process, range between 0.5 – 6 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance values for a 1.5 mm diameter hole, which is machined using STEM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.025 mm",
            "b) ± 0.050 mm",
            "c) ± 0.075 mm",
            "d) ± 0.100 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diametrical tolerance value increases with the increase in hole diameter, which varies as – ± 0.050 mm for 0.6 mm diameter hole, ± 0.075 mm for 1.5 mm diameter hole and ± 0.100 mm for 6 mm hole diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Which of the following parts can be machined using STEM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbine blade cooling nozzles",
            "b) Fuel nozzles",
            "c) Starting holes for wire-EDM",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: STEM has its applications in jet engines and gas turbine parts such as cooling nozzles for turbine blades, fuel nozzles and any holes where EDM recast is undesirable."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the advantages of STEM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth to diameter ratio of 300",
            "b) Non parallel holes can be drilled",
            "c) No recast layer",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Main advantages of STEM are depth to diameter ratio of 300, non-parallel holes can be drilled, no recast layer are produced, shaped and curved holes can be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "What are the limitations of STEM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Used for corrosion resistant materials",
            "b) Hazardous waste is generated",
            "c) Complex machining and tooling systems",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Some of the limitations of STEM are only used for corrosion resistant materials, hazardous wastes are generated, special work place environment are required, complex machining and tooling systems are required."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of ES drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro stream",
            "b) Electrical shaped",
            "c) Electron shaped",
            "d) Electric shock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of ES drilling is Electrostream drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "This Electrostream drilling is used when we cannot drill which of the following type of holes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Too deep holes by EDM",
            "b) Small holes by STEM",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ES drilling is used to drill finer holes which are too deep to be produced by EDM and too small to be drilled by STEM."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "What is the value of diameter of glass nozzle used in Electrostream drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.02 mm",
            "b) 0.025 – 0.5 mm",
            "c) 0.5 – 0.75 mm",
            "d) 0.75 – 1.25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrostream drilling uses a gas nozzle, whose diameter ranges between 0.025 – 0.5 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Compared to the required diameter of the hole, how is the nozzle diameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smaller",
            "b) Larger",
            "c) Same as required",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diameter of nozzle used is smaller than the hole size required to be drilled in work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as the cathodic tool in ES drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Titanium base",
            "b) Platinum wire",
            "c) Glass nozzle",
            "d) Work piece"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike the case of STEM process, which uses coated Ti tube as cathode, ES drilling used platinum wire as cathode electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "What is the concentration of electrolytes that are commonly used in ES drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 10wt %",
            "b) 12 to 20wt %",
            "c) 23 to 30wt %",
            "d) 34 to 50wt %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Commonly used electrolytes have a concentration between 12 to 20wt %."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Options": [
            "7. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding ES drilling.",
            "“In ES drilling, hydrochloric acid is used for machining aluminium and its alloys.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrochloric acids are used for machining Al and its alloys and sulphuric acid is recommended for other metals."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the metals, which can be machined using sulphuric acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon steels",
            "b) Haste alloy",
            "c) Inconel",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Haste alloy, Rene alloy, Inconel, carbon and stainless steels are the materials machined using sulphuric acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "What are the values of electrolyte pressure recommended for ES drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 – 100 kPa",
            "b) 100 – 250 kPa",
            "c) 275 – 400 kPa",
            "d) 500 – 750 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electrolyte pressure values must range between 275 – 400 kPa for ES drilling to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Which of the following parameters must be carefully monitored for satisfactory machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acid temperature",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Concentration",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Acid temperature, pressure, concentration and feed rate are to be carefully monitored for satisfactory machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "What are the values of voltages used in ES drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 40 V",
            "b) 40 to 70 V",
            "c) 70 to 150 V",
            "d) 150 to 300 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Voltage values used in ES drilling, range between 70 to 150 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "What are the values of feed rates used in ES drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.5 mm/min",
            "b) 0.75 to 2.5 mm/min",
            "c) 3 to 4.5 mm/min",
            "d) 5 to 7.5 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Feed rate values used in ES drilling, range between 0.75 to 2.5 mm/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Higher material removal rates are associated with _________ feed rates and _________ tool diameters.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Larger, smaller",
            "b) Smaller, larger",
            "c) Smaller, smaller",
            "d) Larger, larger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rates of material removal are high, when feed rates are high and larger tool diameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "What are the normal hole depth tolerance values in ES drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.03 mm",
            "b) ± 0.05 mm",
            "c) ± 0.07 mm",
            "d) ± 0.09 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The normal hole depth tolerances obtained in ES drilling, range between ± 0.05 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "How many holes can be drilled simultaneously using ES drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One hole",
            "b) Two holes",
            "c) Three holes",
            "d) Multiple holes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Depending upon the size of diameters, multiple holes can be drilled using ES drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of ECJD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrochemical Jet Dimensioning",
            "b) Electrochemical Jet Drilling",
            "c) Electrical Jet Drilling",
            "d) Electrical Jet Dimensioning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of ECJD is Electrochemical Jet Drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "What is the value of diameter-to-depth ratio obtained using ECJD process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:10",
            "b) 2:25",
            "c) 1:12",
            "d) 1:100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electrochemical jet drilling is the process used for producing fine holes, having diameter to depth ratio of 1:12."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Compared to the diameter to depth ratio of ES drilling, how is ECJD’s ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower",
            "b) Higher",
            "c) Same as ES",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ES drilling has a diameter to depth ratio of 1:100, while ECJD has a ratio of 1:12."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "How is the material removed in Electrochemical jet drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using Platinum wire",
            "b) Using Ti coated electrode",
            "c) By spraying electrolyte",
            "d) Using glass nozzle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Material is removed by spraying electrolyte through the cathode, in Electrochemical jet drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "What is the material removal mechanism used in Electrochemical jet drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasion",
            "b) Dissolution",
            "c) Vaporization",
            "d) Erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrochemical dissolution is the means of material removal in Electrochemical jet drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "What are the values of voltages used in Electrochemical jet drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 to 200 V",
            "b) 200 to 400 V",
            "c) 400 to 800 V",
            "d) 800 to 1600 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The optimum range of voltages used in Electrochemical jet drilling are between 400 to 800 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "The lower limit of the hole size in ECJD, is determined by which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smallest hole",
            "b) Pressure required",
            "c) Amount of overcut",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The lower limit of hole size depend on smallest hole that can be drilled in cathodic nozzle, pressure required for pumping electrolyte and the overcut amount."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding ECJD.",
            "“In ECJD, diameter of hole produced, depend up on the throwing power of electrolyte.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diameter of the hole produced, depend up on the throwing power of electrolyte."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Compared to the diameter of the electrolyte jet, how are the produced hole diameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 times",
            "b) 3 times",
            "c) 4 times",
            "d) 5 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ECJD, the holes produced are nearly 4 times that of the electrolyte jet diameter used in the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "What is the value of the ratio of hole diameter to capillary diameter in ECJD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, ratio of hole diameter to capillary diameter in ECJD is 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "What are the values of tapers produced in Electrochemical jet drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 2 included angles",
            "b) 5 to 10 included angles",
            "c) 10 to 15 included angles",
            "d) 20 to 30 included angles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Electrochemical jet drilling tapers produced are about 5 to 10 included angles."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "12. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding ECJD?",
            "“In ECJD, there is no need of room for exit of electrolyte.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ECJD, enough room is required for the exit of electrolyte, preferably in the form of spray."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "How much part of tool needs to be in contact with work piece for removal of material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quarter",
            "b) Half",
            "c) Full",
            "d) No contact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As this is an electrochemical dissolution process, electrodes should not be in contact in order to avoid sparking."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, full form of ECDB is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrochemical Drill buffing",
            "b) Electrochemical Dimension Breaking",
            "c) Electrochemical Deburring",
            "d) Electrochemical Dimensioning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In advanced machining processes, full form of ECDB is Electrochemical Deburring."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes can be used for deburring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water blasting",
            "b) Abrasive flow machining",
            "c) Electrochemical deburring",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different methods used for deburring include vibratory and barrel finishing, tumbling, water blasting, Abrasive flow machining, Electrochemical deburring and many more."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "In the following electrodes, on which one the process of deburring takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cathode",
            "b) Anode",
            "c) Cathode & Anode",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Anode is the electrode, on which, the process of deburring is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Burrs are removed at which amount of current densities below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) High",
            "d) Medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: High current densities are required to remove the burrs from the work pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "After deburring is done, which of the following is formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat surfaces",
            "b) Controlled radius",
            "c) Sharp edges",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dimensions of the part are changes by the removal of burrs leaving a controlled radius."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "To which components mentioned below, ECDM can be applied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spline shafts",
            "b) Milled components",
            "c) Drilled holes",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ECDB can be applied to gears, spline shafts, milled components, drilled holes, and punched blanks."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "What are the values of deburring speeds used in ECDB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 to 200 mm/min",
            "b) 200 to 400 mm/min",
            "c) 400 to 500 mm/min",
            "d) 500 to 700 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Values of speeds of deburring, range between 400 to 500 mm/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "What are the normal cycle times for deburring process using ECDB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 20 s",
            "b) 30 to 45 s",
            "c) 50 to 70 s",
            "d) 80 to 100 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The normal cycle times are between 30 to 45 s after which, spindle is retracted and part is removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "What is the value of burr height that can be removed using ECDB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 mm",
            "b) 0.3 mm",
            "c) 0.5 mm",
            "d) 0.7 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Burr height of around 0.5 mm can be removed using ECDB process."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Burr is removed to a radius of _________ in ECDB process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.04 mm",
            "b) 0.05 to 0.20 mm",
            "c) 0.25 to 0.40 mm",
            "d) 0.50 to 0.75 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Burr of height 0.5 mm to a radius of 0.05 to 0.2 mm can be removed using ECDB."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "What is the value of surface roughness obtained in Electrochemical deburring process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 1 µm",
            "b) 1 to 2 µm",
            "c) 2 to 4 µm",
            "d) 5 to 8 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Surface roughness obtained in ECDB process is about 2 to 4 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "What is the value of pressure of electrolyte used in ECDB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 0.2 MPa",
            "b) 0.3 to 0.5 MPa",
            "c) 0.7 to 0.9 MPa",
            "d) 1.1 to 1.5 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pressure of electrolyte used in ECDB is maintained between 0.3 to 0.5 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "What is the value of applied voltage used in ECDB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5 V",
            "b) 5 to 11 V",
            "c) 12 to 24 V",
            "d) 25 to 50 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Value of voltage used in ECDB process ranges from 12 to 24 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "What are the values of current densities used in ECDB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 5 A/cm2",
            "b) 5 – 10 A/cm2",
            "c) 10 – 15 A/cm2",
            "d) 15 – 20 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Current densities used in ECDB process range between 5 – 10 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Which of the following electrolyte can be used for deburring process in ECDB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NaNO2",
            "b) NaNO3",
            "c) NaCl",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sodium nitrite, sodium nitrate and sodium chloride are the electrolytes used in ECDB process."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "What are the values, of inter electrode gaps so that machining occurs easily?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.1 mm",
            "b) 0.1 to 0.3 mm",
            "c) 0.3 to 0.5 mm",
            "d) 0.5 to 0.7 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The inter electrode gap maintained in ECDB process, range between 0.30 – 0.50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "In order to produce a proper radius, by how much should the tool tip overlap the machined area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 to 1 mm",
            "b) 1 to 1.5 mm",
            "c) 1.5 to 2 mm",
            "d) 2 to 2.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ECDB, the tool tip should overlap the machined area by 1.5 to 2 mm in order to produce a proper radius."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials can be machined using ECDB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon steels",
            "b) Copper alloys",
            "c) Aluminium alloys",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the materials mentioned above, can be machined using ECDB process."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "In ECDB process, rotating and feeding the tool electrode __________ the deburring process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enhances",
            "b) Degrades",
            "c) Damages",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotating and feeding the tool in ECDB process, enhances the process of deburring."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Electrochemical deburring ensures which of the following factors after removal of burrs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Required accuracy",
            "b) Proper radius",
            "c) Clean edge",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ECDB ensures the removal of burrs art required accuracy, uniformity, proper radius and clean edges."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the advantages of using ECDB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased product quality",
            "b) Reduced labour cost",
            "c) Increased reliability",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Increased product quality and reliability, reduced labour costs, elimination of costly hand deburring etc.., are some of the advantages of ECDB."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Options": [
            "11. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the advantages of ECDB.",
            "“In ECDB, automation does not contribute to productivity.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrochemical deburring can be automated for higher productivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "In advanced machining processes, what is the full form of EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro discharge Machining",
            "b) Electro discharge Manufacturing",
            "c) Electrical dimensioning Machining",
            "d) Electrode dimensions Manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full form of EDM in advanced machining processes is, Electrodischarge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "The evolution of wire EDM took place in which part of history?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1940s",
            "b) 1950s",
            "c) 1960s",
            "d) 1970s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Evolution of wire EDM in 1970s was due to powerful generators, new wire electrodes, improved machining intelligence and better flushing."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Machining speeds have gone up to how many times after the invention of EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ten",
            "b) Twenty",
            "c) Thirty",
            "d) Fifty"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Machining speeds have gone up to 20 times after the invention of EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "By using EDM, how much percentage of machining costs can be reduced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 %",
            "b) 20 %",
            "c) 30 %",
            "d) 50 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: EDM decreased the machined cost at least by 30 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "After invention of EDM, surface finish have improved by how much factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 15",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface finish have been improved by a factor of 15 after the invention of EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Cavities with, which of the following factors can be produced using Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thin walls",
            "b) Fine features",
            "c) Thin walls & Fine features",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cavities with thin walls and fine features can be machined using EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following geometries can be machined using EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple",
            "b) Complex",
            "c) Difficult to cut",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrodischarge machining can be used for simple as well as complex geometries."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding EDM.",
            "“In EDM, process is affected by hardness of material.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: EDM process is not affected by the hardness of material."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "How much amount of burr is produced in this process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 %",
            "b) 40 %",
            "c) 70 %",
            "d) No burr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electro discharge machining is a burr free process."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Which of the following mechanisms is used for material removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro discharge erosion",
            "b) Magnetic abrasion",
            "c) Electro chemical dissolution",
            "d) Mechanical erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Material is removed by electro-discharge erosion (EDE) in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "What is the value of order of frequency applied between the two electrodes in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 kHz",
            "b) 3 kHz",
            "c) 5 kHz",
            "d) 7 kHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnitude of frequency applied between the electrodes in EDM is about 5 kHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "What are the magnitude of voltages used in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 20 V",
            "b) 20 to 120 V",
            "c) 120 to 220 V",
            "d) 220 to 320 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In EDM, the magnitude of voltages range between 20 and 120 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "What are the values of gaps between the electrodes in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 – 0.05 mm",
            "b) 0.01 – 0.5 mm",
            "c) 0.1 – 5 mm",
            "d) 1 – 15 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In EDM, very small gaps that range between 0.01 – 0.5 mm are maintained."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "How is material removed in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melt and evaporate",
            "b) Corrode and break",
            "c) Mechanical erosion takes place",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, material is melted and then evaporated."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "What is the radius of channel, when electrical breakdown occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 µm",
            "b) 6 µm",
            "c) 8 µm",
            "d) 10 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In EDM, the electrical breakdown occurs in dielectric in a channel of radius about 10 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding EDM.",
            "“In EDM, negative ions (electrons) collide with positive ions to generate heat.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, electrons collide with neutral atoms producing positive ions and further electrons."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "What are the values of temperature that are obtained while machining using EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000 to 3000ᵒC",
            "b) 4000 to 6000ᵒC",
            "c) 8000 to 12000ᵒC",
            "d) 15000 to 20000ᵒC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The temperatures obtained when the ions reach their respective electrodes, range between 8000ᵒC and 12000ᵒC."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "What range of heat fluxes are obtained while machining using EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1017 W/m2",
            "b) 1019 W/m2",
            "c) 1024 W/m2",
            "d) 1027 W/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heat flux up to the value of 1017 W/m2 are obtained in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "What is the duration of sparks that are produced in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 – 1 µs",
            "b) 0.1 – 2000 µs",
            "c) 0.2 – 100 ms",
            "d) 100 – 2000 ms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Duration of spark in Electro discharge machining is about 0.1 to 2000 µs."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "10. State whether the following statement is true or false about material removal in EDM.",
            "“In EDM, high pressures allow the metal to evaporate.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: High pressures in EDM try to prevent the super-heated metal from evaporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "What are the values of pressure of the plasma in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Up to 2 atm",
            "b) Up to 20 atm",
            "c) Up to 200 atm",
            "d) Up to 2000 atm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pressure on the plasma channel rises to values as high as 200 atm when dielectric evaporates."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "At the end of pulse, super-heated metal evaporates _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Explosively",
            "b) Normally",
            "c) Periodically",
            "d) Occasionally"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the end of pulse, pressure drops suddenly and super-heated metal evaporates explosively."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "After the explosion is over, how is the debris carried away?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporation",
            "b) Fresh dielectric",
            "c) Old dielectric",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Debris is carried away by the fresh dielectric that rushes in. "
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "The layer formed when unexpelled molten metal solidifies is known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reabsorbed layer",
            "b) Recast layer",
            "c) Unevaporated layer",
            "d) Condensed layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unexpelled molten metal solidifies to form a layer known as recast layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Amount of material removed from anode and cathode depend on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrons",
            "b) Positive ions",
            "c) Electrons & Positive ions",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The amount of material removed from electrodes depend on the contribution of the charged ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "What happens when the electron current predominates in the discharge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More anodic removal",
            "b) More cathodic removal",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When electron current predominates the electrical discharge, anodic material removal is greater than cathodic material."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Between what values mentioned below, do the discharges and sparks usually vary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 and 10,000",
            "b) 500 and 500,000",
            "c) 500,000 and 1,000,000",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frequency of discharges or sparks generally vary between 500 and 500,000 sparks per second."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "What is the value of gap maintained between the electrodes when we use servo mechanism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 100 µm",
            "b) 100 – 200 µm",
            "c) 200 – 500 µm",
            "d) 500 – 1000 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In EDM, value of gap maintained between the electrodes range between 200 and 500 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Based on the electrode gap, which of the following electric pulses are generated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open Circuit pulses",
            "b) Sparks",
            "c) Arcs",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Based on the electrode gap, electric pulses are distinguished which are – circuit pulses, sparks, arcs and short circuits."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding EDM.",
            "“In Electro discharge machining, electric pulses generated affect the material removal.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, electric pulses generated have an impact on the material removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Open gap voltages contribute to how much amount of material removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 %",
            "b) 50 %",
            "c) 70 %",
            "d) No contribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Open gap voltage that occur at too large distances do not contribute to any material removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "When the electrode gap is too small or electrodes are in contact, how much material is removed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 30%",
            "d) No material removed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When electrodes come in contact with one another, short circuits occur and material removed is not possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Which components mentioned below are affected due to arcs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece",
            "b) Tool",
            "c) Work piece & Tool",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Arcs are believed to occur at same spots on electrode surfaces which damage both tool and work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "Which of the following pulses contribute to the desired material removal in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open circuit pulses",
            "b) Short circuits",
            "c) Arcs",
            "d) Sparks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sparks are the one which contributes to the desired material removal in Electro discharge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "Which of the following are main components of EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dielectric system",
            "b) Servomechanism",
            "c) Power supply",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Main components of machining system in EDM are – dielectric system, power supply and servomechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "What is the function of feed-control system in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant gap",
            "b) Supply power",
            "c) Dielectric fluid supply",
            "d) Work piece holding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Feed control system is used to maintain constant gap between electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "What is the use of power supply system in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant gap",
            "b) Supply power",
            "c) Dielectric fluid supply",
            "d) Work piece holding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Power supply system is used to supply pulses at certain voltages, current, on time and off time."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "What is the function of dielectric circulation unit in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant gap",
            "b) Supply power",
            "c) Dielectric fluid supply",
            "d) Work piece holding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dielectric circulation unit is used to supply dielectric fluid for flushing."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are used as electrodes in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graphite",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Brass",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the materials mentioned above, can be used as electrodes in Electro discharge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "Metals with _________ melting point and _________ electrical conductivity are chosen as tools in EDM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low, good",
            "b) Low, bad",
            "c) High, good",
            "d) High, bad"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In EDM, metals with high melting point and good electrical conductivity are used as tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Copper has _________ Electro discharge machining wear and _________ conductivity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good, better",
            "b) Good, worse",
            "c) Bad, better",
            "d) Bad, worse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cu is the metal which has better conductivity and good electro discharge machining wear."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Which of the following tungsten carbides are used as electrodes in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silver tungsten",
            "b) Copper tungsten",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both Silver tungsten and copper tungsten are the tungsten carbides used in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Options": [
            "9. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding materials used in Electro discharge machining.",
            "“In metals, copper graphite has less electrical conductivity than graphite.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Copper graphite has better electrical conductivity than graphite."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Brass metal ensures which type of sparking conditions in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stable",
            "b) Unstable",
            "c) Unsteady",
            "d) Insecure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Brass is a type of metal which ensures stable sparking conditions in Electro discharge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "In addition to the feed of tool, Electro discharge machining tool can have which type of motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscillatory",
            "b) Rotary",
            "c) Vibrational",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In addition to feed, the tool electrode may have rotary or orbiting motion."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Which of the following parameters determines the size of cavities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of electrode",
            "b) Radius of orbit",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Size of electrode and radius of orbit determines the size of cavities in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Electrode orbiting ________ the flushing of dielectric fluid in Electro discharge machining.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improves",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Reduces",
            "d) Degrades"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The additional orbiting motion of electrodes helps in improving the flushing by creating a pumping effect of dielectric liquid."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Quality of hole produced by orbiting motion is _________ to that obtained by using stationary electrode.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inferior",
            "b) Superior",
            "c) Lower",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Quality of hole produced by orbiting motion is superior to that obtained by using stationary electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "In EDM, electrode polarity depends up on which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece",
            "b) Electrode material",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, electrode polarity depends on both work piece and electrode material."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "Which one among the following, is the most important factor in determining the tool wear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melting point",
            "b) Boiling point",
            "c) Power supplied",
            "d) Feed rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In EDM, melting point is the most important factor in determining the tool wear."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "Electrode wear ratios can be expressed as, which of the following wears?",
        "Options": [
            "a) End wear",
            "b) Side wear",
            "c) Corner wear",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrode wear ratios are expressed as end wear, corner wear, side wear and volume wear."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "The term no wear in EDM occurs when electro-to-work piece wear ratio is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) <1%",
            "b) <3%",
            "c) <5%",
            "d) <10%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, no wear is the term used when the electrode-to-work piece ratio is less than 1%."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the other factors that influence the electrode wear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voltage",
            "b) Current",
            "c) Electrode material",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In EDM, electrode wear depends on the factors such as voltage, current, electrode material and polarity."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Options": [
            "5. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding wear in EDM.",
            "“In EDM, electrode wear is less dominant when it comes to micromachining applications.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrode wear is more when it comes to micromachining applications in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding wear in EDM.",
            "“In EDM, corner wear ratio does not depend on type of electrode material.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In EDM, corner wear ratio depend on the material of electrode used."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "In Electro discharge machining, highest wear ratio is associated with which type of melting point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, lowering of the melting point of electrode material results in high wear ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a function of dielectric in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flush particles",
            "b) Cool the section",
            "c) Maintain voltage",
            "d) Provide insulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flushing particles, providing insulation and cooling the sections that are heated, are the functions of dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the main requirements of dielectric fluids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity",
            "b) High flash point",
            "c) Minimum odour",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adequate viscosity, high flash point, oxidation stability, minimum odour, low cost and good electrical discharge are the main requirements of dielectric fluids."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used as dielectric fluids in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerosene",
            "b) Silicon fluids",
            "c) Distilled water",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dielectric fluids used are kerosene, silicon fluid, ethylene glycol, water in emulsions and distilled water."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "In EDM, inadequate flushing will not result in which of the following consequences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arcing",
            "b) Debris removal",
            "c) Decrease electrode life",
            "d) Increased production time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Inadequate flushing in Electro discharge machining results in less removal or no removal of debris."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which methods below, are used for introducing the dielectric in machining gap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal flow",
            "b) Reverse flow",
            "c) Jet flushing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Four methods namely normal flow, reverse flow, jet flushing and immersion flushing are used for introducing dielectric."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Few large holes are _________ than many small flushing holes in Electro discharge machining.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Worse",
            "b) Better",
            "c) Well",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Many small holes are better than a few large holes in machining thorough the EDM process."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "14. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the dielectric in EDM.",
            "“In EDM, flushing through the tool is more preferred than side flushing.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flushing through the tool is preferred than side flushing for deep cuts."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "In Electro discharge machining, which type of dielectric flow mentioned below is desirable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unsteady flow",
            "b) Steady flow",
            "c) Unstable flow",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In EDM, steady dielectric flow on the entire electrode-work piece interfaces is most desirable."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Metal is removed on which of the components in electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrode tool",
            "b) Work piece",
            "c) Electrode tool & Work piece",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, material is removed from both tool and work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "On which of the following components, does the MRR depend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece",
            "b) Electrode tool",
            "c)  Electrode tool & Work piece",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Material removal rate not only depends on work piece material but also the tool material."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors influence the material removal rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse condition",
            "b) Electrode polarity",
            "c) Machining medium",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors such as pulse conditions, electrode polarity and machining medium also affect the material removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "In Electro discharge machining, materials with low melting point have which type of material removal rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, materials having low melting point have high material removal rates and vice-versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "In Electro discharge machining, materials with low melting point have which type of surface roughness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rough",
            "b) Smooth",
            "c) Fine",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, materials having low melting point have high rougher surfaces and vice-versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "What are the values of material removal rates in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 to 0.1 mm3/min",
            "b) 0.1 to 400 mm3/min",
            "c) 400 to 1000 mm3/min",
            "d) 1000 to 5000 mm3/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In EDM, material removal rates range from 0.10 to 400 mm3/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "What happens to the material removal rate if the sparks are very less in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Increase and then decrease",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In EDM, if sparks generated are less then material removal rate decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "What is the relation between the melting point and the material removal rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly Proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Indirectly proportional",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, material removal rate is inversely proportional to the melting point."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "What happens to the crater size if we increase the current keeping the pulse time constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Decrease and increase",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By keeping pulse time constant and increasing current, crater size also increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "What happens to the crater size if we decrease the pulse time keeping the current constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Increase and decrease",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By decreasing pulse time and keeping current constant, crater size also decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "On which of the following factors do the craters depend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical properties",
            "b) Mechanical properties",
            "c) Composition of medium",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In EDM, craters depend on the physical and mechanical properties of material and composition of medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "The maximum depth of damaged layer is how many times that of average surface roughness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 time",
            "b) 2 times",
            "c) 2.5 times",
            "d) 3 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depth of damaged layer is two and half times the average surface roughness value."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "What happens to the surface roughness values if the MRR increases in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Decrease and increase",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In EDM, the surface roughness values increases linearly with increase in the material removal rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the surface roughness in EDM.",
            "“In EDM, graphite electrodes produce smoother surfaces than metal ones.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In EDM, graphite electrodes produce rougher surfaces than that of the metal ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "In Electro discharge machining, what happens to the surface finish if the pulse energy is decreased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduces",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Improves",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, the surface finish improves if the pulse energy is decreased."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "Using of a mate electrode in Electro discharge machining _____________ the surface roughness of material.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Enhances",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By using a mate electrode in Electro discharge machining, the surface roughness values are decreased."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "What happens to the surface roughness if oxygen gas is introduced in the gap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Decrease and then increase",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In EDM, surface roughness increases with the supply of oxygen gas in gaps."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "By how much percent surface roughness is reduced if we use proper dielectric flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 75%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, if we use a proper dielectric fluid flow, surface roughness is decreased by 50 percent."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance values obtained by machining using EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 10 mm",
            "b) ± 15 mm",
            "c) ± 25 mm",
            "d) ± 40 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tolerance values of ± 25 mm are obtained when we machine components using EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "How much extra tolerances are achieved when we choose proper variables?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 5 mm",
            "b) ± 10 mm",
            "c) ± 15 mm",
            "d) ± 20 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Extra tolerances of ± 5 mm are obtained with a proper choice of process variables."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "What are the values of temperatures obtained in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 to 2000 oC",
            "b) 2000 to 4000 oC",
            "c) 4000 to 8000 oC",
            "d) 8000 to 12000 oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperature attained while machining in Electro discharge machining are from 8000 to 12000 oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "What is the value of thickness of recast layer obtained when power of 5 µJ is given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 µm",
            "b) 3 µm",
            "c) 5 µm",
            "d) 7 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a power of 5 µJ is given, recast layer thickness of 1 µm is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "What are the values of thickness of recast layers in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 to 0.025 µm",
            "b) 0.01 to 0.25 µm",
            "c) 1 to 25 µm",
            "d) 10 to 250 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, the value of thickness of recast layers ranges from 1 to 25 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "In Electro discharge machining, some annealing of the work piece can be expected __________ the machined surface.",
        "Options": [
            "a) On",
            "b) Just below",
            "c) Above",
            "d) At bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Annealing of some part of the work piece in EDM can be expected just below the machined surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "The depth of the annealed surface is __________ to the amount of power used in machining operation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Exponential",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The depth of annealed surface in EDM is proportional to the amount of power used."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "What are the values of thickness of annealed surface obtained while machining using EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 25 µm",
            "b) 50 to 200 µm",
            "c) 200 to 500 µm",
            "d) 500 to 1000 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Values of annealed surface thickness range from 50 µm to 200 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "In EDM, choosing electrodes that produce which type of machining reduces the annealing effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stable",
            "b) Unstable",
            "c) Uneven",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Electro discharge machining, choosing the electrodes which produce more stable machining reduces the annealing effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "What happens to the fatigue strength of alloys if altered surfaces are produced in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Reduces",
            "c) Enhances",
            "d) Improves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The altered surface layers that are produced in Electro discharge machining, significantly reduces the fatigue strength of alloys."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "The altered layers formed during the process of EDM consists of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tempered layers",
            "b) Heat affected zones",
            "c) Intergranular precipitates",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Altered layers consists of recast layers, tempered layers, HAZs and intergranular precipitates in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "During roughing process through Electro discharge machining, what is the thickness of layer formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <0.075 mm",
            "b) <0.125 mm",
            "c) <0.500 mm",
            "d) <0.750 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thickness of layer obtained after machining is <0.127 mm in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "During finishing process through Electro discharge machining, what is the value thickness of layer formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <0.075 mm",
            "b) <0.125 mm",
            "c) <0.500 mm",
            "d) <0.750 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The thickness of layer obtained during EDM finishing is <0.075 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes can be used for restoration of fatigue properties?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low-stress grinding",
            "b) Chemical machining",
            "c) Reheat treatment",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For removal of altered layers processes such as low-stress grinding, chemical machining, reheat treatment, metallurgical type coating and application of shot peening."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Options": [
            "13. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the HAZ in EDM.",
            "“In EDM, post treatment to recover fatigue strength is not recommended.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After machining using EDM, post treatment to restore the fatigue strength is recommended."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Which of the following shapes can be produced using Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex shapes",
            "b) Simple shapes",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electro discharge machining is used to machine complex shapes to a high degree of accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials can be machined using Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat resistant alloys",
            "b) Super alloys",
            "c) Carbides",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: EDM is used to machine materials such as carbides, heat resistant and super alloys which are difficult-to-machine materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the applications of Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Holes",
            "b) Slots",
            "c) Texturing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Micromachining of holes, slots, dies, texturing, milling, surface modification and mechanical pulsing are some typical applications of Electro discharge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the applications of EDM.",
            "“In advanced machining processes, the incorporation of EDM with CIM increased the length of time for unit operation.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The incorporation of EDM in CIM reduced the length of time per unit operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "Which type of electrode is used for drilling in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat electrode",
            "b) Cuboidal electrode",
            "c) Tubular electrode",
            "d) Spherical electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tubular electrode is mostly preferred in Electro discharge machining, for drilling purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "The dielectric fluid is flushed in thorough which part of the electrode in drilling in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interior hole",
            "b) Side gaps",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EDM drilling uses a tubular electrode which flushes the dielectric thorough the interior holes for removing debris."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Which type of holes can be produced through drilling using Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Irregular",
            "b) Curved",
            "c) Tapered",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Drilling of work piece using EDM produced holes which can be irregular, curved, tapered as well as inclined holes."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "What are the values of general feed rates used for drilling in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 mm/min",
            "b) 0.3 m/min",
            "c) 0.5 mm/min",
            "d) 0.7 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Usually a feed rate of 0.10 mm/min is used for drilling the work piece using Electro discharge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "What are range of diameter values obtained by drilling using EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.05 mm",
            "b) 0.1 to 0.5 mm",
            "c) 1 to 5 mm",
            "d) 10 to 15 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diameter values while drilled using Electro discharge machining, ranges from 0.10 to 0.50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "What are the values of overcuts left behind after drilling of work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.05 mm",
            "b) 0.1 to 0.5 mm",
            "c) 1 to 5 mm",
            "d) 10 to 15 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Overcut values from 0.01 to 0.05 mm are obtained after the drilling process in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Electro discharge sawing is an application of EDM which employs __________ as tool material.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel band",
            "b) Disc",
            "c) Steel band & Disc",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electro discharge sawing is an application of EDM which employs either steel band or disc as tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "When compared to the conventional abrasive sawing, how many times faster is the MRR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twice",
            "b) Thrice",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electro discharge sawing cuts the work piece material at the rates which are twice that of conventional abrasive sawing method."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "How much amount of burr is produce while machined using Electro discharge sawing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) No Burr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cuts produced in Electro discharge sawing have smaller kerf widths which hav no burrs in it."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "What are the values of finish obtained by machining work piece thorough Electro discharge sawing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 4 µm",
            "b) 6.3 to 10 µm",
            "c) 12.4 to 23 µm",
            "d) 25.6 to 40 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The finish obtained ranges from 6.3 to 10 µm when machined using Electro discharge sawing."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "What are the recast layer thickness values obtained in ED sawing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 to 0.022 mm",
            "b) 0.025 to 0.130 mm",
            "c) 0.236 to 0.352 mm",
            "d) 0.432 to 0.568 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The recast layer thickness values obtained from ED sawing range from 0.025 to 0.13 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Which of the following electrodes are used for machining spherical surfaces in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tubular electrodes",
            "b) Flat electrodes",
            "c) Cuboidal electrodes",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Simple tubular electrodes are used to machine convex and concave spherical surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "What are the values of dimensional accuracy obtained while machining spherical surfaces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 1 µm",
            "b) ± 3 µm",
            "c) ± 5 µm",
            "d) ± 7 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dimensional accuracy of ± 1 µm is obtained while machining spherical surfaces using EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "What are the surface roughness values obtained while machining spherical surfaces using Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <0.1 µm",
            "b) <0.3 µm",
            "c) <0.5 µm",
            "d) <0.7 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surface roughness values obtained while machining of spherical surfaces are <0.1 µm in Electro discharge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Which motion of tool is used for machining spherical surfaces in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscillatory",
            "b) Vibratory",
            "c) Rotary",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rotary motion tool is used for machining spherical surfaces of conducting ceramic materials in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Which type of electrodes are used for milling application in Electro discharge machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tubular type electrodes",
            "b) Cylindrical type electrodes",
            "c) Flat type electrodes",
            "d) Spherical type electrodes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Standard cylindrical electrodes are used for milling application in EDM process."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Which type of cavities can be machined using milling process by Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex cavities",
            "b) Simple cavities",
            "c) Simple & Complex cavities",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Simple cavities and complex cavities are machined by successive NC sweeps of electrode over the desired path."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "The simple electrodes are rotated at which speed for milling of work pieces in Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Simple electrodes are rotated at high speeds for milling in Electro discharge machining same as that of conventional milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "What happens to the dielectric flushing while milling tool is rotated at a high speed in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improved",
            "b) Worsen",
            "c) Reduced",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Milling by electro discharge machining enhances the dielectric flushing due to high speed rotation of tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Options": [
            "9. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the applications of EDM.",
            "“In EDM, milling process can machine complex shapes with sharp corners.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: EDM milling has a main limitation i.e.., it cannot machine complex shapes with sharp tools because of rotating tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the steps included in the die sinking process of EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CAD of electrode",
            "b) Electrode manufacturing",
            "c) Programming for die sinking",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Designing of electrode, then manufacturing, and programming of die sinking are the steps to be followed for die sinking process in EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "Wire EDM is a special form of Electro discharge machining which contains __________ electrode.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuously moving",
            "b) Periodically moving",
            "c) Discontinuously moving",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wire EDM is a special type of EDM which uses a continuously moving electrode for removal of material."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "Which path of the components in wire EDM determines the path to be machined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal worktable movement",
            "b) Vertical worktable movement",
            "c) Horizontal & Vertical worktable movement",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Horizontal movement of the work table determines the path to be machined in Wire Electro discharge machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are machined using Wire Electro discharge machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polycrystalline diamond",
            "b) Cubic Boronitride",
            "c) Matrix composites",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polycrystalline diamond (PCD), cubic boron nitride (CBN) and other matrix composites are the material than can be machined using wire EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "How much amount of burr is produce when we use Wire Electro discharge machining for machining of work pieces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) No burr",
            "d) Small amount"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Wire Electro discharge machining no burr is produced without any distortion while machining work pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "Which of the following industries use wire EDM for different applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical industry",
            "b) Aerospace industry",
            "c) Automobile industry",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Industries such as chemical, aerospace, automobile, nuclear etc.., use wire EDM for a wide variety of applications in their industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "While machining insulating ceramic materials using EDM, where is the sheet metal placed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Over material",
            "b) Below material",
            "c) Under material",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sheet metal is placed over the material in machining of insulating materials using EDM."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "Sparks occur between which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece and sheet metal",
            "b) Tool electrode and sheet metal",
            "c) Work piece and electrode",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sparks occur between sheet metal and tool electrode for macining insulating ceramics."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Texturing is applied to the steel sheets at which stages of cold rolling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial stages",
            "b) Middle stages",
            "c) Final stages",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the final stages of cold rolling, texturing is applied to the steel sheets."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "What is the full form of EDT in EDM processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro discharge Tinplating",
            "b) Electro discharge Texturing",
            "c) Electro discharge Tapping",
            "d) Electro discharge Turing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electro Discharge Texturing is a variant of EDM which is the full form of EDT."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the process variables for texturing process in EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse current",
            "b) Electrode polarity",
            "c) Dielectric type",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pulse current, polarity, dielectric, electrode material and roll rotation speed are some process variables of texturing."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "What are the values of current amplitudes used in EDT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2 to 1 A",
            "b) 2 to 10 A",
            "c) 20 to 100 A",
            "d) 40 to 200 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The values of current amplitudes in EDT range from 2 to 10 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "What are duration values of current amplitude in EDT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 1 µs",
            "b) 1 to 10 µs",
            "c) 10 to 100 µs",
            "d) 100 to 1000 µs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Duration of current amplitudes used for EDT range from 10 to 100 µs."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "What are the spindle rotation speeds used in EDT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 4 rpm",
            "b) 10 to 40 rpm",
            "c) 20 to 60 rpm",
            "d) 30 to 90 rpm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spindle rotation speeds for EDT process range from 10 to 40 rpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "What are the values of diameter which are machined using Micro-EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 to 0.01 mm",
            "b) 0.01 to 0.1 mm",
            "c) 0.1 to 1 mm",
            "d) 1 to 10 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Values of diameter in Micro-EDM range from 0.10 to 1.0 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "What happens to the machine capital cost in EDT when there is an increase in tool quantity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: With increase in tools quantity machine cost increases but texturing cost reduces."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "What is the value of depth to diameter ratio in Micro-Electro discharge machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10:1",
            "b) 5:2",
            "c) 4:3",
            "d) 2:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Value of the depth to diameter ratio in Micro-Electro discharge machining is about 10:1."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "What are the values of depths that can be machined using Micro-EDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 mm",
            "b) 10 mm",
            "c) 100 mm",
            "d) 1000 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Micro-Electro discharge machining can machine up to a depth of 100 mm in the work piece material."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "What are the machining rates used in Micro-EDM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 2 mm/min",
            "b) 1 to 20 mm/min",
            "c) 10 to 200 mm/min",
            "d) 100 to 500 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Machining rates used in Micro-EDM process range from 1 to 20 mm/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "What are the values of hole diameters obtained using Wire electro discharge grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 µm",
            "b) 3 µm",
            "c) 5 µm",
            "d) 7 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Values of hole diameters up to 5 µm can be obtained using Wire electro discharge grinding process."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "What are the feed rates used in WEDG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5 mm/min",
            "b) 5 to 10 mm/min",
            "c) 10 to 15 mm/min",
            "d) 15 to 20 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Feed rate values in WEDG process range from 5 to 10 mm/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a major difficulty in the Electro discharge machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proper sparks",
            "b) Abnormal discharges",
            "c) Optimum feed rates",
            "d) No burr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Avoidance of abnormal discharges has become a major difficulty in Electro discharge machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "What has been done to the off time when there is a no-load voltage of electric discharge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased",
            "b) Decreased",
            "c) Reduced",
            "d) Remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The off time of pulse is increased in order to avoid the abnormal electric discharges."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "In a simple application which of the following parameters are inputs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse duration and current",
            "b) Normal and abnormal pulses",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inputs used are pulse duration and current in a simple application."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "In a simple application which of the following parameters are outputs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse duration and current",
            "b) Normal and abnormal pulses",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Outputs used are normal and abnormal pulses in a simple application."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Which of the following are correlated with the machining conditions at output stage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Machining depth",
            "b) Surface roughness",
            "c) Accuracy",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Machining depth, surface roughness, accuracy are correlated with the machining conditions at the output stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "How are EDM’s levels of integration when compared to conventional machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slower rate",
            "b) Faster rate",
            "c) Same rate",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EDM’s levels of computer integration is at a slower rate when compared to conventional machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "Manufacturing of tool electrode undergoes which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Milling",
            "b) Turning",
            "c) Finishing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tool electrode manufacturing used in EDM has to undergo the basic production processes such as milling, turning and finishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "High temperatures produced in the working gap results in which of the following potentials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hazardous smoke",
            "b) Toxic vapours",
            "c) Aerosols",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperatures in the working gap increases leading to hazardous smoke, vapours and aerosols."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Hydro carbons present in the dielectric fluid have impact on which of the body parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eyes",
            "b) Teeth",
            "c) Skin",
            "d) Nails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydrocarbons present in dielectric fluids of EDM will have a negative impact on the skin in our body."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "What happens to the Electro discharge machining process under unfavourable working conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Will remain stable",
            "b) Explosion may occur",
            "c) Machining rate increases",
            "d) Nothing happens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Explosion occurs if Electro discharge machining is done under unfavourable process variables and conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Reduction in the electrical energy consumption will have impact on which aspects mentioned below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Environmental",
            "b) Economic",
            "c) Environmental & Economic",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reduction of electric energy consumption has economic as well as environmental benefits."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "What is the full form of LBM in advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laser Beam Manufacturing",
            "b) Laser Beam Machining",
            "c) Light Blast Manufacturing",
            "d) Light Beam Machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of LBM is Laser Beam Machining in the advanced machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "LBM offers a good solution for which material properties below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermal conductivity",
            "b) Specific heat",
            "c) Boiling temperature",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LBM offers good solution for material properties such as thermal conductivity, specific heat, melting and boiling temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "What is the abbreviation of Laser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Light allowed simple emission of radiation",
            "b) Light amplification by stimulated emission of radiation",
            "c) Light amplified simultaneous emission of rays",
            "d) Light amplified stimulated emanation of rays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Full form of laser is Light Amplification by Stimulated emission of radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the properties of a laser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highly collimated",
            "b) Monochromatic",
            "c) Coherent light beam",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Highly collimated, high monochromaticity and the coherence of the light beam are the properties of a laser."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "Laser beam machining uses which type of power sources for machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low power",
            "b) Low power",
            "c) Medium power",
            "d) High power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High power densities are used for the generation of laser and for machining  in Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Which of the following are different types of lasers used in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid-state ion",
            "b) Neutral gas",
            "c) Semiconductor",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Laser such as solid-state ion, neutral gas, molecular, semiconductor etc.., can be used in LBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Which types of lasers are used in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous wave",
            "b) Pulsed mode",
            "c) Continuous wave & Pulsed mode",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Laser may be in continuous wave (CW) or in Pulsed mode (PM) for machining in LBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "What is the wavelength value of Ruby laser used in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 633 nm",
            "b) 694 nm",
            "c) 856 nm",
            "d) 1064 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of wave length of Ruby laser used in Laser Beam machining is 694 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "What is the wavelength value of Nd-YAG and Nd-glass lasers used in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 633 nm",
            "b) 694 nm",
            "c) 856 nm",
            "d) 1064 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of wave length of Nd-YAG and Nd-glass lasers used in LBM is 1064 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "What is the wavelength value of neutral gas laser used in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 633 nm",
            "b) 694 nm",
            "c) 856 nm",
            "d) 1064 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of wave length of Neutral gas laser used in Laser beam machining is 633 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "What is the wavelength value of CO2 laser used in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.16 μm",
            "b) 1.6 μm",
            "c) 10.6 μm",
            "d)  106 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of wave length of CO2 laser used in Laser Beam machining is 10.6 μm."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "What are the values of wavelengths of GaAs laser used in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 – 200 nm",
            "b) 200 – 400 nm",
            "c) 600 – 700 nm",
            "d) 800 – 900 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The wavelengths of GaAs laser used in LBM range from 800 – 900 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "What are the values of wavelengths of Excimer laser used in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 – 200 nm",
            "b) 200 – 500 nm",
            "c) 600 – 700 nm",
            "d) 800 – 900 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wavelengths of Excimer laser used in LBM range from 200 – 500 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "What are the values of wavelengths of Argon laser used in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 – 230 nm",
            "b) 220 – 310 nm",
            "c) 330 – 530 nm",
            "d) 760 – 940 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wavelengths of Argon laser used in LBM range from 330 – 530 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "What is the material removal mechanism of Laser beam machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melt and evaporate",
            "b) Electro chemical corrosion",
            "c) Mechanical erosion of materials",
            "d) Electro chemical dissolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The material is removed by melting and evaporation in Laser Beam Machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "Physics of laser is very complex due to which of the reasons below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scattering loss",
            "b) Reflection loss",
            "c) Scattering & Reflection loss",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Physics of laser is very complex because of scattering and reflection losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "What happens when the heat is diffused into bulk material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phase change occurs",
            "b) Melting occurs",
            "c) Vaporization may take place",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The heat diffusion into bulk material causes phase change, melting or vaporization in the materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Options": [
            "4. State whether the following statement is true of false regarding LBM.",
            "“In LBM, high intensity laser beams are recommended for more material.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High intensity laser beams are not recommended since they form a plasma plume near surface of material."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "What happens to the process efficiency if plasma plumes are formed in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Enhances",
            "c) Decreases",
            "d) Improves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Laser beam machining, the process efficiency is reduced due the absorption and scattering loses when plasma plumes are formed."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Machining of LBM takes place when power density is ____________ than what is lost by conduction and radiation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater",
            "b) Smaller",
            "c) Lower",
            "d) Same as"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Machining of laser takes place when power density is greater than what is lost by conduction, convection and radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Which of the following phenomenon take place before melting and evaporating in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conduction",
            "b) Reflection",
            "c) Absorption",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Material in LBM is removed through several effects such as conduction, absorption, reflection following melting and evaporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "What happens to the material removal rate when reflectivity is higher?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Will decrease",
            "b) Will increase",
            "c) Will enhance",
            "d) Remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In LBM, as the reflectivity of the metals is increased the material removal rates of the process are decreased."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Reflectivity of the materials depends on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wave length",
            "b) Properties of material",
            "c) Surface finish",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reflectivity of the materials depends on wavelength, the properties of materials, surface finish and temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "How much amount of incident radiation is reflected at lower power densities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 percent",
            "b) 20 percent",
            "c) 50 percent",
            "d) 90 percent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Most of the metals reflect nearly 90 percent of incident radiation if the power densities are low."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "How are minimum energies required for plastics when compared to that required for metals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower than",
            "b) Higher than",
            "c) Same as",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum energies required for plastic are lower than that required for metals."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Which of the following has high machining speeds in Laser Beam Machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metals",
            "b) Non metals",
            "c) Metal alloys",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Non metallic material machine at higher speeds than metallic ones due to higher reflectivity in metallic materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the applications of Laser Beam Machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drilling",
            "b) Cutting",
            "c) Texturing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Drilling, cutting and grooving, texturing and structuring, milling and dressing etc.., are the applications of Laser beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Options": [
            "2. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the drilling using LBM.",
            "“Compared to LBM, conventional machining is more accurate and efficient.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Conventional machining is less sufficient than Laser Beam machining because of their material toughness."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "Other non-conventional processes lay behind Laser beam machining in drilling process because of which factors below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High cost",
            "b) Long lead times",
            "c) Low machining speeds",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Other non-conventional processes need high costs for tools, long lead times, and low machining speeds when compared to LBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "Laser drilling has proven to be more efficient in which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost",
            "b) Quality",
            "c) Reliability",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Laser drilling has proven to be an efficient one in terms of cost, quality, and reliability for large-scale production applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "Which of the following are different laser drilling processes in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct drilling",
            "b) Drill and ream",
            "c) Trepanning",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Laser drilling can be performed by three methods that are – direct (percussion) drilling, trepanning, drill and ream."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "The hole size in direct drilling depend up on which of the factors below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Input power",
            "b) Focusing adjustments",
            "c) Input power & Focusing adjustments",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hole size in the direct drilling method of Laser drilling process, depend on input power and focusing adjustments."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Which method mentioned below is used for drilling of large size holes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct drilling",
            "b) Drill and ream",
            "c) Trepanning",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trepanning method of laser drilling process is used for drilling large holes either by rotating or moving the part."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "What are the values of diameters obtained by using Laser drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0001 – 0.001 mm",
            "b) 0.001 – 0.01 mm",
            "c) 0.005 – 1.25 mm",
            "d) 1.5 – 10.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Values of diameters obtained by using Laser drilling process range between 0.005 – 1.27 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "What is the value the maximum optimum depth that can be machined using Laser drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.17 mm",
            "b) 1.7 mm",
            "c) 17.1 mm",
            "d) 171.7 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum depth obtained when by using laser drilling is about 1.7 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "What are the values of entrance angles that vary in Laser drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 1 oC",
            "b) 1 – 5 oC",
            "c) 15 – 90 oC",
            "d) 90 – 150 oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Values of the entrance angles in Laser drilling process range between 15 – 90 oC."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "The taper obtained in Laser drilling process is how much of the hole diameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 5%",
            "b) 5 – 20%",
            "c) 20 – 50%",
            "d) 50 – 90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Taper value obtained in Laser drilling process range between 5 – 20% of the hole diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "What is the depth-to-diameter ratio obtained in drilling process using Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10:1",
            "b) 20:1",
            "c) 50:1",
            "d) 80:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Value of the maximum depth-to-diameter ratio obtained in drilling using Laser beam machining is 50:1."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "What is the maximum value of drilling depth in trepanning method of laser drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7 mm",
            "b) 4.3 mm",
            "c) 6.4 mm",
            "d) 7.9 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The depth increases when we use a trepanning method for laser drilling process and that is about 6.40 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance values obtained when we use laser drilling process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 5%",
            "b) 5 – 20%",
            "c) 25 – 50%",
            "d) 50 – 80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tolerance values are will range between 5 – 20% of the diameters obtained in Laser drilling process."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "What is the value of minimum corner radius obtained by drilling in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.10 mm",
            "b) 0.25 mm",
            "c) 0.50 mm",
            "d) 0.65 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the minimum corner radius obtained while drilling using LBM is about 0.25 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Peak power should be increased in Laser drilling process by __________ pulse energy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing",
            "b) Decreasing",
            "c) Reducing",
            "d) Constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Required peak power in the laser drilling process can be obtained by increasing the pulse energy while keeping the pulse duration constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "Drilling of holes with larger pulse duration causes which effect to the holes produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enlarge holes",
            "b) Reduce hole size",
            "c) Decrease the depth",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Drilling the holes with larger pulse duration causes enlargement of the hole entrance."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "What are pulse duration values used for laser drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.25 ms",
            "b) 0.1 to 2.5 ms",
            "c) 1 to 25 ms",
            "d) 10 to 250 ms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Value of the duration of the pulse range from 0.1 to 2.5 ms."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "_________ pulse energy and _________ pulse duration are suitable for drilling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low, short",
            "b) Low, long",
            "c) High, short",
            "d) High, long"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In LBM, high energy pulses and low pulse duration are more suitable for hole drilling in aerospace materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the functions of assist gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removal of molten material",
            "b) Shield the lenses",
            "c) Better efficiency",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Assist are used to remove the molten material, it also shield the lenses from expelled material and they are also used for obtaining better process efficiencies."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "Selection of assist gas depends on which of the following properties of work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material",
            "b) Thickness",
            "c) Material & Thickness",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The selection of different assist gases depends on the work piece material and its thickness."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "Which of the following properties of material affect the quality of holes obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflectivity",
            "b) Absorption coefficient",
            "c) Thermal conductivity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Quality of holes depend on reflectivity, absorption coefficient, thermal conductivity, density, specific heat, and latent heat of material."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "What range of powers are used for cutting through steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 20 W",
            "b) 20 to 100 W",
            "c) 200 to 1000 W",
            "d) 1 to 20 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The power ranges from 200 W to 1 kW for cutting through steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "Which gas jet assisted process is suitable for most of the metals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen gas",
            "b) Nitrogen gas",
            "c) Helium gas",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oxygen-jet assistance is used for most metals, as the gas liberates additional energy by the exothermal chemical reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "What happens to the cutting speed with an increase in the work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Enhances",
            "d) Remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cutting speed of the process of drilling decreases with an increase in the thickness of the work piece material."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "What is the full form of LBT in the processes of LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laser Beam Tempering",
            "b) Laser Beam Templating",
            "c) Laser Beam Texturing",
            "d) Laser Beam Tinning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Full form of LBT is Laser beam texturing which is an application of Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Depth and the crater size depends on which of them below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy of beam",
            "b) Dwell time of beam",
            "c) Energy & Dwell time of beam",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depth and the crater size depend on the energy and the dwell time of beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "Where are the textured surfaces used that are obtained in LBT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mould makings",
            "b) Bearings",
            "c) Printer roll manufacturing",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Textured surfaces obtained in LBT are widely used in mold making, bearings and printer roll manufacturing."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "The roll is _________ and the laser beam is moved ________ along the roll.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stationary, axially",
            "b) Stationary, perpendicularly",
            "c) Rotated, axially",
            "d) Rotated, perpendicularly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In texturing process of LBT, the roll is rotated and laser is moved axially along the roll."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Options": [
            "15. State whether the following statement is true regarding the texturing in LBT.",
            "“In LBT, hardness of the material is a limitation to the process.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Laser beam texturing, hardness of material is not a limitation to the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the other applications of LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dressing of grinding wheels",
            "b) Scribing",
            "c) Micromachining",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dressing of grinding wheels, scribing, micromachining, controlled fracturing are some of the other applications of Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "How the grooves in grinding wheels are produced using laser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporation",
            "b) Damage of composite",
            "c) Evaporation & Damage of composite",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grooves on the grinding wheels are produced due to evaporation and damage of the composite wheel material."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Work piece tilting depends on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incident power",
            "b) Beam speed",
            "c) Groove direction",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Work piece tilting depends on the incident power, beam speed, groove direction, and optical absorption coefficient of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "What are the values of thickness used is fine cutting process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 to 0.05 mm",
            "b) 0.05 to 0.1 mm",
            "c) 0.5 to 15 mm",
            "d) 15 to 50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The thickness of material used in fine cutting process vary from 0.5 to 16 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "The advantages of excimer laser are due to __________ laser wavelength and _________ pulse duration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short, short",
            "b) Short, long",
            "c) Long, short",
            "d) Long, long"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The practical advantages of excimer laser are mainly due to short laser wavelength and pulse duration."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "Lasers of which type are used for modification of electronic components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High power",
            "b) Small spot size",
            "c) Short pulse length",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lasers of high power density, small spot size and short pulse length are useful devices for modification of electronic components."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "Material removal rates which are about mg/pulse produces which type of holes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow",
            "b) Deep",
            "c) Very deep",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In LBM, material removal at the rate of milligrams per pulse produces shallow holes in the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials can be easily separated by laser scribing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon",
            "b) Glass",
            "c) Ceramic",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Brittle materials such as silicon, glass and ceramics may be effectively shaped or separated by laser scribing."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Which type of holes can be drilled using Nd-YAG laser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small holes",
            "b) Large holes",
            "c) Small & Large holes",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nd-YAG laser can be used for drilling small holes as well as large holes by trepanning process."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Which type of laser can be used for direct drilling or percussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ruby laser",
            "b) Nd-YAG laser",
            "c) Ruby & Nd-YAG laser",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both Ruby and Nd-YAG laser can be used for direct (percussion) drilling purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "Which of the following lasers is used for cutting thick materials in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2 + gas assisted",
            "b) CO2 only",
            "c) Nd-YAG",
            "d) Ruby"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CO2 + gas assisted laser is used for cutting thicker materials in Laser beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "Which of the following lasers is used for slitting of thin metallic materials in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2 + gas assisted",
            "b) CO2 only",
            "c) Nd-YAG",
            "d) Ruby"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nd-YAG laser is used for slitting of thin metallic materials in Laser beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "Which of the following lasers is used for slitting of thin plastic materials in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2 + gas assisted",
            "b) CO2 only",
            "c) Nd-YAG",
            "d) Ruby"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CO2 laser is used for slitting of thin plastic materials in Laser beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Which of the following lasers is used for organics and non-metallic materials in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2 + gas assisted",
            "b) Pulsed CO2",
            "c) Nd-YAG",
            "d) Ruby"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pulsed CO2 laser is used for organics and non-metallic materials in Laser beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "Which of the following lasers is used for ceramic materials in LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulsed CO2",
            "b) Nd-YAG",
            "c) Pulsed CO2 & Nd-YAG",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both pulsed CO2 and Nd-YAG lasers can be used for ceramic materials in LBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid machining",
            "b) Low operating cost",
            "c) High equipment cost",
            "d) No tool wear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rapid machining, low operating cost and no tool wear are some of the advantages of Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "Which of the following systems is used for locating the hole accurately for alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical control system",
            "b) Optical laser system",
            "c) Measurement system",
            "d) Alignment system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Holes can be accurately located using optical laser system for alignment in Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "Very __________ holes with a ________ aspect ratio can be produced using Laser beam machining.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small, small",
            "b) Small, large",
            "c) Large, small",
            "d) Large, large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Laser beam machining, very small holes with large aspect ratios can be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "How are the machining times in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very slow machining times",
            "b) Slow machining times",
            "c) Moderate machining times",
            "d) Fast machining times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Machining is very much rapid and the setup times are economical in Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "How is the operating cost of the machines used in Laser beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Moderate",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The operating cost of the machines in LBM is low but the equipment cost itself is of high cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Options": [
            "6. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the advantages of LBM.",
            "“In LBM, difficult to cut machine material can also be machined.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A large variety of hard and difficult to cut materials can be machined using LBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "How much amount of tapers are occurred in Laser drilled holes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No taper",
            "b) Negligible amount of taper",
            "c) Some amount",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tapers are generally occurred in the direct drilling of holes using Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement regarding Laser beam machining is true or false.",
            "“In LBM, a blind hole of precise depth is easy to achieve.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A blind hole of precise is difficult to achieve in Laser beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "What is the maximum depth up to which holes can be drilled using LBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 30 mm",
            "c) 50 mm",
            "d) 70 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The thickness of the material that can be laser drilled is restricted to 50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "What is to be done to the adherent material which are found at exit holes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape them",
            "b) Leave away",
            "c) Remove them",
            "d) Flatten them"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adherent material found at the exit of holes has to be removed in LBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "What is the full form of EBM in the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro blast manufacturing",
            "b) Electron beam machining",
            "c) Electron beam manufacturing",
            "d) Electron blast manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of EBM is Electron beam machining in the advanced machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "The prototype of the machine used in EBM process was first introduced in which year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1924",
            "b) 1943",
            "c) 1947",
            "d) 1956"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Steigerwald was the scientist who designed a prototype machine of electron beam machining in 1947."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "When did the Electron beam machining come into the machining industry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1920s",
            "b) 1930s",
            "c) 1950s",
            "d) 1960s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Electron beam machining was introduced to the machining industry in the early 1960s."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the applications of EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drilling",
            "b) Cutting",
            "c) Engraving",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Drilling small holes, cutting, engraving, and heat treatment are some of modern applications of Electron beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "The tungsten filament cathode is heated to what temperatures in EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 to 1500 ᵒC",
            "b) 1500 to 2000 ᵒC",
            "c) 2500 to 3000 ᵒC",
            "d) 3500 to 5000 ᵒC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tungsten filament cathode is heated to 2500 to 3000 ᵒC in Electron beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "What are the values of currents used in EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 and 20 mA",
            "b) 20 and 100 mA",
            "c) 100 and 200 mA",
            "d) 200 and 400 mA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The values of the currents used in the Electron beam machining process are between 20 and 100 mA."
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "What are the values of current densities used in the process of EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 and 15 A/cm2",
            "b) 15 and 20 A/cm2",
            "c) 20 and 30 A/cm2",
            "d) 40 and 60 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The values of the current densities used in EBM lie between 5 and 15 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "Emission current depends up on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cathode material",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Voltage supply",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Emission current depends on the cathode material, temperature, and the high voltage in the process of Electron beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "What are the values of voltages used in the EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 V",
            "b) 50 V",
            "c) 150 V",
            "d) 200 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The values of voltages used in the process of electron beam machining is about 150 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "Which of the following lenses are used for refocussing the electrons in EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic lens",
            "b) Electronic lens",
            "c) Magnetic & Electronic lens",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Magnetic and electronic lenses are used to refocus the electrons in EBM process."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "What are the values of velocity maintained in the EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 118 x 103 m/s",
            "b) 228 x 103 m/s",
            "c) 338 x 103 m/s",
            "d) 448 x 103 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the velocity used in the process of electron beam machining is about 228 x 103 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "What are the values of power densities used in the EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.05 MW/mm2",
            "b) 0.55 MW/mm2",
            "c) 1.55 MW/mm2",
            "d) 2.55 MW/mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the power densities used in the process of electron beam machining are about 1.55 MW/mm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "What is the frequency of the pulse of electrons used in EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 Hz",
            "b) 102 Hz",
            "c) 103 Hz",
            "d) 104 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A pulsed electron beam at 104 Hz reduces the temperature of the work piece outside the region being machined."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "What are the values of material removal rates in EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 mm3/min",
            "b) 10 mm3/min",
            "c) 100 mm3/min",
            "d) 1000 mm3/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The values of the material removal rates in the process of electron beam machining are about 10 mm3/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "What are the values of the cavity diameters that are obtained in EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 to 20 µm",
            "b) 20 to 25 µm",
            "c) 30 to 35 µm",
            "d) 35 to 40 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The values of the cavity diameters range from 35 to 40 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the applications of EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hole drilling",
            "b) Slotting",
            "c) Perforation of thin sheets",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Drilling, perforation of thin sheets, slotting and integrated circuit fabrication are some of the applications of Electron beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "What is the value of largest diameter of the hole drilled on EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 mm",
            "b) 1.0 mm",
            "c) 1.5 mm",
            "d) 2.0 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum value of diameter that can be drilled using Electron beam machining is about 1.5 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "What is the value of maximum depth of the hole drilled on EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 20 mm",
            "c) 30 mm",
            "d) 40 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Value of the maximum depth that can be drilled using Electron beam machining is about 10 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "What is the range of depth-to-diameter ratio in Electron beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2:5 to 2:11",
            "b) 1:1 to 1:15",
            "c) 3:4 to 3:20",
            "d) 4:5 to 4:19"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The depth to diameter ratio in Electron beam machining will vary between 1:1 and 1:15."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "How many holes can be produced in perforation of thin sheets using EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 101 to 102",
            "b) 102 to 103",
            "c) 103 to 104",
            "d) 104 to 105"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Number of holes produced range from 104 to 105 per second in perforation using EBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "What is the value of energy required for bond breaking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 20kV",
            "b) 20 to 30kV",
            "c) 30 to 40kV",
            "d) 40 to 50kV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Value of the beam energy used for breaking bonds or cross linking them range from 10 to 20kV."
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "What is the value of pulse time used in EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.004 to 0.064 µs",
            "b) 0.04 to 0.64 µs",
            "c) 0.4 to 640 µs",
            "d) 4 to 64000 µs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Value of the pulse time of beam ranges from 4 to 64000 µs."
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "What is the value of frequency used in EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 – 0.016 Hz",
            "b) 0.01 – 16 Hz",
            "c) 0.1 – 16000 Hz",
            "d) 10 – 1600 kHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frequency of the pulse range between 0.1 and 16000 Hz in Electron beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "What is the tolerance value obtained in EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 10 %",
            "b) ± 20 %",
            "c) ± 30 %",
            "d) ± 40 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tolerances obtained in Electron beam machining is about ± 10 % of the depth of cut."
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the advantages of EBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drilling rates",
            "b) No distortion",
            "c) High accuracy",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main advantages of Electron beam machining are high drilling rates, no mechanical distortion, high accuracy and repeatability."
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "There is no limitation imposed on which of the following factors in EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material ductility",
            "b) Surface hardness",
            "c) Surface reflectivity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Electron beam machining, no limitation is imposed by work piece hardness, ductility, and surface reflectivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "How much is the capital equipment cost of equipment used in EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low cost",
            "b) Low cost",
            "c) Moderate cost",
            "d) High cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The capital equipment cost of the Electron beam machining is high compared to other machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "How are the production times for a material in electron beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very small",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Moderate",
            "d) Long"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Electron beam machining, long production times are required due to the generation of vacuum in the chamber for machining purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "Which type of thin cast layer is produced when we use EBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thin layer",
            "b) Thick layer",
            "c) No layer",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thin recast layer is produced in Electron beam machining which an added disadvantage to the machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "What is the full form of PBM in the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plasma Beam Manufacturing",
            "b) Plasma Beam Machining",
            "c) Plasma Blast Manufacturing",
            "d) Plasma Blast Machining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of PBM in the advanced machining processes is Plasma Beam Machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "When the Plasma Beam machining process came into the industrial world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1920s",
            "b) 1930s",
            "c) 1950s",
            "d) 1970s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Plasma Beam machining process came into the industrial world in the early 1950s as an alternative for the oxy-gas flame cutting process."
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "PBM is the only process which works faster in ________ steel than _________ steel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stainless, mild",
            "b) Mild, stainless",
            "c) Remains same all",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PBM is the only fabrication process which works faster in stainless steels compared to mild steels."
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "What is the temperature reached by cathode in order to produce plasma beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12000 ºC",
            "b) 18000 ºC",
            "c) 28000 ºC",
            "d) 40000 ºC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The temperature reached by cathode to produce plasma arc is about 28000 ºC in Plasma Beam Machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "What is the value of velocity of plasma jet in Plasma beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 m/sec",
            "b) 300 m/sec",
            "c) 400 m/sec",
            "d) 500 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the velocity of the plasma jet in Plasma beam machining is about 500 m/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "What is the value of material removal rate in Plasma Beam Machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 cm3/min",
            "b) 100 cm3/min",
            "c) 150 cm3/min",
            "d) 200 cm3/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The values of the material removal rates in Plasma beam machining will be nearly 150 cm3/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "What is the value of specific energy used in Plasma beam machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 W/(cm3-min)",
            "b) 200 W/(cm3-min)",
            "c) 300 W/(cm3-min)",
            "d) 400 W/(cm3-min)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the specific energy used in Plasma beam machining process is about 100 W/(cm3-min)."
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "What is the value of the power used in PBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 10 kW",
            "b) 2 – 200 kW",
            "c) 200 – 400 kW",
            "d) 400 – 700 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the power used in Plasma beam machining range from 2 to 200 kW."
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "What is the value of the voltage used in PBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 20 V",
            "b) 30 – 250 V",
            "c) 300 – 400 V",
            "d) 500 – 600 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of voltage in the Plasma beam machining processes is about 30 – 250 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": "What is the value of the current used in PBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Up to 200 A",
            "b) Up to 400 A",
            "c) Up to 600 A",
            "d) Up to 800 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the current used in PBM will be up to 600 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "What is the value of machining speed used in PBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 7.5 m/min",
            "b) 8.5 – 10.5 m/min",
            "c) 15.5 – 19.5 m/min",
            "d) 20.5 – 25.5 m/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of machining speed is about 0.1 – 7.5 m/min in Plasma beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "What is the maximum value of the thickness used in PBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 mm",
            "b) 200 mm",
            "c) 300 mm",
            "d) 400 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum value of the thickness used in the Plasma beam machining process is about 200 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the different shielded plasmas used in PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas-shielded plasma",
            "b) Water-shielded plasma",
            "c) Gas-shielded & Water-shielded plasma",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both gas-shielded plasma and water shielded plasma are used in the Plasma beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "Material removal rates depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece material",
            "b) Type of cutting",
            "c) Shielding gases",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Material removal rates in PBM depend on work piece material, type of cutting and the shielding gas."
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "A low power factors indicates __________ energy required and __________ removal rates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low, low",
            "b) Low, high",
            "c) High, low",
            "d) High, high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A low power factor in Plasma beam machining indicates low energy required and high material removal rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "What happens to the machining speed if the thickness of material is increased in PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Enhanced",
            "d) Remains same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Machining speed in Plasma beam machining reduces with an increase in the thickness of the work piece material."
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "What is the machining speed required for machining of 12mm thick plate with 220 kW energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 mm/min",
            "b) 1500 mm/min",
            "c) 2000 mm/min",
            "d) 2500mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Machining speed required for cutting 12-mm thick plate with 220 kW power is about 2500 mm/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "How much distortion is produced while machining using PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 30%",
            "d) No distortion is produced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Heat does not penetrate more than few microns from the edges of the cuts produced by machining using PBM that produce no distortion."
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "The cut edge of the material tends to be __________ than the base metal in PBM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smoother",
            "b) Harder",
            "c) Same as",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cut edge of material in PBM tends to be harder than the base metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "What is the thickness of the HAZ in PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 to 0.23 mm",
            "b) 0.25 to 1.12 mm",
            "c) 1.3 to 2.56 mm",
            "d) 2.73 to 5.26 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thickness of the HAZ obtained in PBM range from 0.25 to 1.12 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": "How much thickness of cracks may arise beyond HAZ due to rapid cooling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.6 mm",
            "b) 2.6 mm",
            "c) 3.6 mm",
            "d) 4.6 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cracks due to rapid cooling in PBM may extend beyond HAZ to a thickness of 1.6 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": "What are the values of tolerances obtained by using PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.6 mm",
            "b) ± 1.6 mm",
            "c) ± 2.6 mm",
            "d) ± 3.6 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The values of the tolerances obtained by using Plasma beam machining will be about ± 1.6 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 894,
        "Question": "What is the maximum thickness of the walls of tube machined using plasma arc?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 30 mm",
            "c) 50 mm",
            "d) 70 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum thickness of the wall tubes that can be produced using PBM is about 50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 895,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the advantages of PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No chemical",
            "b) Less harmful",
            "c) Operates cleanly",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Main advantages of Plasma bema machining are no complicated chemical analysis, less harmful and no harmful exposure and it operates cleanly."
    },
    {
        "id": 896,
        "Question": "Which of the following chemicals are used in PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Harmful chlorinated fluorocarbons",
            "b) Acid cleaning chemicals",
            "c) Dissolvable solvent chemicals",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plasma beam machining uses no harmful chlorinated fluorocarbons, acid cleaning chemicals or any dissolvable solvents."
    },
    {
        "id": 897,
        "Question": "How much amount of energy is required for machining using PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Moderate",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cost for operating the jobs in Plasma beam machining is less and also less energy is required for operating the machine in PBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 898,
        "Question": "What are the disadvantages of PBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large power supplies",
            "b) Heat produced",
            "c) Toxic fumes produced",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Large power for more thick materials, production of heat and toxic fumes are some of the main disadvantages of PBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 899,
        "Question": "What is the full form of IBM in the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion Beam Machining",
            "b) Ion Beam Manufacturing",
            "c) Ion Blast Machining",
            "d) Ion Blast Manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of IBM is Ion Beam Machining in the advanced machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 900,
        "Options": [
            "2. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding IBM.",
            "“In IBM, vacuum chamber is not necessary unlike that of Electron beam machining.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ion beam machining also requires a vacuum chamber like that required for Electron beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 901,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the components of Ion beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum chamber",
            "b) Voltage source",
            "c) Tungsten filament cathode",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Main components of IBM are vacuum chamber, voltage source, tungsten cathode filament, plasma source of argon atoms and lens."
    },
    {
        "id": 902,
        "Question": "How does the ions strike the work piece in machining using IBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oblique striking",
            "b) Normal incident striking",
            "c) Oblique & Normal incident striking",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ions may strike obliquely or at normal incidence in Ion Beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 903,
        "Question": "Number of atoms yielded in oblique cutting is __________ normal incidence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than",
            "b) Lesser than",
            "c) Same as",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Number of atoms yielded for an incident atom in oblique cutting is greater than normal incidence in IBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 904,
        "Question": "How much amount of energy is required for effective removal of atoms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5 eV",
            "b) 5 to 10 eV",
            "c) 10 to 15 eV",
            "d) 15 to 20 eV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: About 5 to 10eV of energy is required for effective removal of atoms."
    },
    {
        "id": 905,
        "Question": "Machining rates in IBM depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work piece material",
            "b) Ions type",
            "c) Incident angle",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The machining rates or yield depends on material to be machined, type of ions and incident angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 906,
        "Question": "What is the value of voltage required for machining in Ion beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 kV",
            "b) 2 kV",
            "c) 3 kV",
            "d) 4 kV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of voltage required for machining in Ion beam machining process is about 1 kV."
    },
    {
        "id": 907,
        "Question": "What are the values of current densities required in IBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25 mA/cm2",
            "b) 0.35 mA/cm2",
            "c) 0.55 mA/cm2",
            "d) 0.85 mA/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of current density of about 0.85 mA/cm2 is required for machining the work piece materials in Ion beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 908,
        "Question": "What is the value of beam diameter that is obtained in IBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 cm",
            "b) 3 cm",
            "c) 5 cm",
            "d) 7 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the beam diameter for machining the work piece material in Ion beam machining is about 5 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 909,
        "Question": "What are the dimensions that can machined on IBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 1 nm",
            "b) 1 to 10 nm",
            "c) 10 to 100 nm",
            "d) 100 to 1000 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Small dimensions as 10 to 100 nm can also be machined on Ion beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 910,
        "Question": "The slope of the side walls depends on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voltage supply",
            "b) Angle of incidence",
            "c) Flux",
            "d) Current density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of the sidewalls of the surface and its surface finish depend on the angle of incidence."
    },
    {
        "id": 911,
        "Question": "What are the accuracy levels that are obtained by using IBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 1.0%",
            "b) ± 2.0%",
            "c) ± 3.0%",
            "d) ± 4.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The accuracy levels that are obtained when machined the work piece using IBM is about ± 1.0 %."
    },
    {
        "id": 912,
        "Question": "What are the values of repeatability obtained in Ion beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 1.0%",
            "b) ± 2.0%",
            "c) ± 3.0%",
            "d) ± 4.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A repeatability of about ± 1 % are obtained while machining the work piece using Ion beam machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 913,
        "Question": "Surface texturing produces a cone-and-ridge like configuration on the order of which size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 µm",
            "b) 1 µm",
            "c) 1.5 µm",
            "d) 2 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface texturing produces a cone-and-ridge-like configuration on the order of 1 µm in size in Ion beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 914,
        "Question": "What is the value of surface finish obtained by using Ion beam machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <1 µm",
            "b) <3 µm",
            "c) <5 µm",
            "d) <7 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The smoothness of the surface finish obtained in Ion beam machining is less than 1 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 915,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the applications of IBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smoothing laser mirrors",
            "b) Polishing surfaces",
            "c) Shaping surface",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Smoothing of laser mirrors, polishing and shaping of optical surfaces are some of the applications of Ion beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 916,
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the applications of IBM.",
            "“In IBM, thickness can be reduced which affects the surface finish.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reduction of thickness of thin films can be done without affecting the surface finish."
    },
    {
        "id": 917,
        "Question": "What are the thickness values of silicon samples that can be thinned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5 µm",
            "b) 5 to 10 µm",
            "c) 10 to 15 µm",
            "d) 15 to 20 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thickness ranging from 10 to 15 µm can be thinned using IBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 918,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials can be textured using the IBM process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper",
            "b) Nickel",
            "c) Stainless steel",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Materials such as Copper, stainless steel, nickel, silver and gold can be used for producing textured cones using IBM."
    },
    {
        "id": 919,
        "Question": "How much amount of energies are required for removal of oxide layers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Larger",
            "c) Moderate",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Higher energies are needed for the removal of layer of oxides on the surfaces using Ion Beam machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 920,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ECG in the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro cardio graph",
            "b) Electro chemical grinding",
            "c) Electro chemical grooving",
            "d) Electric cathode grinding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The full form of ECG in the advanced machining processes is Electro chemical grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 921,
        "Question": "The grinding wheel used in the ECG process is of which charge given below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive charge",
            "b) Negative charge",
            "c) Neutral charge",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The abrasive grinding wheel used in the Electro chemical grinding process is negatively charged."
    },
    {
        "id": 922,
        "Question": "Which of the following mentioned below are utilized in the ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrolytic solution",
            "b) Abrasive grinding wheel",
            "c) Work piece",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electro chemical grinding utilizes the abrasive grinding wheel, the electrolytic solution and the work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 923,
        "Question": "Electro chemical grinding is ___________ Electro chemical machining.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superior to",
            "b) Inferior to",
            "c) Similar to",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process of Electro chemical grinding is similar to that of ECM except the cathode is a constructed grinding wheel."
    },
    {
        "id": 924,
        "Question": "What is the value of inter electrode gap maintained in ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) <0.015 mm",
            "b) <0.025 mm",
            "c) <0.035 mm",
            "d) <0.045 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the inter electrode gap maintained in Electro chemical grinding is 0.025 mm or less."
    },
    {
        "id": 925,
        "Question": "What is the value of the grit number of the abrasives used in ECG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 20",
            "b) 20 – 60",
            "c) 60 – 320",
            "d) 350 – 640"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the grit number of abrasive particles used in the ECG process are about 60 – 320."
    },
    {
        "id": 926,
        "Question": "Which of the following electrolytes are used for machining purpose in ECG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium nitrate",
            "b) Hydro chloric acid",
            "c) Nitric acid",
            "d) Potassium permanganate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally sodium nitrate is the electrolyte that is used for machining purpose in Electro chemical grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 927,
        "Question": "What are the values of surface speeds at which the wheel rotates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 to 15 m/s",
            "b) 10 to 20 m/s",
            "c) 20 to 35 m/s",
            "d) 40 to 60 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The speeds used in ECG will range from 20 to 35 m/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 928,
        "Question": "What are the values of current used in ECG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 50 A",
            "b) 50 to 300 A",
            "c) 300 to 600 A",
            "d) 600 to 1000 A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The values of current in Electro chemical grinding range from 50 to 300 A."
    },
    {
        "id": 929,
        "Options": [
            "10. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the material removal in ECG.",
            "“In ECG, material removal is not continuous using abrasive.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Abrasive particles continuously remove the material products from the working area in Electro chemical grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 930,
        "Question": "What is the value of gap voltage maintained in ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 10 V",
            "b) 4 to 40 V",
            "c) 40 to 400 V",
            "d) 500 to 5000 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the gap voltage in ECG process is 4 to 40 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 931,
        "Question": "What are the values of current densities used in the ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 60 A/cm2",
            "b) 60 to 120 A/cm2",
            "c) 120 to 240 A/cm2",
            "d) 240 to 480 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The values of current densities range from 120 to 240 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 932,
        "Question": "Current density depends on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Machined material",
            "b) Gap width",
            "c) Applied voltage",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The current density values in Electro chemical grinding depend on machined material, gap width and the applied voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 933,
        "Question": "What is the main mechanism of material removal in Electro chemical grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical erosion of material",
            "b) Electro chemical dissolution",
            "c) Melting and vaporization",
            "d) Electron removal from material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electro chemical grinding process removes the material mainly by electro chemical dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 934,
        "Question": "The grinding wheel is _________ and the work piece is ________ in ECG process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cathode, anode",
            "b) Anode, cathode",
            "c) Cathode, cathode",
            "d) Anode, anode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The grinding wheel is cathode and the work piece is anode in the Electro chemical grinding process."
    },
    {
        "id": 935,
        "Question": "Mechanical abrasion counts to how much amount of the material removal in ECG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5%",
            "b) 5 to 10%",
            "c) 10 to 15%",
            "d) 15 to 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Material removal through abrasion counts to 5 to 10% of the total material removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 936,
        "Question": "Removal rates of ECG process are how may time to that of the conventional machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 times",
            "b) 3 times",
            "c) 4 times",
            "d) 5 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The MRR of ECG process are nearly 4 times that of the conventional machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 937,
        "Question": "How much amount of burr is produce in Electro chemical grinding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less amount",
            "b) Moderate amount",
            "c) High amount",
            "d) No burrs are produced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Electro chemical grinding process is a burr free process which produce parts that are unstressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 938,
        "Question": "What are the volumetric removal rates that are obtained in ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 mm3/min",
            "b) 800 mm3/min",
            "c) 1600 mm3/min",
            "d) 3200 mm3/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The volumetric removal rates that are obtained in Electro chemical grinding process will be around 1600 mm3/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 939,
        "Question": "ECG is a hybrid machining process of which material removal mechanisms below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical abrasion",
            "b) Electro chemical dissolution",
            "c) Mechanical abrasion & Electro chemical dissolution",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ECG is a hybrid machining process which uses MA and ECD for material removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 940,
        "Question": "Action of abrasive grains depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric filed",
            "b) Transport of electrolyte",
            "c) Hydrodynamic effects",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Action pf abrasive grains in the gap depends on the electric field, transport of electrolyte and the hydrodynamic effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 941,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance value that are obtained by using ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.01 mm",
            "b) ± 0.03 mm",
            "c) ± 0.05 mm",
            "d) ± 0.07 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tolerance values that are obtained by using Electro chemical grinding are about ± 0.03 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 942,
        "Question": "Under special circumstances what are the tolerances obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.02 mm",
            "b) ± 0.04 mm",
            "c) ± 0.06 mm",
            "d) ± 0.08 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tolerance values of about ± 0.08 mm are obtained under special circumstances in Electro chemical grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 943,
        "Question": "What are the production tolerances obtained in ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.005 mm",
            "b) ± 0.015 mm",
            "c) ± 0.025 mm",
            "d) ± 0.035 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The production tolerances obtained by machining using Electro chemical grinding process is about ± 0.025 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 944,
        "Question": "The tolerance values in ECG depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrolyte flow",
            "b) Feed rate",
            "c) Metallurgy of material",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tolerance values depend on the electrolyte flow, feed rate and the metallurgy of work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 945,
        "Question": "What are the values of accuracies obtained in ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.025 mm",
            "b) ± 0.125 mm",
            "c) ± 0.225 mm",
            "d) ± 0.325 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The accuracy values obtained by using Electro chemical grinding process is about ± 0.125 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 946,
        "Question": "Which type of voltages are recommended for closer tolerances in ECG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Moderate",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lower voltages are recommended for closer tolerances, reduced overcut, sharp edges and bright surface finish in the process of Electro chemical grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 947,
        "Question": "What are the values of radii of corners obtained in ECG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.15 to 0.225 mm",
            "b) 0.25 to 0.375 mm",
            "c) 0.45 to 0.525 mm",
            "d) 0.55 to 0.675 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The values of radii of corner range from 0.25 to 0.375 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 948,
        "Question": "Surface finish in ECG depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal machined",
            "b) Abrasive size",
            "c) Wheel speed",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Surface finish in ECG process depend on metal being machined, abrasive grit size, wheel speed and feed rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 949,
        "Question": "What are the values of radii of corners obtained in ECG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 0.2 µm",
            "b) 0.2 to 0.3 µm",
            "c) 0.3 to 0.4 µm",
            "d) 0.4 to 0.5 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The values of surface finish range from 0.2 to 0.3 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 950,
        "Question": "What are the values of voltages used for better surface quality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 2 V",
            "b) 2 – 3 V",
            "c) 3 – 5 V",
            "d) 5 – 8 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Voltages ranging between 3 and 5 V can be used for better surface quality in ECG."
    },
    {
        "id": 951,
        "Question": "What are the machining speeds recommended for high surface quality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 250 mm/min",
            "b) 250 – 500 mm/min",
            "c) 500 – 750 mm/min",
            "d) 750 – 100 mm/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The machining speeds recommended for high surface quality are between 250 and 500 mm/min in ECG."
    },
    {
        "id": 952,
        "Question": "What are the applications of Electro chemical grinding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Milling the material",
            "b) Tool and cutter sharpening",
            "c) Cutting off",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The applications of electro chemical grinding are milling, grinding, cutting off, sawing, tool and cutter sharpening."
    },
    {
        "id": 953,
        "Question": "What are the advantages of machining in Electro chemical grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good surface quality",
            "b) Absence of distortion",
            "c) Longer wheel life",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Good surface quality, absence of distortion, longer wheel life etc.., are some advantages of Electro chemical grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 954,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the disadvantages of ECG process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High capital cost",
            "b) Limited to conductive materials",
            "c) Corrosive nature",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High capital cost, limited to conductive materials, corrosive nature etc.., are some disadvantages of ECG."
    },
    {
        "id": 955,
        "Options": [
            "15. State whether the following statement is true of false regarding ECG process.",
            "“In ECG process, filtering and disposal of electrolyte is not necessary.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Main disadvantage of ECG is to filter and dispose the electrolyte used in the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 956,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ECH in the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro chemical honing",
            "b) Electro chemical hammering",
            "c) Electro chlorinated hammering",
            "d) Electro chlorinated honing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of ECH in the advanced machining processes is Electro chemical honing."
    },
    {
        "id": 957,
        "Question": "Which of the following mechanisms are used in the hybrid machining of ECH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro chemical dissolution",
            "b) Mechanical abrasion",
            "c) Electro chemical dissolution & Mechanical abrasion",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MA and ECD are used in material removal of the hybrid process of ECH."
    },
    {
        "id": 958,
        "Question": "ECH has __________ material removal rates than conventional honing or the internal cylindrical grinding.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower",
            "b) Higher",
            "c) Same",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electro chemical honing has higher material removal rates than conventional honing and the internal cylindrical grinding processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 959,
        "Question": "Majority of the material is removed in which phase of ECH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro chemical dissolution",
            "b) Mechanical abrasion",
            "c) Electro chemical dissolution & Mechanical abrasion",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Majority of the material in Electro chemical honing is removed in electro chemical dissolution phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 960,
        "Question": "Which of the following electrolytes is used for ECH process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium chloride",
            "b) Sodium nitrate",
            "c) Hydrochloric acid",
            "d) Sulphuric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sodium nitrate (240 g/L) is mostly used than Sodium chloride (120 g/L) and other acid electrolytes in Electro chemical honing."
    },
    {
        "id": 961,
        "Question": "What is the value of electrolytic temperature maintained in ECH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18 ᵒC",
            "b) 28 ᵒC",
            "c) 38 ᵒC",
            "d) 48 ᵒC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the temperature of the electrolytic solution that is used in Electro chemical honing process is about 38 ᵒC."
    },
    {
        "id": 962,
        "Question": "What is the value of pressure of the electrolytic solution in ECH process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 kPa",
            "b) 10 kPa",
            "c) 100 kPa",
            "d) 1000 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the pressure of the electrolytic solution maintained in Electro chemical process is about 1000 kPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 963,
        "Question": "What is the flow rate of the electrolytic solution used in ECH process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 85 L/min",
            "b) 95 L/min",
            "c) 105 L/min",
            "d) 115 L/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of the electrolytic solution used in Electro chemical honing process is about 95 L/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 964,
        "Question": "What are the voltage values used in the process of ECH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 1 V",
            "b) 1 to 5 V",
            "c) 6 to 30 V",
            "d) 40 to 80 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The voltage values used in ECH range from 6 to 30 V."
    },
    {
        "id": 965,
        "Question": "What are the current density values that are used in ECH process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 165 A/cm2",
            "b) 235 A/cm2",
            "c) 385 A/cm2",
            "d) 465 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The current density values that are used in the process of Electro chemical honing are about 465 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 966,
        "Options": [
            "1. State whether the following statement is true or false about ECH process.",
            "“In ECH, improper electrolytic distribution will have no effect on any component.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Improper electrolytic distribution leads to geometric irregularities and errors in the process of Electro chemical honing."
    },
    {
        "id": 967,
        "Question": "The machining system employs which type of abrasive stone for removal of material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulsating",
            "b) Vibrating",
            "c) Reciprocating",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The machining system of the Electro chemical honing process employs a reciprocating abrasive stone for the removal of material."
    },
    {
        "id": 968,
        "Question": "What is the value of gap maintained in ECH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.025 to 0.075 mm",
            "b) 0.075 to 0.250 mm",
            "c) 0.250 to 0.750 mm",
            "d) 0.750 to 2.50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of gap maintained in electro chemical honing is between 0.076 and 0.250."
    },
    {
        "id": 969,
        "Question": "How much faster is MRR in ECH when compared to the conventional honing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 2 times",
            "b) 2 to 3 times",
            "c) 3 to 5 times",
            "d) 5 to 8 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MRR in ECH is nearly 3 to 5 times faster than conventional honing."
    },
    {
        "id": 970,
        "Question": "How much faster is MRR in ECH when compared to the conventional internal grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 times",
            "b) 4 times",
            "c) 6 times",
            "d) 8 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Material removal rate in ECH is nearly 4 times faster than that of the internal cylindrical grinding."
    },
    {
        "id": 971,
        "Question": "What are the tolerances that are achieved using ECH process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.001 mm",
            "b) ± 0.002 mm",
            "c) ± 0.003 mm",
            "d) ± 0.004 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the tolerances that are achieved during machining in ECH is about ± 0.003 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 972,
        "Question": "What are the surface roughness values obtained while we use ECH process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 0.2 µm",
            "b) 0.2 to 0.8 µm",
            "c) 0.8 to 1.6 µm",
            "d) 1.6 to 3.2 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the surface roughness range from 0.2 to 0.8 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 973,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "8. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding applications of ECH.",
            "“In ECH, the roundness errors are reduced compared to other processes.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the tool rotates and reciprocates the roundness errors are reduced in electro chemical honing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 974,
        "Question": "Tool reciprocation can be used to reduce which of the following effects on work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Taper",
            "b) Waviness",
            "c) Taper & Waviness",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tool reciprocation in Electro chemical honing is used to reduce taper and waviness errors."
    },
    {
        "id": 975,
        "Question": "",
        "Options": [
            "10. State whether the following statement is true or false regarding the process of ECH.",
            "“In ECH, the electro chemical dissolution phase introduces stresses.”",
            "a) True",
            "b) False"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electro chemical dissolution produces no stresses and automatically deburrs the part in Electro chemical honing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 976,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ECS in the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro chemical superfinishing",
            "b) Electro chemical scribing",
            "c) Electron cluster scribing",
            "d) Electron cluster superfinishing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of ECS in the advanced machining processes is Electro chemical superfinishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 977,
        "Question": "Which of the mechanisms combine to form this hybrid process of ECS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro chemical dissolution",
            "b) Mechanical scrubbing",
            "c) Electro chemical dissolution & Mechanical scrubbing",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electro chemical dissolution and mechanical scrubbing combined in the hybrid process of ECS."
    },
    {
        "id": 978,
        "Question": "How much amount of burr is produced in the process of ECS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 %",
            "b) 20 %",
            "c) 50 %",
            "d) No burr produced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Burr free components are produced in the process of Electro chemical superfinishing due to electro chemical dissolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 979,
        "Question": "MRR are reduced by how much amount in the presence of the oxide film?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 %",
            "b) 30 %",
            "c) 50 %",
            "d) 70 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Material removal rates are reduced by 50 % in the presence of the film in Electro chemical superfinishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 980,
        "Question": "What are the tolerance values obtained in the ECS process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 0.003 mm",
            "b) ± 0.013 mm",
            "c) ± 0.023 mm",
            "d) ± 0.033 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tolerance values obtained in the Electro chemical superfinishing process are about ± 0.013 mm on the diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 981,
        "Question": "What are the values of roundness and straightness obtained from machining using ECS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 mm",
            "b) 0.003 mm",
            "c) 0.007 mm",
            "d) 0.013 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The values of roundness and straightness obtained from machining by Electro chemical superfinishing process is about 0.007 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 982,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the process variables related to ECS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gap voltage",
            "b) Electrolyte type",
            "c) Concentration",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gap voltage, electrolyte type, concentration and temperature are some of the variable related to Electro chemical superfinishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 983,
        "Question": "Which of the following affect the process performance of Mechanical scrubbing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stone pressure",
            "b) Oscillating frequency",
            "c) Amplitude",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stone pressure, oscillating frequency and amplitude affect the mechanical scrubbing in the process of Electro chemical superfinishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 984,
        "Question": "High electro chemical dissolutions occur at which type of current densities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very Low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Moderate",
            "d) High"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High electro chemical dissolutions occur at high current densities in the process of Electro chemical superfinishing."
    },
    {
        "id": 985,
        "Question": "Rise in different parameters related to the MS and ECD lead to ___________ material removal rates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in",
            "b) Decrease in",
            "c) Normal",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A rise in the scrubbing speed, voltage, and duty cycle would lead to an increase in MRR."
    },
    {
        "id": 986,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ECB in the advanced machining processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electro chemical buffing",
            "b) Electro chemical blasting",
            "c) Electron cluster blasting",
            "d) Electron cluster briefing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full form of ECB is Electro chemical buffing in the advanced machining processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 987,
        "Question": "Compared to conventional mechanical buffing Electro chemical buffing is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slower process",
            "b) Faster process",
            "c) Same speed process",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electro chemical buffing process is a faster machining process when compared to the conventional mechanical buffing."
    },
    {
        "id": 988,
        "Question": "Which of the following electrolytes are used ECB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium chloride solution",
            "b) Sodium nitrate solution",
            "c) Sodium chloride & nitrate solution",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sodium chloride and sodium nitrate are the electrolytes that are used for machining purpose in the process of Electro chemical buffing."
    },
    {
        "id": 989,
        "Question": "What can be the concentration of Sodium chloride used in ECB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 0.5 g/L",
            "b) 1 – 5 g/L",
            "c) 10 – 50 g/L",
            "d) 100 – 500 g/L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The concentration of sodium chloride solution used for machining in ECB is about 100 – 500 g/L."
    },
    {
        "id": 990,
        "Question": "What are the values of the current densities used in ECB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01 – 0.7 A/cm2",
            "b) 0.1 – 7 A/cm2",
            "c) 1 – 14 A/cm2",
            "d) 21 – 42 A/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The current densities used in the process of ECB range between 0.1 and 7 A/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 991,
        "Question": "What are the values of buffing speeds used in ECB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 – 0.6 m/s",
            "b) 1 – 6 m/s",
            "c) 10 – 16 m/s",
            "d) 100 – 600 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the buffing speed in Electro chemical buffing is about 1 – 6 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 992,
        "Question": "What are the values of contact pressures used in ECB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 6 g",
            "b) 10 – 60 g",
            "c) 100 – 600 g",
            "d) 1000 – 6000 g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The values of contact pressure used in the ECB process are between 100 and 600 g."
    },
    {
        "id": 993,
        "Question": "What are the values of electrolyte flow rates used in ECB process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 – 10 L/min",
            "b) 10 – 100 L/min",
            "c) 100 – 1000 L/min",
            "d) 1000 – 10000 L/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The values of electrolyte flow rates used in ECB process range between 1 – 10 L/min."
    },
    {
        "id": 994,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors control the polishing speed in the process of ECB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Current density",
            "b) Electrolyte type",
            "c) Work piece material",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors that control the polishing speed are current density, electrolyte time, work piece material."
    },
    {
        "id": 995,
        "Question": "Which of the following electrolytes can be used for high speed polishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium chloride",
            "b) Sodium nitrate",
            "c) Sodium chloride & Sodium nitrate",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sodium chloride electrolyte can be used for high speed polishing in Electro chemical buffing process."
    }
]